<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- UNL Department of Mathematics                                         -->
<!-- Based upon the work of                                                -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Coordinated Calculus.                            -->
<!-- This file is based on Active Calculus.                                -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-3-5-rel-rates" permid="uiS">
  <title>Related Rates</title>
  <objectives permid="ySL">
    <ul permid="jJN">
      <li permid="cfo">
        <p permid="RGj">
          If two quantities that are related,
          such as the radius and volume of a spherical balloon,
          are both changing as implicit functions of time,
          how are their rates of change related?
          That is, how does the relationship between the values of the quantities affect the relationship between their respective derivatives with respect to time?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="eZU">
    <p permid="IWr">
In section <xref ref="sec-3-5-implicit">Section</xref> we have saw that <m>y</m> can be defined implicitly as a function of <m>x</m> and that it was possible to find the rate of change of <m>y</m> with respect to <m>x</m>, that is <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dx}</m>, without explicitly solving for <m>y</m>. It is also possible for both <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> to be defined as implicit functions of time <m>(t)</m>; that is, both variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> implicitly change with time. 
When two variables change in time, it is possible to find the rate of change of one variable given the rate of change of the second variable; these are known as <em>related rates</em>. 
</p>
<p permid="QCD">
We will start  by examining an example without contect to understand the process, then move onto applications in which we use related rates.
</p>
<example xml:id="PA-4-5" permid="wJM">
<statement>
  <p permid="QCD">
Suppose that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are both implicitly functions of time <m>(t)</m> and are related to each other by the equation 
<me>
xy^2+y=x^2+17.
</me>

 We can find the <em> rate of change of y with respect to time</em> <m>(\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt})</m> given <m>x=2</m>, <m>y=3</m> and the <em> rate of change of x with respect to time</em> when <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}=13</m>. Take the implicit time derivative of the equation:
<me>
\frac{d}{dt}\left[xy^2+y=x^2+17\right]=\overbrace{\frac{dx}{dt}y^2+x(2y\frac{dy}{dt})}^{\text{using the product rule}}+\frac{dy}{dt}=2x\frac{dx}{dt}
</me>
Substitute the known values and solve for <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}</m>:
<me> 13 (3)^2+(2)(2(3)\frac{dy}{dt})+\frac{dy}{dt}=4(13)</me>
<me>117+12\frac{dy}{dt}+\frac{dy}{dt}=52</me>
<me>13\frac{dy}{dt}=-65</me>
<me>\frac{dy}{dt}=-5</me>
</p>
</statement>
</example>

</introduction>

  <subsection permid="aqb">
    <title>Related Rates Problems</title>
    <p permid="VkJ">
   In looking at applications of related rates we will start with an application to Buisness. We have seen that we can determine Profit, Revenue, and Cost as functions of the number of items sold <m>(x)</m>; however, it the real world the number of items that are produced and sold is always changing in time. We can apply the idea of related rates to understand how  Profit, Revenue, or Cost change in time given how the number of items changes in time.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-3-1-RevCostProfit" permid="mEt">
      <statement>
        <p permid="QAQ">
Suppose that the revenue, in dollars, from the sale of <m>x</m> items is <m>R(x)=480x-0.4x^2</m>, and the cost, in dollars, of producing <m>x</m> items is <m>C(x)=5000+0.6x^2</m>. Find the rate of change of profit <m>\displaystyle \frac{dP}{dt}</m> when <m>40</m> items are sold <m>(x=40)</m> and the rate of change of units is <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}=30</m> units per day.
</p>
</statement>
      <hint>
      <p>Start by finding the Profit function, then find the implicit time derivative.
      </p>
      </hint>
      <answer>
      <p>
      <m>\displaystyle \frac{dP}{dt}=12000</m> dollars per day.
      </p>
      </answer>
      <solution permid="Lhd">

        <p permid="non">
          We begin by creating the profit function
<me>
P(x)=R(x)-C(x)=(480x-0.4x^2)-(5000+0.6x^2)=480x-x^2-5000.
</me>
Then take the implicit time derivative of the profit function as an implicit equtation
<me>
\frac{d}{dt}\left[P(x)=480x-x^2-5000\right]
</me>
<me>
\frac{dP}{dt}=480\frac{dx}{dt}-2x\frac{dx}{dt}
</me>
Then plug in the values that are given, <m>x=40</m> and <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dx}=30</m>
<me>
\frac{dP}{dt}=480(30)-2(40)(30)=12000
</me>


    </p>
      </solution>
    </example>




    <p permid="pdA">
   Now we want to consider other applications of related rates.  Before we start we will outline a stragety for tackeling these type of problems.
</p>

   <assemblage xml:id="RelatedRates" permid="zJJ">
      <title>Stratigy for Setting up and Solving Related Rates Problems</title>


      <p permid="ktH">
        <ul permid="DCE">
          <li permid="Imx">
            <p permid="xNs">
              Identify the quantities in the problem that are changing and choose clearly defined variable names for them.
              Draw one or more figures that clearly represent the situation.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="otG">
            <p permid="dUB">
              Determine all rates of change that are known or given and identify the rate(s) of change to be found.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="UAP">
            <p permid="KbK">
              Find an equation that relates the variables whose rates of change are known to those variables whose rates of change are to be found.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="AHY">
            <p permid="qiT">
              Differentiate implicitly with respect to <m>t</m> to relate the rates of change of the involved quantities.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="gPh">
            <p permid="Wqc">
              Evaluate the derivatives and variables at the information relevant to the instant at which a certain rate of change is sought.
              Use proper notation to identify when a derivative is being evaluated at a particular instant.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="pdA">

      For example,
      suppose that air is being pumped into a spherical balloon so that its volume increases at a constant rate<!-- of 20 cubic inches per second-->.
      Since the balloon's volume and radius are related,
      we ought to be able to discover how fast the radius is changing
      by knowing how fast the volume is changing.
      <!--We are interested in questions such as:-->
      Can we determine how fast the radius of the balloon is increasing <!--at the moment the balloon's diameter is 12 inches?-->
      when the balloon is a certain size? 
      We explore a scenario of this type in <xref ref="PA-3-5">Example</xref>.
    </p>

<example xml:id="PA-3-5" permid="wJM">
<statement>
  <p permid="QCD">
    A spherical balloon with diameter <m>d</m> is being inflated at a constant rate of 20 cubic inches per second. <!--The following parts of this example will walk you through how to answer these questions: -->
    How fast is the radius of the balloon changing at the instant the balloon's diameter is 12 inches?
    Is the radius changing more rapidly when <m>d = 12</m> or when <m>d = 16</m>?
    Why?
    These questions have been broken up into the following parts to guide you through the 
    solution process.</p>

    <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
          Recall that the volume of a sphere of radius <m>r</m> is <m>V = \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m>.
          Note that in the setting of this problem,
          <em>both</em> <m>V</m> and <m>r</m> are changing as <m>t</m> (time) changes,
          and thus both <m>V</m> and <m>r</m> may be viewed as implicit functions of <m>t</m>,
          with respective derivatives
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m> and <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m>.
          Differentiate both sides of the equation
          <m>V = \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m> with respect to <m>t</m>
          to find a formula for
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m> that depends on both <m>r</m> and <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m>.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
          By differentiating the volume function with respect to <em>time</em>, we have 
          <!--At this point in the problem,
          by differentiating we have-->
          <q>related the rates</q>
          of change of <m>V</m> and <m>r</m>.
          Recall that the problem statement tells us that the balloon is being inflated at a constant <em>rate</em>
          of 20 cubic inches per second.
          Is this rate the value of
          <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m> or <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>?
          Why?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
          Note that when the diameter of the balloon is 12 inches,
          we know the value of the radius.
          <!--In the equation <m>\frac{dV}{dt} = 4\pi r^2 \frac{dr}{dt}</m>,-->
          In the formula you found in (a) for <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>,
          substitute the values we know for the relevant quantities and solve for the remaining unknown quantity.
          How fast is the radius changing at the instant <m>d = 12</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="fLB">
        <p permid="kvu">
          How is the situation different when <m>d = 16</m>?
          When is the radius changing more rapidly,
          when <m>d = 12</m> or when <m>d = 16</m>?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </statement>
  <hint>
      <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
          Remember that we need to apply the chain rule to the right side of the equation to differentiate <m>r</m> with respect to <m>t</m>.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
          Look at the units.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
          Use your answer to part (b) to help fill in all missing information. Only one variable should be left.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="fLB">
        <p permid="kvu">
         Which radius results in a larger rate? Note that this question asks about the rate of change 
         of the radius, not of the volume.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </hint>
    
  <answer>
          <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt}=4\pi r^2\frac{dr}{dt}.</m>
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt}=20</m> cubic inches per second.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
          <m>20=4\pi (6)^2 \frac{dr}{dt},</m> so <m>\frac{dr}{dt}=\frac{5}{36\pi}</m> inches per second when the diameter is 12 inches.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="fLB">
        <p permid="kvu">
          <m>\frac{dr}{dt}=\frac{5}{64\pi}</m> inches per second when the diameter is 16 inches. Thus, the radius is changing more rapidly when the diameter is 12 inches.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
    </answer>
  <solution>
        <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
          Starting with the equation <m>V=\frac{4}{3}\pi r^3</m>, we differentiate both sides with respect to <m>t</m>. We need to use the chain rule to differentiate the right side of the equation since <m>r</m> is really <m>r(t)</m>, a function of <m>t</m>. So, the equation we have is really <m>V(t)=\frac{4}{3}\pi [r(t)]^3</m>. Differentiating with respect to <m>t</m> we have <me>\frac{dV}{dt}=4\pi r^2\frac{dr}{dt}.</me>
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
          Since the units are cubic inches per second, this is a volume rate. So, <m>\frac{dV}{dt}=20</m> cubic inches per second.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
          Since <m>\frac{dV}{dt}=20</m> and <m>r=6</m> when <m>d=12</m>, we have <m>20=4\pi(6)^2\frac{dr}{dt}</m>. So, <m>\frac{dr}{dt}=\frac{5}{36\pi}</m> inches per second.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="fLB">
        <p permid="kvu">
          Doing the same thing as in part (c), we find that <m>\frac{dr}{dt}=\frac{5}{64\pi}</m> inches per second when the diameter is <m>16</m> inches (so <m>r=8</m>). This number is smaller than the one calculated in part (c), so the radius is changing more rapidly when the diameter is <m>12</m> inches.
          Intuitively, this makes sense since the balloon's volume is growing at a constant rate: as the balloon grows, a small change in the radius will have a larger impact on the change in volume; equivalently, the same change in volume corresponds to a smaller change in the radius when the balloon is large.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </solution>
</example>


    <example xml:id="Ex-3-3-Sliddingladder" permid="mEt">
      <statement>
        <p permid="QAQ">
A <m>16</m> foot ladder is placed against a wall.  To visulize this use follow the link: (<url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9o">http://gvsu.edu/s/9o</url>);


    <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
       If the bottom of the ladder moves away from the wall at a constant rate, how would you describe the movement of the top of the ladder?
 
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
Let  <m>x</m> be the distance from the bottom of the wall to the bottom of the ladder, and <m>h</m> be the distance from the bottom of the wall to the top of the ladder, both of these quantities change as a function of time, <m>t</m>.  If the base <m>(x)</m> is increasing, is the rate of change of the height of the ladder on the wall <m>\displaystyle \frac{dh}{dt}</m> positive or negative? 
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
         Suppose the top of the ladder slides down at a constant rate of <m>4</m> feet per second. How fast is the base of the ladder moving when the height is 12 feet.?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>

          </p>

</statement>
     <!-- <hint>
      <p>Use the Pythagorean Thereom.
      </p>
      </hint>-->
      <answer>
      <p>
      The base is moving away from the wall at a rate of <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}=\frac{24}{\sqrt{112}}</m> feet per second.
      </p>
      </answer>
      <solution permid="Lhd">
 <p permid="rZT">
    <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
       As the base of the ladder moves away from the wall at a constant rate, the top of the ladder slides down the wall with a constant rate. 
 
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
The rate of change of the height of the ladder on the wall would be negative, <m>\displaystyle \frac{dh}{dt} \lt 0</m>. This is negative since the height of the ladder on the wall is decreasing.

        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
Here we want <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}</m>, how fast the base of the ladder is moving away from the wall. We know <m>h=12</m> and <m>\displaystyle \frac{dh}{dt}=-4</m>.
</p>
 <p permid="Eol">
We will use the Pythagorean Theorem: <m>x^2+h^2=16^2</m>, first we length of the missing side <m>x</m> by plugging in <m>h=12</m>
<me>
x^2+12^2=16^2 \implies x^2=16^2-12^2 \implies x=\sqrt{16^2-12^2}=\sqrt{112}
</me>
Then we take the implicit time derivative
<me>
\frac{d}{dt}\left[x^2+h^2=16^2\right]
</me>
<me>
2x\frac{dx}{dt}+2h\frac{dh}{dt}=0
</me>
Finally substitute in what is known and solve for <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}</m>
<me>
2(\sqrt{112})\frac{dx}{dt}+2(12)(-4)=0 \implies \frac{dx}{dt}=\frac{24}{\sqrt{112}}
</me>
Thus the base is moving away from the wall at a rate of <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}=\frac{24}{\sqrt{112}}</m> feet per second.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>

          </p>
      </solution>
    </example>



    <example xml:id="Ex-3-4-boat" permid="mEt">
      <statement>
        <p permid="QAQ">
A person is watching a boat sailing parallel to a straight shoreline, shown  below. The boat stays at a constant <m>50</m> feet from the coastline, moving at a rate of <m>10</m> feet per minute. Let <m>y</m> be the distance from the boat to the person.
</p>
<p permid="QAQ">

<figure xml:id="F-1-1-boat" permid="Dxa">
<caption>Boat sailing parallel to a straight shoreline </caption>
<image width="47%" source="images/exam3-graph2a.jpg" />
</figure>


    <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
     Is the rate of change of the distance from the person to the boat, <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}</m> positive or negative? 
 
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Txj">
        <p permid="Yhc">
How fast is the distance <m>y</m>, the distance from the person to the boat, changing the when <m>y=130</m> feet?  
        </p>
      </li>

    </ol>

          </p>

</statement>

      <answer>
      <p>
The distance from the person to the boat is increasing at a rate of <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}=\frac{12}{\sqrt{13}}</m> feet per minute.
      </p>
      </answer>
      <solution permid="Lhd">
 <p permid="rZT">
    <ol label="a." permid="bbI">

      <li permid="nqa">
        <p permid="rZT">
 The rate of change fof the distance from the person to the boat is positive, <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}\gt 0</m>, since the distance is increasing as the boat sails away.
 
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="zEs">
        <p permid="Eol">
Here we want <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}</m>, How fast is the distance <m>y</m>, the distance from the person to the boat, changing.  We know <m>y=130</m> and <m>\displaystyle \frac{dx}{dt}=10</m> feet per minute.
</p>
 <p permid="Eol">
We will use the Pythagorean Theorem: <m>x^2+50^2=y^2</m>. Note that now the <m>y</m> is the hypotenuse and it is varying!  First we length of the missing side <m>x</m> by plugging in <m>y=12</m>
<me>
x^2+50^2=130^2 \implies x^2=130^2-50^2 \implies x=\sqrt{130^2-50^2}=120
</me>
Then we take the implicit time derivative
<me>
\frac{d}{dt}\left[x^2+50^2=y^2\right]
</me>
<me>
2x\frac{dx}{dt}+0=2y\frac{dy}{dt}
</me>
Finally substitute in what is known and solve for <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}</m>
<me>
2(120)(10)=2(130)\frac{dy}{dt} \implies \frac{dy}{dt}=\frac{120}{\sqrt{130}}
</me>
The distance from the person to the boat is increasing at a rate of <m>\displaystyle \frac{dy}{dt}=\frac{12}{\sqrt{13}}</m> feet per minute.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>

          </p>
      </solution>
    </example>



<example xml:id="act-3-5-3" permid="dfm">
  <statement>
    <p permid="ECC">
      As pictured in the applet at<nbsp /><url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9q">http://gvsu.edu/s/9q</url>,
      a skateboarder who is 6 feet tall (while on the skateboard) rides under a 15 foot tall lamppost at a constant rate of 3 feet per second.
      We are interested in understanding how fast the length of his shadow is changing at various points in time.

      <ol label="a." permid="dAL">
        <li permid="JHU">
          <p permid="AYc">
            Draw an appropriate right triangle that represents a snapshot in time of the skateboarder,
            lamppost,
            and his shadow.
            Let <m>x</m> denote the horizontal distance from the base of the lamppost to the skateboarder and <m>s</m> represent the length of his shadow.
            Label these quantities,
            as well as the skateboarder's height and the lamppost's height on the diagram.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="pPd">
          <p permid="hfl">
            Observe that the skateboarder and the lamppost represent parallel line segments in the diagram,
            and thus similar triangles are present.
            Use similar triangles to establish an equation that relates <m>x</m> and <m>s</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="VWm">
          <p permid="Nmu">
            Use your work in (b) to find an equation that relates
            <m>\frac{dx}{dt}</m> and <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Cdv">
          <p permid="ttD">
            At what rate is the length of the skateboarder's shadow increasing at the instant the skateboarder is 8 feet from the lamppost?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ikE">
          <p permid="ZAM">
            As the skateboarder's distance from the lamppost increases,
            is his shadow's length increasing at an increasing rate,
            increasing at a decreasing rate,
            or increasing at a constant rate?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="OrN">
          <p permid="FHV">
            Which is moving more rapidly:
            the skateboarder or the tip of his shadow?
            Explain, and justify your answer.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="EYb">
    <p permid="Yvt">
      <ol label="a." permid="xtC">
        <li permid="uyW">
          <p permid="lPe">
            Note that the lengths of the legs of the right triangle will be <m>15</m> for the vertical one and <m>x + s</m> for the horizontal one.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="aGf">
          <p permid="RWn">
            The small triangle formed by the skateboarder and his shadow,
            with legs <m>6</m> and <m>s</m>, is similar to the large triangle that has the lamppost as one of its legs.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="GNo">
          <p permid="ydw">
            Simplify the equation in (b) as much as possible before differentiating implicitly with respect to <m>t</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="mUx">
          <p permid="ekF">
            Find <m>\left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x=8}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="TbG">
          <p permid="KrO">
            Does the equation that relates
            <m>\frac{dx}{dt}</m> and <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m> involve <m>x</m>?
            Is <m>\frac{dx}{dt}</m> changing or constant?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ziP">
          <p permid="qyX">
            Let <m>y</m> represent the location of the tip of the shadow,
            so that <m>y = x + s</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="YQS">
    <p permid="sok">
      <ol label="a." permid="Rmt">
        <li permid="fpY">

          <sidebyside width="40%" permid="QQU">
            <image source="images/3_5_Act3Soln" />
          </sidebyside>

        </li>

        <li permid="Lxh">
          <p permid="WGg">
            <m>3s = 2x</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="rEq">
          <p permid="CNp">
            <m>3 \frac{ds}{dt} = 2\frac{dx}{dt}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="XLz">
          <p permid="iUy">
            <m>\left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x=8} = 2</m> feet per second.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="DSI">
          <p permid="PbH">
            The shadow length increases at a constant rate.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="jZR">
          <p permid="viQ">
            The tip of the shadow is moving at a rate of <m>5</m> ft/sec.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="sJJ">
    <p permid="Mhb">
      <ol label="a." permid="lfk">
        <li permid="Qha">
          <p permid="bpZ">
            The given information leads us to construct the following diagram:
          </p>

          <sidebyside width="40%" permid="wYd">
            <image source="images/3_5_Act3Soln" />
          </sidebyside>

        </li>

        <li permid="woj">
          <p permid="Hxi">
            The two right triangles shown in the diagram in (a) are similar: 
            the small triangle is formed by the skateboarder and his shadow, and has legs of length <m>6</m> and <m>s</m>; 
            the large triangle is formed by the lampost and the distance from the post to the shadow's tip, and has legs of length <m>15</m> and <m>x+s</m>. 
            Similarity gives us that the ratios of leg lengths are equal, so we have
            <me permid="kJL">
              \frac{s}{6} = \frac{s+x}{15}
            </me>.
            Simplifying yields <m>15s = 6s + 6x</m>,
            or <me>3s = 2x</me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="cvs">
          <p permid="nEr">
            Differentiating with respect to <m>t</m>,
            it is immediate that <me>3 \frac{ds}{dt} = 2\frac{dx}{dt}</me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ICB">
          <p permid="TLA">
            Since <m>\frac{ds}{dt} = \frac{2}{3} \frac{dx}{dt}</m>,
            and <m>\frac{dx}{dt} = 3</m>,
            it follows that <m>\frac{ds}{dt} = 2</m> for every value of <m>t</m>
            (and <m>x</m>).
            Thus,
            <m>\left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x=8} = 2</m> feet per second.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="oJK">
          <p permid="zSJ">
            Because <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m> is constant,
            the shadow's length is increasing at a constant rate
            (irrespective of the distance from the skateboarder to the lamppost).
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="UQT">
          <p permid="fZS">
            Let <m>y</m> represent the location of the tip of the shadow,
            so that <m>y = x + s</m>.
            Observe that we can now compute <m>\frac{dy}{dt}</m> in terms of
            <m>\frac{dx}{dt}</m> and <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m>,
            with <me>\frac{dy}{dt} = \frac{dx}{dt} + \frac{ds}{dt} = 3 + 2 = 5</me> feet per second,
            and hence the tip of the shadow is moving more rapidly than the skateboarder himself.
          </p>
          <p>
            Even though the shadow's length is growing slower than the skateboarder is moving, the tip of the shadow 
            is moving both due to growth and due to the skateboarder's movement, giving us the faster rate.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

    <p permid="KLE">
      <!--In the first three examples of this section,-->
      In most of the examples thus far,
      we provided guided instruction to build a solution in a step-by-step way.
      For the closing example and the following exercises,
      most of the detailed work is left to the reader.
    </p>

<example xml:id="act-3-5-4" permid="MQV">
  <statement>
    <p permid="riR">
      A baseball diamond is square and measures <m>90</m> feet on each side.
      A batter hits a ball along the third base line and runs to first base.
      At what rate is the distance between the ball and first base changing when the ball is halfway to third base,
      if at that instant the ball is traveling <m>100</m> feet/sec?
      At what rate is the distance between the ball and the runner changing at the same instant,
      if the runner is at that point one-eigth of the way to first base and running at <m>30</m> feet/sec?
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="VAN">
    <p permid="LbI">
      Draw some pictures! Label everything you know with a constant, and everything that is changing with a variable and a corresponding rate of change (with respect to time, <m>t</m>). 
      For the instant in question, you will also want to write down the values of the variables at that instant and identify what quantities you need to find.
      <!--Let <m>x</m> denote the position of the ball along the third base line at time <m>t</m>,
      and <m>z</m> the distance from the ball to first base.-->
      Note that the basepaths meet at right angles.
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="ptE">
    <p permid="myY">
      Let <m>x</m> denote the position of the ball (as a distance from home plate) at time <m>t</m> and <m>z</m> the distance from the ball to first base,
      as pictured below.
    </p>

    <sidebyside width="50%" permid="ool">
      <image source="images/3_5_Act4Soln1" />
    </sidebyside>

    <p permid="SGh">
      <me> \left. \frac{dz}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = \frac{100}{\sqrt{5}} \approx 44.7214 \ \text{ft/sec} </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="yNq">
      Let <m>r</m> be the runner's position (as a distance from home plate) at time <m>t</m> and let <m>s</m> be the distance between the runner and the ball,
      as pictured.
    </p>

    <sidebyside width="50%" permid="Uvu">
      <image source="images/3_5_Act4Soln2" />
    </sidebyside>

    <p permid="eUz">
      <me> \left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = \frac{430}{\sqrt{17}} \approx 104.2903 \ \text{ft/sec} </me>.
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="Jmv">
    <p permid="BHW">
      We let <m>x</m> denote the position of the ball (as a distance from home plate) at time <m>t</m> and <m>z</m> the distance from the ball to first base,
      as pictured below.
    </p>

    <sidebyside width="50%" permid="ACD">
      <image source="images/3_5_Act4Soln1" />
    </sidebyside>

    <p permid="hPf">
      By the Pythagorean Theorem, we know that <m>x^2 + 90^2 = z^2</m>;
      differentiating with respect to <m>t</m>, we have
      <me permid="Xqa">
        2x\frac{dx}{dt} = 2z\frac{dz}{dt}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="NWo">
      At the instant the ball is halfway to third base,
      we know <m>x = 45</m> and <m>\left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = 100</m>.
      Moreover, by Pythagoras,
      <m>z^2 = 90^2 + 45^2</m>, so <m>z = 45\sqrt{5}</m>.
      Thus,
      <md>
      <mrow>\left.\frac{dz}{dt}\right|_{x=45}=\mathstrut\amp\left.\left(\frac xz\frac{dx}{dt}\right)\right|_{x=45}</mrow>
      <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp\frac{45}{45\sqrt5}(100)</mrow>
      <mrow>\approx\mathstrut\amp44.7214 \ \text{ft/sec}</mrow>
      </md>.
      Therefore, the distance between the ball and first base is at this instant growing at a rate of about 
      <m>44.72</m> feet per second.
      <!--<me permid="Dxj">
        2 \cdot 45 \cdot 100 = 2 \cdot 45 \sqrt{5} \cdot \left. \frac{dz}{dt} \right|_{x = 45}
      </me>,
      so
      <me permid="jEs">
        \left. \frac{dz}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = \frac{100}{\sqrt{5}} \approx 44.7214 \ \text{feet/sec}
      </me>.-->
    </p>

    <p permid="udx">
      For the second question,
      we still let <m>x</m> represent the ball's position at time <m>t</m>,
      but now we introduce <m>r</m> as the runner's position (also as a distance from home plate) at time <m>t</m> and let <m>s</m> be the distance between the runner and the ball.
      In this setting, as seen in the diagram below,
      <m>x</m>, <m>r</m>,
      and <m>s</m> form the sides of a right triangle, so that
      <men xml:id="baseballPT" permid="PLB">
        x^2 + r^2 = s^2
      </men>,
      by the Pythagorean Theorem.
    </p>

    <sidebyside width="50%" permid="gJM">
      <image source="images/3_5_Act4Soln2" />
    </sidebyside>

    <p permid="akG">
      Differentiating each side of Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="baseballPT" /> with respect to <m>t</m>,
      it follows that the three rates of change are related by the equation
      <me permid="vSK">
        2x \frac{dx}{dt} + 2r \frac{dr}{dt} = 2s \frac{ds}{dt}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="GrP">
      We are given that at the instant <m>x = 45</m>, <m>r = \frac{90}{8}=\frac{45}4</m>,
      so by Pythagoras, <m>s = \frac{45}{4}\sqrt{17}</m>.
      In addition, at this same instant we know that
      <m>\left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = 100</m> and <m>\left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = 30</m>.
      Applying this information, we end up with 
      <md>
      <mrow>\left.\frac{ds}{dt}\right|_{x=45}=\mathstrut\amp\left.\left(\frac xs\frac{dx}{dt}+\frac rs\frac{dr}{dt}\right)\right|_{x=45}</mrow>
      <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp\frac{45}{\big(\frac{45}4\sqrt{17}\big)}(100)+\frac{\big(\frac{45}4\big)}{\big(\frac{45}4\sqrt{17}\big)}(30)</mrow>
      <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp\frac{400}{\sqrt{17}}+\frac{30}{\sqrt{17}}</mrow>
      <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp\frac{430}{\sqrt{17}}</mrow>
      <mrow>\approx\mathstrut\amp104.2903 \ \text{ft/sec}</mrow>
      </md>.
      Therefore, the distance between the ball and the runner is at this instant increasing 
      at a rate of about <m>104.29</m> feet per second.
      <!--<me permid="bZT">
        2 \cdot 45 \cdot 100 + 2 \cdot \frac{45}{4} \cdot 30 = 2 \cdot \frac{45}{4}\sqrt{17} \cdot \left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x = 45}
      </me>
      and therefore
      <me permid="Ihc">
        \left. \frac{ds}{dt} \right|_{x = 45} = \frac{430}{\sqrt{17}} \approx 104.2903 \ \text{feet/sec}
      </me>.-->
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="Gxk">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="qSN">
      <ul permid="vYf">
        <li permid="lza">
          <p permid="aZV">
            When two or more related quantities are changing as implicit functions of time,
            their rates of change can be related by implicitly differentiating the equation that relates the quantities themselves.
            For instance,
            if the sides of a right triangle are all changing as functions of time,
            say having lengths <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>,
            then these quantities are related by the Pythagorean Theorem:
            <m>x^2 + y^2 = z^2</m>.
            It follows by implicitly differentiating with respect to <m>t</m> that their rates are related by the equation
            <me permid="sIa">
              2x \frac{dx}{dt} + 2y\frac{dy}{dt} = 2z \frac{dz}{dt}
            </me>,
            so that if we know the values of <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>,
            and <m>z</m> at a particular time,
            as well as two of the three rates,
            we can deduce the value of the third.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"> 
  <!-- Uses EV2 so not compatible with PTX -->
  <!--
  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/csuf_dr_8_1.pg" />
  </exercise>
  -->
  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW2" permid="cjo">
    <title>Height of a conical pile of gravel</title>
    <webwork source="Library/270/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/s2_8_21.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW3" permid="Iqx">
    <title>Movement of a shadow</title>
    <webwork source="Library/270/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/s2_8_7.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW4" permid="oxG">
    <title>A leaking conical tank</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/c2s8p3.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="UEP">
  <title>Docking a boat</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="Eqy">
        A sailboat is sitting at rest near its dock.
        A rope attached to the bow of the boat is drawn in over a pulley that stands on a post on the end of the dock that is 5 feet higher than the bow.
        If the rope is being pulled in at a rate of 2 feet per second,
        how fast is the boat approaching the dock when the length of rope from bow to pulley is 13 feet?
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="ZoI">
      <p permid="fNO">
        The boat is approaching the dock at a rate of <m>\frac{13}{6} \approx 2.167</m> feet per second.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="thz">
      <p permid="qmT">
        Using the given information, we construct the figure shown below.
      </p>

      <sidebyside permid="jNN">
        <image source="images/3_5_Ez1Soln" />
      </sidebyside>

      <p permid="Wuc">
        As pictured,
        we know that <m>5</m> is the vertical height from the pulley to the level of the bow of the boat,
        and we let <m>z</m> be the length of the rope from the pulley to the bow of the boat,
        and <m>x</m> the horizontal distance from the dock to the bow of the boat.
      </p>

      <p permid="CBl">
        We are given that the rope is being pulled in at <m>2</m> feet per second,
        and thus <m>\frac{dz}{dt} = -2</m> feet per second.
        Because we want to know how fast the boat is approaching the dock when the length of rope from bow to pulley is 13 feet,
        we want to know <m>\left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{z=13}</m>.
        Thus, we need to relate the changing quantities <m>z</m> and <m>x</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="iIu">
        Because the rope, the post
        (vertically extended),
        and the horizontal distance from the bow of the boat to the post on the dock form a right triangle at all times,
        it follows that
        <me permid="phA">
          x^2 + 5^2 = z^2
        </me>.
        Having now related <m>z</m> and <m>x</m>,
        we differentiate this equation with respect to <m>t</m>.
        By the chain rule, we now see that
        <me permid="VoJ">
          2x \frac{dx}{dt} = 2z \frac{dz}{dt}
        </me>.
        At the instant <m>z = 13</m>,
        <m>x^2 + 5^2 = 13^2</m>, and thus <m>x = 12</m>.
        Using all of the given information at the instant <m>z = 13</m> (including that <m>\frac{dz}{dt} = -2</m>),
        <me permid="BvS">
          2(12) \left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{z = 13} = 2(13)(-2)
        </me>.
        Solving for <m>\left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{z = 13}</m>,
        <me permid="hDb">
          \left. \frac{dx}{dt} \right|_{z = 13} = -\frac{13}{6}
        </me>
        feet per second.
        Thus the boat is approaching the dock at a rate of <m>\frac{13}{6} \approx 2.167</m> feet per second.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-pool" permid="ALY">
  <title>Filling a swimming pool</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="kxH">
        A swimming pool is <m>60</m> feet long and <m>25</m> feet wide.
        Its depth varies uniformly from <m>3</m> feet at the shallow end to <m>15</m> feet at the deep end,
        as shown in the <xref ref="F-3-5-Ez3">Figure</xref>.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-3-5-Ez3" permid="wLZ">
        <caption>The swimming pool.</caption>
        <image width="50%" source="images/3_5_Ez3" />
      </figure>

      <p permid="QEQ">
        Suppose the pool has been emptied and is now being filled with water at a rate of <m>800</m> cubic feet per minute.
        At what rate is the depth of water
        (measured at the deepest point of the pool)
        increasing when it is <m>5</m> feet deep at that end?
        Over time, describe how the depth of the water will increase:
        at an increasing rate, at a decreasing rate, or at a constant rate.
        Explain.
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="lDa">
      <p permid="LUX">
        The depth of the water is increasing at
        <me permid="NKk">
          \left. \frac{dh}{dt}\right|_{h = 5} = 1.28
        </me>
        feet per minute.
        The depth of the water is increasing at a decreasing rate.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="FvR">
      <p permid="OPD">
        The variables in this problem are the volume <m>V</m> of water in the pool and the depth <m>y</m> of water in the pool (measured at the deepest point of the pool);
        each is implicitly a function of time, <m>t</m>.
        We are given that <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m> is a constant <m>800</m> cubic feet per minute and want to find <m>\frac{dh}{dt}\bigm|_{h=5}</m>.
        To do this, we first need to relate <m>V</m> and <m>h</m>.
        The volume of the water in the pool at height
        <m>h \lt 12</m> is the volume of the triangular cross sectional area of height <m>h</m>
        (as shown in the figure below)
        times the width (25 feet) of the pool.
        The height of the triangular cross section is <m>h</m> and the length is distance of the dotted line indicated in the figure.
      </p>

      <sidebyside width="65%" permid="PUW">
        <image source="images/3_5_Ez2Soln" />
      </sidebyside>

      <p permid="uWM">
        Placing the cross section on a coordinate system as in the figure,
        the hypotenuse of the triangle is the line connecting the points <m>(0,-15)</m> and <m>(60, -3)</m>.
        This line has slope <m>\frac{12}{60} = 0.2</m> and <m>y</m>-intercept <m>(0,-15)</m>.
        So the equation of this line is <m>y = 0.2x-15</m>.
        It is the <m>x</m> coordinate of the point on this line corresponding to the <m>y</m>-coordinate <m>h-15</m> that is the length of the triangle whose height is <m>h</m>.
        So the length <m>l</m> is <m>l = \frac{(h-15)+15}{0.2} = 5h</m>.
        Thus, the volume of water in the pool at height <m>h</m> is
        <me permid="tRt">
          V = \left(\frac{1}{2}(h)(5h)\right)(25) = 62.5h^2
        </me>.
        Both <m>V</m> and <m>h</m> are functions of time.
        Differentiating both sides of the equation with respect to  <m>t</m> gives
        <me permid="ZYC">
          \frac{dV}{dt} = 62.5(2h) \frac{dh}{dt}
        </me>,
        so
        <me permid="GfL">
          \frac{dh}{dt} = \frac{1}{125h} \frac{dV}{dt}
        </me>.
        When the depth of water in the pool is <m>5</m> feet,
        then the depth is increasing at the rate
        <me permid="mmU">
          \left. \frac{dh}{dt}\right|_{h = 5} = \frac{1}{125(5)} (800) = 1.28
        </me>
        feet per minute.
        Since <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m> is inversely proportional to <m>h</m>,
        the rate at which the depth of the water increases slows as <m>h</m> increases,
        so the depth of the water is increasing at a decreasing rate.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="gTh">
  <title>Baseball player and umpire</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="cTi">
        A baseball diamond is a square with sides <m>90</m> feet long.
        Suppose a baseball player is advancing from second to third base at the rate of <m>24</m> feet per second,
        and an umpire is standing on home plate.
        Let <m>\theta</m> be the angle between the third baseline and the line of sight from the umpire to the runner.
        How fast is <m>\theta</m> changing when the runner is <m>30</m> feet from third base?
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="xRs">
      <p permid="scg">
        <m>
        \left. \frac{d\theta}{dt} \right|_{x = 30} = -0.24
        </m>
        radians per second.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="RKj">
      <p permid="bdV">
        Let <m>x</m> represent the distance from the runner to third base along the path from second to third,
        let <m>z</m> be the distance from the umpire at home plate to the runner,
        and call <m>\theta</m> the angle between the third baseline and the line of sight from the umpire to the runner.
        See the figure below.
      </p>

      <sidebyside permid="wcf">
        <image source="images/3_5_Ez3Soln" />
      </sidebyside>

      <p permid="Hle">
        Each of <m>x</m>, <m>z</m>,
        and <m>\theta</m> is implicitly a function of <m>t</m>.
        We are given that the runner is advancing at a rate of <m>24</m> feet per second,
        so <m>\frac{dx}{dt} = -24</m>.
        Since we want to know <m>\left. \frac{d\theta}{dt} \right|_{x = 30}</m>,
        we want to relate <m>x</m> and <m>\theta</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="nsn">
        We first observe that by definition,
        <me permid="Sud">
          \tan(\theta) = \frac{x}{90} = \frac{1}{90}x
        </me>.
        Having related <m>x</m> and <m>\theta</m>,
        we can differentiate both sides of the preceding equation with respect  to <m>t</m>.
        By the chain rule,
        <me permid="yBm">
          \sec^2 (\theta) \frac{d\theta}{dt} = \frac{1}{90} \frac{dx}{dt}
        </me>,
        and thus
        <me permid="eIv">
          \frac{d\theta}{dt} = \frac{1}{90 \sec^2 (\theta)} \frac{dx}{dt}
        </me>
        At the instant <m>x = 30</m>,
        since <m>x^2 + 90^2 = z^2</m>,
        <m>z = \sqrt{90^2 + 30^2} = \sqrt{9000} = 30\sqrt{10}</m>.
        Hence, at this same instance,
        <m>\sec(\theta) = \frac{1}{\cos(\theta)} = \frac{30\sqrt{10}}{90} = \frac{\sqrt{10}}{3}</m>.
        Recall we also know that <m>\frac{dx}{dt} = -24</m>.
        Applying this information to the equation that relates the rates of change of <m>x</m> and <m>\theta</m>,
        <me permid="KPE">
          \left. \frac{d\theta}{dt} \right|_{x = 30} = \frac{1}{90 \left( \frac{\sqrt{10}}{3} \right)^2} (-24) = -\frac{1}{100}(24) = -0.24
        </me>
        radians per second.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

 </exercises>
</section>

