<!--Section Conic Sections-->

<section xml:id='Conic-Sections'>

<title>Conic Sections</title>

<introduction>

<p> </p>

<p>
	We've been working with the <term>unit circle</term> for quite some time, exploring the relationship between points on the unit circle, the angle made by the line which connects a point on the unit circle to the origin, and the trigonometric function (e.g. sine and cosine) values of said angle.
</p>

<p>
	The unit circle was simply defined to be the circle with radius <m>1</m> centered at the origin. In this section, we use that definition, along with our knowledge of transformations of functions and their associated graphs, to explore other important geometric shapes.
</p>

</introduction>

<subsection><title>The Unit Circle Revisited</title>

<p> </p>

<p>
	One way of defining the unit circle is via <term>geometry</term>, the collection of all points that are a distance of one unit from the origin.
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	There are also other (equivalent) ways of defining the unit circle. For example, it may be advantageous to define the unit circle <term>analytically</term>, that is, using a formula relating variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>. This can be done, and you may have seen the formula before - the unit circle is the collection of all points with <m>(x,y)</m>-coordinates which satisfy the equation
</p>

\begin{equation}\label{eq:unit-circle-formula}
x^2 + y^2 = 1.
\end{equation}

<p>
	Think about an arbitrary point in the first quadrant of the unit circle:
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	For any such point, we can draw a right triangle whose legs have lengths <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>, as depicted in the picture above. The hypotenuse of the triangle is a line connecting the arbitrary point on the circle, <m>(x,y)</m>, to the origin, so its length must be <m>1</m> (as in the definition of the unit circle, the collection of all points a distance of <m>1</m> from the origin).
</p>

<p>
	What does the Pythagorean Theorem tell us about the relationship among the side lengths of this right triangle? They Pythagorean Theorem says that the sum of the squares of the lengths of the legs is equal to the square of the length of the hypotenuse, i.e.
\[
{\color{Red}x}^2 + {\color{Magenta}y}^2 = {\color{OliveGreen}1}^2.
\]
	This aligns perfectly with the formula \eqref{eq:unt-circle-formula}, confirming that our ``different ways of representing a circle" are in alignment.
</p>

<p>
	However, we should be a little careful - what about points on the unit circle that are <alert>not</alert> in the first quadrant?
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	In the picture above, the numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are both <em>positive</em>, since they represent side lengths of a triangle. We know by the Pythagorean Theorem that
	\begin{equation}\label{eq:second-quad}
	a^2 + b^2 = 1^2
	\end{equation}
	Since <m>(x,y)</m> is in the second quadrant, the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the point <m>(x,y)</m> is positive, and is equal to the length <m>b</m>. However, the <m>x</m>-coordinate is negative, so it cannot be equal to the value <m>a</m>! The <m>x</m>-coordinate is a (positive) distance of <m>a</m> units to the left of the origin, which means that <m>x=-a</m>. Knowing that <m>x=-a</m> (which means <m>a=-x</m>) and <m>y=b</m>, the formula \eqref{eq:second-quad} turns into
	\begin{align*}
	(-x)^2 \amp+ (y)^2 = 1 \\
	x^2 \amp+ y^2 = 1,
	\end{align*}
	all because <m>(-x)^2=(-x)\cdot(-x)=(-1)^2\cdot x^2=x^2</m>. Even though the <m>x</m>-coordinate is negative, the `squared" term makes the negative sign disappear, and we confirm that the point on the circle satisfies the equation <m>x^2+y^2=1</m>.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Other Circles in the Plane</title>

<introduction>

<p>
	In this section, we consider circles in the plane other than the unit circle. For example, we should be able to come up with a formula to describe the following circle.
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	Notice that this circle neither has radius <m>1</m>, nor is it centered at the origin. Nonetheless, our knowledge of the unit circle, combined with what we know about general transformations of functions, will be useful for determining formulae to describe general circles in the plane.
</p>

</introduction>

<subsubsection><title>Different Radii</title>

<p>
	As a starting point, let's consider a circle centered at the origin (just like the unit circle) but which has a radius not equal to <m>1</m>.
</p>

<p>
	Figure X below depicts a general circle with radius <m>r</m> (where <m>r</m> is some positive real number) centered at the origin, and Figure X next to it shows a useful right triangle associated with an arbitrary point <m>(x,y)</m> on the circle with radius <m>r</m> - a right triangle that should look familiar from our work with the unit circle earlier in this section.
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	On the unit circle, the hypotenuse of this right triangle was always <m>1</m>, but for <m>(x,y)</m> coordinates on a circle of radius <m>r</m>, the hypotenuse of the right triangle equals <m>r</m>. The Pythagorean Theorem tells us that the quantities <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>r</m> are related via
	\begin{equation}\label{eq:r-circle-formula}
	x^2 + y^2 = r^2
	\end{equation}
</p>

<p>
	Although we have looked at a point <m>(x,y)</m> in the first quadrant, formula \eqref{eq:r-circle-formula} holds for points in any quadrant on the circle of radius <m>r</m> centered at the origin (by the same reasoning as was used for the unit circle previously). We summarize this important formula for circles of arbitrary radius as follows:
</p>

<assemblage>
	<p>
		A <term>circle of radius <m>r</m> centered at the origin</term> is the collection of all points which satisfy the equation
		\[
		x^2 + y^2 = r^2
		\]
	</p>
</assemblage>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>Not Centered at the Origin</title>

<p>
	We will use our knowledge of transformations of functions (see Section X) to come up with formulae for circles not centered at the origin.
</p>

<p>
	First, let's suppose we would like a formula for the circle of radius <m>4</m> centered at the point <m>(7,0)</m>.
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	The lighter red circle in Figure X is centered at the origin, so we know a formula for the points on this circle:
	\begin{equation}\label{eq:circle-origin-rad4}
  {\color{red} x^2 + y^2 = 16}
	\end{equation}
</p>

<p>
	The blue circle in Figure X, the circle of radius <m>4</m> which is centered at the point <m>(7,0)</m>, looks identical to the circle whose equation is given by \eqref{eq:circle-origin-rad4}, just shifted <m>7</m> units to the right. Our knowledge of transformations of functions tells us that their formulae look very similar, but to shift <m>7</m> units to the <em>right</em>, replace each variable "<m>x</m>" in the formula with "<m>x-7</m>", which gives the formula for the circle of radius <m>4</m> centered <m>(7,0)</m>:
	\begin{equation}\label{eq:circle-7_0-rad4}
	{\color{blue} (x-7)^2 + y^2 = 16}
	\end{equation}
</p>

<p>
	We would also like to know what happens to the formula for a circle if it is shifted vertically. Vertical transformations are covered in Section X, but in a slightly different context. Section X dealt only with <em>explicit</em> functions, that is, functions we could write in the form "<m>y=f(x)</m>" (where the variable <m>y</m> is isolated all by itself on one side of the equals sign). The formula for the points on a circle, however, is known as an <em>implicit</em> function because we cannot solve for <m>y</m> on its own without changing or losing some information about the formula. In this instance, we'll treat vertical shifts just like we handled horizontal shifts, but we change the <m>y</m> variable instead of the <m>x</m> variable.
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	Specifically, if we would like to write down an equation for the circle of radius <m>4</m> centered at the point <m>(7,3)</m>, we can make note that this circle is the same as the circle of radius <m>4</m> centered at the point <m>(7,0)</m> shifted up by <m>3</m> units (see Figure X). Since we are shifting <m>3</m> units upward from the circle represented by formula \eqref{eq:circle-7_0-rad4}, we replace each instance of "<m>y</m>" with "<m>y-3</m>" to obtain the formula for the circle of radius <m>4</m> centered at <m>(7,3)</m>:
	\[
	(x-7)^2 + (y-3)^2 = 16
	\]
</p>

<p>
	The preceding examples generalize to the following result regarding formulae for circles not centered at the origin:
</p>

<assemblage>
	<p>
		A <term>circle of radius <m>r</m> centered at the point <m>(h,k)</m></term> is the collection of all points which satisfy the equation
		\[
		(x-h)^2 + (y-k)^2 = r^2
		\]
	</p>
</assemblage>

<p>
	Note that the definition above works if <m>h</m> or <m>k</m> (or both) is negative. For example, the circle of radius <m>15</m> centered at the point <m>(-5,-19)</m> would be represented by the equation
	\[
	(x-(-5))^2 + (y-(-19))^2 = 15^2,
	\]
	which would be simplified to give a more clean formula that represents the circle:
	\[
	(x+5)^2 + (y+19)^2 = 225.
	\]
</p>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Ellipses</title>

<p>
	If we take the unit circle and stretch it both vertically and horizontally by exactly the same amount, we end up with a larger circle (that is, a circle with a radius greater than <m>1</m>). However, we may choose to stretch the unit circle both vertically and horizontally by different factors, and this results in an {\bf ellipse}.
</p>

<p>
	See an example below, where we take the unit circle and stretch it horizontally by a factor of <m>5</m> and vertically by a factor of <m>3</m>:
</p>

<p>INSERT GRAPHIC</p>

<p>
	Let's build a formula for this ellipse by again using our knowledge of transformations of functions with the equation of the unit circle, <m>x^2+y^2=1</m>.
</p>

<p>
	First, let's consider how the formula must be adjusted to stretch the graph horizontally by a factor of <m>5</m>. In order to {\it stretch} horizontally, we need to replace each instance of "<m>x</m>" in the formula with "<m>\frac{1}{5}x</m>". This is not so intuitive, since we want to stretch the graph by a factor of <m>5</m>, but we multiply each <m>x</m> term by a number smaller than <m>1</m>. Nonetheless, as outlined in Section X, multiplying each <m>x</m> term by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{5}</m> has the result of stretching the graph horizontally by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{\sfrac{1}{5}}</m>, which is equal to <m>5</m>, as desired.
</p>

<p>
	Because the formula for the unit circle is an <em>implicit</em> formula, we treat our vertical stretch similarly, accomplishing stretching the graph vertically by a factor of <m>3</m> by replacing each instance of "<m>y</m>" in the formula with "<m>\frac{1}{3}y</m>". Thus, the formula that represents the ellipse depicted in Figure X is given by:
	\begin{equation}\label{eq:ellipse-origin-5_3}
	\left( \frac{1}{5} x \right)^2 + \left( \frac{1}{3} y \right)^2 \amp= 1.
	\end{equation}
	Note the very careful use of parentheses. In the formula for the unit circle, <m>x^2+y^2=1</m>, each variable <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> is being squared. If we wish to replace, say, each instance of the variable <m>x</m> with the expression "<m>\frac{1}{5}x</m>", we must add parentheses to make sure that order of operations is followed appropriately (with <m>\frac{1}{5}</m> multiplying <m>x</m> first, then squaring the result).
</p>

<p>
	Although formula \eqref{eq:ellipse-origin-5_3} perfectly captures the collection of all points that lie on the ellipse depicted in Figure X, it is helpful to do some algebra to obtain another presentation of the formula:
	\begin{align*}
	\left( \frac{1}{5} x \right)^2 + \left( \frac{1}{3} y \right)^2 \amp= 1 \\
	\left( \frac{x}{5} \right)^2 + \left( \frac{y}{3} \right)^2 \amp= 1 \\
	\frac{x^2}{5^2} + \frac{y^2}{3^2} \amp= 1
	\end{align*}
</p>

<p>
	Thus, the ellipse centered at the origin which is obtained by stretching the unit circle horizontally by a factor of <m>{\color{red}5}</m> and vertically by a factor of <m>{\color{blue}3}</m> is precisely the collection of <m>(x,y)</m>-coordinates which satisfy the equation
	\[
	\frac{x^2}{{\color{red}5}^2} + \frac{y^2}{{\color{blue}3}^2} = 1.
	\]
</p>

<p>
	The horizontal and vertical stretch factors used in the previous example could be taken to be any constants, and the result is summarized as follows:
</p>

<assemblage>
	<p>
		The general equation of an <term>ellipse centered at the origin</term> is the collection of all points which satisfy the equation
		\[
		\frac{x^2}{a^2} + \frac{y^2}{b^2} = 1,
		\]
		where the ellipse is obtained by stretching the unit circle by a factor of <m>a</m> in the horizontal direction and a factor of <m>b</m> in the vertical direction.
	</p>
</assemblage>

<p>
	We conclude this section with one final important result about ellipses not centered at the origin. See the formula below which represents a general ellipse centered at any point <m>(h,k)</m>, generated using the same reasoning as was justified above for a general circle not centered at the origin.
</p>

<assemblage>
	<p>
		The general equation of an <term>ellipse centered at the point <m>(h,k)</m></term> is the collection of all points which satisfy the equation
		\[
		\frac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} + \frac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} = 1,
		\]
		where the ellipse is obtained by stretching the unit circle by a factor of <m>a</m> in the horizontal direction and a factor of <m>b</m> in the vertical direction.
	</p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>

</section>
