<!--Section Complex Numbers-->

<section xml:id='Complex'>

<title>Complex Numbers</title>

<introduction>

<p> </p>

<p>
   All the mathematical work you have done so far has involved using <term>real numbers</term>. In this section, we will work with a new set of numbers called the <term>complex numbers</term><idx>complex numbers</idx>; it should be noted that the real numbers are actually a specific case of the complex numbers.</p> 

</introduction>

<subsection><title>Motivation</title>

<p> </p>

<p>
  Let's start by providing some background as to where complex numbers arise from. Suppose that we want to solve for the <m>x</m>-intercepts of <m>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</m>. We can use the quadratic formula to obtain the <me>x</me>-intercepts, and when doing so, we obtain the following expression: <me>x = \frac{-(-2) \pm \sqrt{(-2)^2-4(1)(2)}}{2(1)} = \frac{2 \pm \sqrt{-4}}{2}</me>.
  
  Notice that <m>\sqrt{-4}</m> is <term>not</term> a real number because there are no real numbers whose square is negative. In fact, the square of any real number is either positive or zero. As a result, <m>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</m> has no real <m>x</m>-intercepts. This can be also be verified graphically since the graph of <m>f(x) = x^2 - 2x + 2</m> never crosses the <m>x</m>-axis. (INSERT GRAPH)
  
</p>

<p> </p>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Imaginary Numbers</title>
<p></p>
Even though the square root of a negative number is not a real number, we can still work with it by defining a new set of numbers, i.e. the complex numbers. Before we do any work with complex numbers, let's define the <term>imaginary unit</term><idx>imaginary unit</idx>.

<assemblage>
  <title>Imaginary Unit</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      The imaginary unit <m>i</m> is defined as
          <m>i = \sqrt{-1}</m> or <m>i^2 = -1</m>.
    
  </p>
  
</assemblage>

It is important to be aware that the letter <m>i</m> is used to represent a constant, not a variable! With the number <m>i</m>, we can now define <term>imaginary numbers</term><idx>imaginary numbers</idx>.

<assemblage>
  <title>Imaginary Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      Let <m>a > 0</m> be a real number. Then,
          <me>\sqrt{-a} = \sqrt{a}\sqrt{-1} = \sqrt{a}i</me>.
    
  </p>
  
</assemblage>
  
Let's refer back to the example introduced earlier in this section. The value <m>\sqrt{-4}</m> can be expressed as follows:

<md>
  <mrow> \sqrt{-4} \amp= \sqrt{4(-1)}</mrow>
  <mrow> \amp= \sqrt{4}\sqrt{-1} </mrow>
  <mrow> \amp = sqrt{4}i </mrow>
  <mrow> \amp = 2i </mrow>.
  
</md>

Here are more examples of imaginary numbers <me>5i</me>, <me>\frac{2}{3}i</me>, <me>-24i</me>, and <me>\sqrt{15}i</me>. 
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Complex Numbers</title>
  Recall that when we are solving for the <me>x</me>-intercepts of <me>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</me>, we obtained the following values for <me>x</me> with the quadratic formula:
  
  <md>x = \frac{2\pm \sqrt{-4}}{2}</md>.
  
  Using our new established knowledge of imaginary numbers, we find that <me>x = \frac{2\pm 2i}{2}</me> which implies that <me>x = 1 + i</me> or <me>1 - i</me>. These <me>x</me>-values are examples of <term>complex numbers</term><idx>complex numbers</idx>. 
  
  <assemblage>
  <title>Complex Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      A <term>complex number</term> can be written in the form
      
      <md> z = a + bi</md>
      
      where <me>a</me> and <me>b</me> are real numbers. Here, <me>a</me> is called the <term>real part</term> and <me>b</me> is called the <term>imaginary part</term>.
  </p>
  
</assemblage>
  
  From this definition, we can observe that all real numbers are actually complex numbers with imaginary part equal to <me>0</me>. Moreover, imaginary numbers are actually complex numbers with real part equal to <me>0</me>; these numbers are called <term>pure imaginary numbers</term>.
  
  The reader shoudl note that the real and imaginary parts of a complex number can never be combined. Hence, two complex numbers are equal if and only if their real parts equal and their imaginary parts are equal. 

<assemblage>
  <title>Equality of Complex Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
    Two complex numbers <me>z = a+bi</me> and <me>w = c+di</me> are equal if and only if <me>a = c</me> and <me>b = d</me>.
    
  </p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Arithmetic of Complex Numbers</title>
  Like real numbers, we can use the following arithmetic operations with complex numbers: addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division. 
  <assemblage>
    <title>Sum and Difference of Complex Numbers</title>
    <p></p>
    <p>
      Consider two complex number <me>z = a+bi</me> and <me>w = c+di</me>. Then their sum is given by
      <md>z+w = (a+bi) + (c+di) = (a+c) + (b+d)i</md>,
      and their difference is given by
      <md>z-w = (a+bi) - (c+di) = (a-c) + (b-d)i</md>.
      
    </p>
    
  </assemblage>
  
  <example>
    <statement>
      Compute <me>(4+5i) + (8-6i)</me> and <me>(2-3i) - (5+2i)</me>.   
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <p>
        <md>(4+5i) + (8-6i) \amp= (4+8) + (5-6)i</md>
        <md> \amp= 12 + (-1)i</md>
        <md> \amp= 12 - i</md>
        
      </p>
      and
      
      <p>
        <md>(2-3i) - (5+2i) \amp= (2-5) - (-3+2)i</md>
        <md> \amp= (-3) - (-1)i </md>
        <md> \amp= -3 + i</md>.
      </p>
      
    </solution>
    
  </example>
  
  <p></p>
  When taking the product of two complex numbers, you should always remember that <me>i^2 = -1</me>. The product of two pure imaginary numbers is very nice and straightfoward to do.
  <assemblage>
    <title>Product of Pure Imaginary Numbers</title>
    <p></p>
    <p>
      Consider two pure imaginary numbers <me>z = ai</me> and <me>w = bi</me>. Then their product is given by
      <md>zw = (ai)(bi) = (ab)i^2 = -ab</md>.
    </p>
    
  </assemblage>
  Finding the product of two complex is slightly different since we need to use the distributive property. 
  <assemblage>
    <title>Product of Complex Numbers</title>
    <p></p>
    <p>
      Consider two complex numbers <me>z = a+bi</me> and <me>w = c+di</me>. Then their product is given by
      <md>zw = (a+bi)(c+di) = (ac - bd) + (ad + bc)i</md>.
    </p>
  </assemblage>
  
  <example>
    <statement>
      Compute <me>(3i)(4i)</me> and <me>(2+3i)(-3-2i)</me>.
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <p>
      <md>(3i)(4i) \amp= (3\cdot 4)i^2 </md>
      <md>\amp= 12(-1)</md>
      <md>\amp= -12</md>,
      </p>
      and
      <p>
        <md>(2+3i)(-3-2i) \amp= (2(-3) - 3(-2)) + (2(-2) + 3(-3))i</md>
        <md>\amp= (-6 + 6) + (-4-9)i</md>
        <md>\amp= 0 - 13i</md>
        <md>\amp= -13i</md>.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </example>
  
  <p></p>
  <text>WARNING:</text> The following property is true with real numbers, but it fails with complex numbers:
  <md>\sqrt{ab} = \sqrt{a}\sqrt{b}</md>.
  Here is a counter-example: let <me>a = b = -2</me>. Then,
  <md>\sqrt{ab} = \sqrt{(-2)(-2)} = \sqrt{4} = 2</md>,
  but
  <md>\sqrt{a}\sqrt{b} \amp= \sqrt{-2}\sqrt{-2}</md>
  <md> \amp= (\sqrt{2}i)(\sqrt{2}i)</md>
  <md> \amp= (\sqrt{2})^2i^2</md>
  <md> \amp = 2(-1) = -2.</md>
Hence, <me>\sqrt{ab} \neq \sqrt{a}\sqrt{b}</me> (especially when <me>a</me>, <me>b</me> are both negative). 
<p></p>
Finding the quotient of two complex numbers requires us to use the technique of rationalizing the denominator. We will consider two different types of quotients: division by a pure imaginary number and division by a complex number. 
  
<assemblage>
  <title>Division by a Pure Imaginary Number</title>
  <p></p>
    <p>
    Consider a complex number <me>z = a+bi</me> and a pure imaginary number <me>w = ci</me>. Then,
    <md>\frac{z}{w} = \frac{a+bi}{ci} = \frac{a+bi}{ci}\cdot \frac{i}{i} = \frac{(a+bi)i}{ci^2} = \frac{-b + ai}{-c} = \frac{b - ai}{c}</md>.
    </p>
</assemblage>
<p></p>
When dividing by a complex number, we rationalize the denonimator by multiplying by the complex conjugate.
<assemblage>
  <title>Complex Conjugate</title>
  For any complex number <me>z = a + bi</me>, the number
  <md>\bar{z} = a - bi</md>
  is called the <term>complex conjugate</term> of <me>z</me>. 
</assemblage>

<term>FACT:</term> The product of a complex number and its conjugate is a real number. That is,
<md>z\bar{z} = (a+bi)(a-bi) = a^2 -abi + abi - b^2i^2 = a^2 - b^2(-1) = a^2 + b^2</md>.

<assemblage>
  <title>Quotient of two Complex Number</title>
  Consider two complex numbers <me>z = a+bi</me> and <me>w = c + di</me>. Then,
  <md>\frac{z}{w} = \frac{a+bi}{c+di} = \frac{a+bi}{c+di}\cdot \frac{c-di}{c-di] = \frac{ac+bd}{c^2+d^2} + \frac{bc-ad}{c^2+d^2}i</md>.
</assemblage>

<example>
  <statement>
    <p>
      Compute <me>\frac{8+9i}{2i}</me> and <me>\frac{4-2i}{2+3i}</me>.
    </p>
    <solution>
      <md>
        \frac{8+9i}{2i} \amp= \frac{8+9i}{2i}\cdot\frac{i}{i}
      </md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{(8+9i)i}{2i^2}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{8i + 9i^2}{2(-1)}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{8i + 9(-1)}{-2}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{-9+8i}{-2}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{9-8i}{2}</md>,
      <p>
        and
      </p>
      <md>
        \frac{4-2i}{2+3i} \amp= \frac{4-2i}{2+3i}\cdot \frac{2-3i}{2-3i}
      </md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{(4-2i)(2+3i)}{(2)^2 + (3)^2}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{(4(2)-(-2)(3)) + (4(3)+(-2)(2))i}{13}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{(8+6)+(12-4)i}{13}</md>
      <md>\amp= \frac{14+8i}{13}</md>.
    </solution>
  </statement>
</example>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Graphing Compex Numbers</title>
  Like real numbers, we can actually graph complex numbers. To plot a complex number, we will utilize a plane called the <term>complex plane</term><idx>complex plane</idx>. The complex plane has two axes; the horizontal axis (<term>real axis</term>) will be used to plot the real part, and the vertical axis (<term>imaginary axis</term>) will be used to plot the imaginary part. The point where the real and imaginary axes cross is called the origin, and it is denoted by <me>(0,0)</me>. 
 
  <assemblage>
  <title>Plotting a Complex Number</title>
  To plot a complex number <me>z = a + bi</me>, we move <me>a</me> units in the horizontal direction and then we move <me>b</me> units in the vertical direction.
</assemblage>
<example>
  <statement>
    <p>Plot the complex numbers <me>2+4i</me>, <me>-2+6i</me>, and <me>-3-i</me> in the complex plane</p>.
  </statement>
  <solution>
    To plot <me>2+4i</me>, we move <me>2</me> units to the right from the origin, and then we move <me>3</me> units up. To plot <me>-2+6i</me>, we move <me>2</me> units to the left from the origin, and then we move <me>6</me> units up. To plot <me>-3-i</me>, we move <me>3</me> units to the left from the origin, and then we move <me>1</me> unit down.  
  </solution>
</example>
INCLUDE FIGURES!!

<p></p>

REMARK: Whenever we plot a complex number <m>z = a + bi</m>, we sometimes use the notation <m>(a,b)</m> to denote a point in the complex plane. In this context, <m>(a,b)</m> represents a single complex number whose real part is <m>a</m> and imaginary part is <m>b</m>. 

<p></p>
We can actually measure the distance a point in the complex plane is from the origin using the Pythagorean theorem. This distance is called the <term>modulus</term><idx>modulus</idx>.
<assemblage>
  <title>Modulus of a Complex Number</title>
  The <term>modulus</term> of a complex number <m>z = a + bi</m> is given by <me>|z| = \sqrt{a^2+b^2}</me> Observe that <m>|z| \geq 0</m>.
</assemblage>

<example>
<statement>Compute the modulus of <m>z = 3 + 4i</m> and <m>w = -1 + i</m>.
<solution><me>|z| = \sqrt{3^2 + 4^2} = \sqrt{25} = 5</me> and <me>|w| = \sqrt{(-1)^2 + 1^2} = \sqrt{1 + 1} = \sqrt{2}</me></solution>
</statement>  

</example>

<example>
  
</example>

</subsection>


</section>
