<!--Section Complex Numbers-->

<section xml:id='Complex'>

<title>Complex Numbers</title>

<introduction>

<p> </p>

<p>
    Up to this point, all the mathematical work you have done has involved using <term>real numbers</term></p>. In this section, we will work with a new set of numbers called <term>complex numbers</term><idx>complex numbers</idx>. It should be noted that the real numbers are actually a subset of the complex numbers!

</introduction>

<subsection><title>Motivation</title>

<p> </p>

<p>
  Let's start by providing some background as to where complex numbers arise from. Suppose that we want to solve for the <me>x</me>-intercepts of <me>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</me>. We can use the quadratic formula to obtain the intercepts, but when we do so we obtain
  
  <md>x = \frac{-(-2) \pm \sqrt{(-2)^2-4(1)(2)}}{2(1)} = \frac{2 \pm \sqrt{-4}}{2}</md>.
  
  Notice that <me>\sqrt{-4}</me> is <term>not</term> a real number. As a result, <me>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</me> has no real <me>x</me>-intercepts. This can be also be verified graphically since the graph of <me>f(x) = x^2 - 2x + 2</me> never crosses the <me>x</me>-axis. (INSERT GRAPH)
  
</p>

<p> </p>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Imaginary Numbers</title>
Even though the square root of a negative number is not a real number, we can still work with it. To do so, we need to first define the <term>imaginary unit</term><idx>imaginary number</idx>.

<assemblage>
  <title>Imaginary Unit</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      The imaginary unit <me>i</me> is defined as
          <me>i = \sqrt{-1}</me> or <me>i^2 = -1</me>.
    
  </p>
  
</assemblage>

It should be noted that the letter <me>i</me> is used to represent a constant, not a variable! With <me>i</me>, we can now define <term>imaginary numbers</term><idx>imaginary numbers</idx>.

<assemblage>
  <title>Imaginary Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      Let <me>a > 0</me> be a real number. Then,
          <me>\sqrt{-a} = \sqrt{a}\sqrt{-1} = \sqrt{a}i</me>.
    
  </p>
  
</assemblage>
  
Let's look at an example. Consider <me>sqrt{-4}</me>. Then,

<md>
  <mrow> \sqrt{-4} \amp= \sqrt{4(-1)}</mrow>
  <mrow> \amp= \sqrt{4}\sqrt{-1} </mrow>
  <mrow> \amp = sqrt{4}i </mrow>
  <mrow> \amp = 2i </mrow>.
  
</md>

Here are more examples of imaginary numbers <me>5i</me>, <me>\frac{2}{3}i</me>, <me>-24i</me>, and <me>\sqrt{15}i</me>. 
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Complex Numbers</title>
  Recall that when were solving for the <me>x</me>-intercepts of <me>f(x) = x^2 -2x + 2</me>, we obtained the following values for <me>x</me> using the quadratic formula:
  
  <md>x = \frac{2\pm \sqrt{-4}}{2}</md>.
  
  Using our knowledge of imaginary numbers, we find that <me>x = \frac{2\pm 2i}{2}</me> which implies that <me>x = 1 + i</me> or <me>1 - i</me>. These <me>x</me>-values are examples of <term>complex numbers</term><idx>complex numbers</idx>. 
  
  <assemblage>
  <title>Complex Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
      A <term>complex number</term> can be written in the form
      
      <md> z = a + bi</md>
      
      where <me>a</me> and <me>b</me> are real numbers. Here, <me>a</me> is called the <term>real part</term> and <me>b</me> is called the <term>imaginary part</term>.
  </p>
  
</assemblage>
  
  From this definition, we can observe that all real numbers are complex numbers with imaginary part is <me>0</me>. Also, a complex number whose real part is <me>0</me> is called a <term>pure imaginary number</term>.
  
  The real and imaginary parts of a complex number cannot be combined. Hence, two complex numbers are equal if and only if their real parts equal and their imaginary parts are equal. 

<assemblage>
  <title>Equality of Complex Numbers</title>
  <p></p>
  <p>
    Two complex numbers <me>z = a+bi</me> and <me>w = c+di</me> are equal if and only if <me>a = c</me> and <me>b = d</me>.
    
  </p>
</assemblage>

</subsection><title>Arithmetic of Complex Numbers</title>


<subsection>
  
  
</subsection>



</section>
