<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->




<chapter xml:id="chap1"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction to Writing for Contemporary Mathematics</title>
<section  xml:id="Numbers-and-Operations"><title>Sectioning</title>
<introduction>
<p>This is an example of a <term>section.</term></p>
</introduction>
<subsection><title>SubSectioning</title>
    
    <p>This is an example of a subsection with a little mathematics involved. 
this is a new sentence</p>

<p>A <term>prime number</term> is an integer greater than <m>1</m> that is divisible only by <m>1</m> and itself. The smallest prime number is <m>2</m> and the rest are necessarily odd:</p>

<me>2,3,5,7,11,13,17,19,23,\dots</me>

<p>Any integer greater than <m>1</m> that is not prime can be uniquely written as a product of primes. When such a number, like <m>42</m>, is written as a product, <m>42=2\cdot 21</m>, we say that <m>2\cdot 21</m> is a factorization of <m>42</m> and that <m>2</m> and <m>21</m> are <term>factors</term>. Note that factors divide the number evenly. We can continue to write factors as products until only a product of primes remains.</p>


<p>Therefore the prime factorization of <m>42</m> is <m>2\cdot 3\cdot 7</m>.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Determine the prime factorization of <m>210</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We begin by writing <m>210</m> as a product with <m>10</m> as a factor. Then we continue factoring until only a product of primes remains.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            210\amp =10\cdot 21\\
            \amp =2\cdot 5\cdot 3\cdot 7
            \end{aligned}</me>
        Since the prime factorization is unique, it does not matter how we choose to initially factor the number - the end result will be the same (although you may write your answer in a different order).
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<example><statement>
    <p> Determine the prime factorization of <m>325</m> 
</p></statement>

<solution> 
    <p> 
        We begin by writing <m>325</m> as a product with <m>25</m> as a factor. Then we continue factoring until only a product of primes remains. 

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            325 \amp= 25\cdot 13\\
            \amp= 5 \cdot 5 \cdot 13
            \end{aligned}</me> 

            Since the prime factorization is unique, it does not matter how we choose to initially factor the number - the end result will be the same (although you may write your answer in a different order).
        </p>
</solution>
</example>



</subsection>
</section>







</chapter> 








<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
