<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->




<chapter xml:id="chap3"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Polynomials and Factoring</title>

<section xml:id="Exponents"><title>Rules of Exponents</title><introduction>
    <p>In this section, we cover the rules of exponents. If a factor is repeated multiple times, then the product can be written in <term>exponential form</term> <m>x^n</m>. The positive integer exponent <m>n</m> indicates the number of times the base <m>x</m> is repeated as a factor.</p>
</introduction>

<me> x^n=x\cdot x\cdots x.</me>

<p>Consider the product of <m>x^4</m> and <m>x^6</m>:</p>

<me>x^4\cdot x^6 =(x\cdot x\cdot x\cdot x)\cdot(x\cdot x\cdot x\cdot x\cdot x\cdot x\cdot)=x^{10}.</me>

<p>Expanding the expression using the definition produces multiple factors of the base which is quite cumbersome, particularly when <m>n</m> is large. For this reason, we have useful rules to help us simplify expressions with exponents. In the example above, notice that we could obtain the same result by adding the exponents.</p>

<me>x^4\cdot x^6=x^{4+6}=x^{10}</me>

<p>In general, this describes the <term>product rule for exponents</term>. In other words, when multiplying two expressions with the same base we add the exponents. Compare this to raising a factor involving an exponent to a power, such as <m>(x^6)^4</m>.</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    (x^6)^4 \amp=x^6\cdot x^6\cdot x^6\cdot x^6\\
    \amp=x^{6+6+6+6}\\
    \amp=x^{24}
    \end{aligned}</me>

<p>Here we have 4 factors of <m>x^6</m> which is equivalent to multiplying the exponents.</p>

<me>(x^6)^4=x^{6\cdot 4}=x^{24}</me>

<p>This describes the <term>power rule for exponents</term>. Now we consider raising grouped products to a power. For example,</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    (x^2y^3)^4 \amp = x^2y^3\cdot x^2y^3\cdot x^2y^3\cdot x^2y^3\\
    \amp = x^2\cdot x^2\cdot x^2\cdot x^2\cdot y^3\cdot y^3\cdot y^3\cdot y^3\\
    \amp = x^{2+2+2+2}\cdot y^{3+3+3+3}\\
    \amp=x^8y^{12}.
    \end{aligned}</me>

<p>After expanding, we are left with four factors of the product <m>x^2y^3</m>. This is equivalent to raising each of the original grouped factors to the fourth power and applying the power rule.</p>

<me>(x^2y^3)^4=(x^2)^4(y^3)^4=x^8y^{12}</me>

<p>In general, this describes the use of the power rule for a product as well as the power rule for exponents. In summary, the rules of exponents streamline the process of working with algebraic expressions and will be used extensively as we move through our study of algebra. Given any positive integers <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> where <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are nonzero we have the rules below.</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\text{Product Rule for Exponents: }\amp x^m\cdot x^n=x^{m+n}</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Quotient Rule for Exponents: }\amp \frac{x^m}{x^n}=x^{m-n}</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Power Rule for Exponents: }\amp (x^m)^n=x^{m\cdot n}</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Power Rule for a Product: }\amp (xy)^n=x^ny^n</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Power Rule for a Quotient: }\amp \left(\frac{x}{y}\right)^n=\frac{x^n}{y^n}.</mrow>
</md>

<p>These rules allow us to efficiently perform operations with exponents.</p>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{10^4\cdot 10^{12}}{10^3}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \frac{10^4\cdot 10^{12}}{10^3}\amp = \frac{10^{16}}{10^3} \amp \alert{\text{ Product Rule}}\\
            \amp = 10^{16-3}\amp\alert{\text{ Quotient Rule}}\\
            \amp=10^{13} \amp
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>


<p>In the previous example, notice that we did not multiply the base 10 times itself. When applying the product rule, we add the <em>exponents</em> and leave the <em>base</em> unchanged.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\left(x^5\cdot x^4\cdot x\right)^2</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Note that the variable <m>x</m> is assumed to have an exponent of one, <m>x=x^1</m>.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \left(x^5\cdot x^4\cdot x\right)^2\amp =\left(x^{5+4+1}\right)^2\\
            \amp =(x^{10})^2\\
            \amp =x^{10\cdot 2}\\
            \amp = x^{20}
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>The base could in fact be any algebraic expression.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>(x+y)^9(x+y)^{13}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Treat the expression <m>(x+y)</m> as the base.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            (x+y)^9(x+y)^{13}\amp =(x+y)^{9+13}\\
            \amp =(x+y)^{22}
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>The commutative property of multiplication allows us to use the product rule for exponents to simplify factors of an algebraic expression.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>-8x^5y\cdot 3x^7y^3</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Multiply the coefficients and add the exponents of variable factors with the same base.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            -8x^5y\cdot 3x^7y^3 \amp =(-8)\cdot 3\cdot x^5\cdot x^7\cdot y^1\cdot y^3\amp \alert{\text{ Commutative Property}}\\
            \amp =-24\cdot x^{5+7}\cdot y^{1+3}\amp \alert{\text{ Power Rule for Exponents}}\\
            \amp = -24x^{12}y^{4}
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Division involves the quotient rule for exponents.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{33x^7y^5(x-y)^{10}}{11x^6y(x-y)^3}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \frac{33x^7y^5(x-y)^{10}}{11x^6y(x-y)^3} \amp = \frac{33}{11}\cdot x^{7-6}\cdot y^{5-1}\cdot (x-y)^{10-3}\\
            \amp =3x^1y^4(x-y)^7\\
            \amp =3xy^4(x-y)^7
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>The power rule for a quotient allows us to apply that exponent to the numerator and denominator. This rule requires that the denominator is nonzero and so we will make this assumption for the remainder of the section.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\left(\frac{-4a^2b}{c^4}\right)^3</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>First apply the power rule for a quotient and then the power rule for a product.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \left(\frac{-4a^2b}{c^4}\right)^3 \amp = \frac{(-4a^2b)^3}{(c^4)^3}\amp \alert{\text{ Power Rule for a Quotient}}\\
            \amp =\frac{(-4)^3(a^2)^3(b)^3}{(c^4)^3}\amp \alert{\text{ Power Rule for a Product}}\\
            \amp =\frac{-64a^6b^3}{c^{12}} \amp
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Using the quotient rule for exponents, we can define what it means to have zero as an exponent. Consider the following calculation:</p>

<me> 1=\frac{25}{25}=\frac{5^2}{5^2}=5^{2-2}=5^0.</me>

<p>Twenty-five divided by twenty-five is clearly equal to one, and when the quotient rule for exponents is applied, we see that a zero exponent results. In general, given any nonzero real number <m>x</m> and integer <m>n</m>,</p>

<me>1=\frac{x^n}{x^n}=x^{n-n}=x^0.</me>

<p>This leads us to the definition of zero as an exponent,</p>

<me>x^0=1,\text{ for }x\neq 0.</me>

<p>It is important to note that <m>0^0</m> is indeterminate. If the base is negative, then the result is still positive one. In other words, any nonzero base raised to the zero power is defined to be equal to one. In the following examples assume all variables are nonzero.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify
        <ol label="a">
            <li><m>(-2x)^0</m> and
            </li>
            <li><m>-2x^0.
            </m></li>
        </ol>
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p> <ol label="a">
        <li>Any nonzero quantity raised to the zeroth power is equal to <m>1</m>.
            <me>(-2x)^0=1
            </me></li>
        <li>In this example, the base is <m>x</m>, not <m>-2x</m>.
            <me>\begin{aligned}
                -2x^0\amp = -2\cdot x^0\\
                \amp = -2\cdot 1\\
                \amp = -2
                \end{aligned}
            </me></li>
    </ol>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Noting that <m> 2^0=1</m> we can write</p>

<me>\frac{1}{2^3}=\frac{2^0}{2^3}=2^{0-3}=2^{-3}.</me>

<p> In general, given any nonzero real number <m>x</m> and integer <m>n</m>,</p>

<me>\frac{1}{x^n}=\frac{x^0}{x^n}=x^{0-n}=x^{-n}\text{ for }x\neq 0.</me>

<p>This leads us to the definition of <term>negative exponents</term>:</p>

<me> x^{-n}=\frac{1}{x^n}\text{ for }x\neq 0.</me>

<p>An expression is completely simplified if it does not contain any negative exponents.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>(-4x^2y)^{-2}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Rewrite the entire quantity in the denominator with an exponent of <m>2</m> and then simplify further.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            (-4x^2y)^{-2}\amp =\frac{1}{(-4x^2y)^2}\\
            \amp =\frac{1}{(-4)^2(x^2)^2(y)^2}\\
            \amp = \frac{1}{16x^4y^2}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Sometimes negative exponents appear in the denominator.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{x^{-3}}{y^{-4}}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        <me>
            \frac{x^{-3}}{y^{-4}} =\frac{\frac{1}{x^3}}{\frac{1}{y^4}}=\frac{1}{x^3}\cdot\frac{y^4}{1}=\frac{y^4}{x^3}
        </me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>The previous example suggests a property of quotients with negative exponents. Given any integers <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> where <m>x\neq 0</m> and <m>y\neq 0</m>, then</p>

<me>\frac{x^{-n}}{y^{-m}}=\frac{\frac{1}{x^n}}{\frac{1}{y^n}}=\frac{1}{x^n}\cdot\frac{y^m}{1}=\frac{y^m}{x^n}.</me>

<p>This leads us to the property</p>

<me>\frac{x^{-n}}{y^{-m}}=\frac{y^m}{x^n}.</me>

<p>In other words, negative exponents in the numerator can be written as positive exponents in the denominator and negative exponents in the denominator can be written as positive exponents in the numerator.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{-5x^{-3}y^3}{z^{-4}}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p> Notice the coefficient <m>-5</m>: recognize that this is the base and that the exponent is actually positive one: <m>-5=(-5)^1</m>. Hence, the rules of negative exponents do not apply to this coefficient which is why we leave it in the numerator.
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
            \frac{-5x^{-3}y^3}{z^{-4}}\amp =\frac{-5 \alert{x^{-3}}y^3}{\alert{z^{-4}}}\\
            \amp =\frac{-5y^3\alert{z^4}}{\alert{x^3}}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>In summary, given integers <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> where <m>x,y\neq 0</m>, we have the rules below.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    \text{Zero Exponent: }\amp x^0=1\\
    \text{Negative Exponent: }\amp x^{-n}=\frac{1}{x^n}\\
    \text{Quotients with Negative Exponents: }\amp \frac{x^{-n}}{y^{-m}}=\frac{y^m}{x^n}
    \end{aligned}
</me>

<p>Furthermore, all of the rules of exponents defined so far extend to any integer exponents. We can expand the scope of these properties to include any real number exponents.</p>


</section>





<section  xml:id="Algebra-of-Functions"><title>Algebra of Functions</title>
<introduction>
<p> A <term>polynomial</term> is an expression made up of a single term or sum of terms with only one variable. Explicitly, any polynomial with one variable defines a function and can be written in the form</p>

<md>
    <mrow>f(x)=a_n x^n+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\cdots +a_1x+a_0.</mrow>
    </md>

<p>Here <m>a_n</m> represents any real number and <m>n</m> represents any whole number. The <term>degree</term> of a polynomial with one variable is the largest exponent of all the terms. Typically, we arrange terms of polynomials in descending order based on their degree and classify them as follows:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\begin{aligned}
        f(x)\amp =2 \ \alert{\text{   Constant function (degree }0\text{)}}\\
        g(x)\amp = 3x+2 \ \alert{\text{   Linear function (degree }1\text{)}}\\
        h(x)\amp = 4x^2+3x+2 \ \alert{\text{   Quadratic function (degree }2\text{)}}\\
        p(x)\amp = 5x^3+4x^2+3x+2 \ \alert{\text{   Cubic function (degree }3\text{)}}
        \end{aligned}
        </mrow>
    </md>

<p>In this course, we call any polynomial with degree higher than 3 an <m>n</m>th-degree polynomial. For example, if the degree is 4, we call it a fourth-degree polynomial; if the degree is 5, we call it a fifth-degree polynomial, and so on.</p>

<p>When a polynomial is arranged in descending order based on their degree, we call the first term of the sum the <term>leading term</term>, and the coefficient part of this term is called the <term>leading coefficient</term>.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=3x^2+5x+17</m>, <m>g(x)=15x^{24}+36x^{22}+17x^4+31</m>, <m>h(x)=11x^2+17x^3+121x</m>, <m>j(x)=5x^3+2x+4x^3+3x+5</m>, and <m>k(x)=25</m>, state the degree, leading term, and leading coefficient of each polynomial.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
       Looking at <m>f(x)</m>, we see that the highest power of <m>x</m> is <m>2</m>, so the degree is <m>2</m>. The term with the highest degree is <m>3x^2</m>, meaning this is our leading term, and the coefficient of this term is <m>3</m>, which means this is our leading coefficient.
    </p>
    <p>
        Looking at <m>g(x)</m>, we see that the highest power of <m>x</m> is <m>24</m>, so the degree is <m>24</m>. The term with the highest degree is <m>15x^{24}</m>, meaning this is our leading term, and the coefficient of this term is <m>15</m>, which means this is our leading coefficient.
    </p>
    <p>
        Looking at <m>h(x)</m>, we see that the polynomial is not arranged in descending order of degree, so we will rearrange first.
        <me>h(x)=17x^3+11x^2+121x</me>
       Now we see that the highest power of <m>x</m> is <m>3</m>, so the degree is <m>3</m>. The term with the highest degree is <m>17x^{3}</m>, meaning this is our leading term, and the coefficient of this term is <m>17</m>, which means this is our leading coefficient.
    </p>
    <p>
        Looking at <m>j(x)</m>, we see that the polynomial is not arranged in descending order of degree, so we will rearrange first.
        <me>j(x)=5x^3+4x^3+2x+3x+5=9x^3+5x+5</me>
        Now we see that the highest power of <m>x</m> is <m>3</m>, so the degree is <m>3</m>. The term with the highest degree is <m>9x^{3}</m>, meaning this is our leading term, and the coefficient of this term is <m>9</m>, which means this is our leading coefficient.
    </p>
    <p>
        Looking at <m>k(x)</m>, we have just a constant. This is the same as <m>k(x)=25\cdot 1=25x^0</m>, so we see that the highest power of <m>x</m> is <m>0</m>, so the degree is <m>0</m>. The term with the highest degree is <m>25x^0=25</m>, meaning this is our leading term, and the coefficient of this term is <m>25</m>, which means this is our leading coefficient.
    </p>


</solution>
</example>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=x^2-8x+17</m>, find <m>f(2)</m> and <m>f(4)</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                Replace each instance of <m>x</m> with the value given inside the parentheses.
            </p>
         <me>
             \begin{aligned}
             f(\alert{2})\amp = (\alert{2})^2-8(\alert{2})+17\\
             \amp =4-16+17\\
             \amp =4+1\\
             \amp =5
             \end{aligned}
             </me>
         <me>
             \begin{aligned}
             f(\alert{4})\amp = (\alert{4})^2-8(\alert{4})+17\\
             \amp =16-32+17\\
             \amp =-16+17\\
             \amp =1
             \end{aligned}
         </me>

         <p>We can write <m>f(2)=5</m> and <m>f(4)=1</m>. Remember that <m>f(x)=y</m> and so we can interpret these results on the graph as follows:</p>

           <p> <image source="images/AlgebraFunctions1.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

         <p> We find that <m>f(2)=5</m> and <m>f(4)=1</m>.</p>

        </solution>
    </example>

         <p>Often we will be asked to evaluate polynomials for algebraic expressions.</p>

         <example><statement>
             <p>
                 Given <m>g(x)=x^3-x+5</m>, find <m>g(-2u)</m> and <m>g(x-2)</m>.
             </p></statement>
         <solution>
             <p>
                 Replace each instance of <m>x</m> with the expressions given inside the parentheses.
             </p>
             <me>
                 \begin{aligned}
                 g(\alert{-2u})\amp = (\alert{-2u})^3-(\alert{-2u})+5\\
                 \amp =-8u^3+2u+5
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>
             <me>
                 \begin{aligned}
                 g(\alert{x-2})\amp = (\alert{x-2})^3-(\alert{x-2})+5\\
                 \amp =(x-2)(x-2)(x-2)-(x-2)+5\\
                 \amp = (x-2)(x^2-4x+4)-x+2+5\\
                 \amp = x^3-4x^2+4x-2x^2+8x-8-x+7\\
                 \amp = x^3-6x^2+11x-1
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>


             <p> We find that <m>g(-2u)=-8u^3+2u+5</m> and <m>g(x-2)=x^3-6x^2+11x-1</m>.</p>

         </solution>
         </example>





<p>The height of an object launched upward, ignoring the effects of air resistance, can be modeled with the following quadratic function:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>h(t)=-\frac{1}{2}gt^2+v_0t+s_0</mrow>
    </md>

<p>With this formula, the height <m>h(t)</m> can be calculated at any given time <m>t</m> after the object is launched. The letter <m>g</m> represents acceleration due to gravity on the surface of the Earth, which is 32 feet per second squared (or, using metric units, <m>g = 9.8</m> meters per second squared). The parameter <m>v_0</m> pronounced “v-naught,” or sometimes “v-zero,” represents the initial velocity of the object.  The parameter <m>s_0</m> represents the initial height from which the object was launched.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        An object is launched from the ground at a speed of <m>64</m> feet per second. Write a function that models the height of the object and use it to calculate the object's height at <m>1</m> second and at <m>3.5</m> seconds.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We know that the acceleration due to gravity is <m>g=32</m> feet per second squared and we are given the initial velocity <m>v_0=64</m> feet per second. Since the object is launched from the ground, the initial height is <m>s_0=0</m> feet. Create the mathematical model by substituting these coefficients into the following formula:
    </p>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        h(t)\amp =-\frac{1}{2}gt^2+v_ot+s_0\\
        h(t)\amp = -\frac{1}{2}(\alert{32})t^2+(\alert{64})t+\alert{0}\\
        h(t)\amp = -16t^2+64t
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Use this model to calculate the height of the object at <m>1</m> second and <m>3.5</m> seconds. </p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        h(\alert{1})\amp = -16(\alert{1})^2+64(\alert{1})=-16+64=48\\
        h(\alert{3.5})\amp = -16(\alert{3.5})^2+64(\alert{3.5})=-196+224=28
        \end{aligned}
    </me>


    <p> Our function is  <m>h(t)=-16t^2+64t</m>. This tells us that at <m>1</m> second the object is at a height of <m>48</m> feet, and at <m>3.5</m> seconds it is at a height of <m>28</m> feet.</p>

</solution>
</example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        An object is dropped from a height of <m>6</m> meters. Write a function that models the height of the object and use it to calculate the object's height <m>1</m> second after it is dropped.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Our function is <m>h(t)=-4.9t^2+6</m>. This means that at <m>1</m> second the object is at a height of <m>1.1</m> meters.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
</introduction>
<subsection><title>Adding and Subtracting Polynomials</title>

<p>On occasion a special notation is used to indicate addition and subtraction of functions.  This mentioned here in the book so you have some exposure to the notation.  The notation is as follows:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\text{Addition of functions: }(f+g)(x)=f(x)+g(x)</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Subtraction of functions: }(f-g)(x)=f(x)-g(x).</mrow>
    </md>

<p>When using function notation, be careful to group the entire function and add or subtract accordingly.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=x^3-5x-7</m> and <m>g(x)=3x^2+7x-2</m>, find <m>f(x)+g(x)</m> and <m>f(x)-g(x)</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>The notation <m>f(x)+g(x)</m> indicates that we should add the given expressions.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        f(x)+g(x)\amp = (x^3-5x-7)+(3x^2+7x-2)\\
        \amp = x^3-5x-7+3x^2+7x-2\\
        \amp = x^3+3x^2+2x-9
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>The notation <m>f(x)-g(x)</m> indicates that we should subtract the given expressions. When subtracting, the parentheses become very important. We can eliminate them after applying the distributive property.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
   f(x)-g(x) \amp = (x^3-5x-7)-(3x^2+7x-2)\\
    \amp = x^3-5x-7-3x^2-7x+2\\
    \amp = x^3-3x^2-12x-5
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>Our solutions are <m>f(x)+g(x)=x^3+3x^2+2x-9</m> and <m>f(x)-g(x)= x^3-3x^2-12x-5</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>


<p>We may be asked to evaluate the sum or difference of two functions. We have the option to first find the sum or difference in general and then use the resulting function to evaluate for the given variable, or evaluate each first and then find the sum or difference.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Evaluate <m>f(3)-g(3)</m> given <m>f(x)=5x^2-x+4</m> and <m>g(x)=x^2+2x-3</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>First, find <m>(f-g)(x)</m>.</p>

    <me>
                \begin{aligned}

                f(x)-g(x)\amp = (5x^2-x+4)-(x^2+2x-3)\\
                \amp = 5x^2-x+4-x^2-2x+3\\
                \amp = 4x^2-3x+7
                \end{aligned}
                </me>

    <p>Now we substitute <m>3</m> in for the variable <m>x</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        f(\alert{3})-g(\alert{3}) \amp = 4(\alert{3})^2-3(\alert{3})+7\\
        \amp = 36-9+7\\
        \amp = 34
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>Our solution is <m>f(3)-g(3)=34</m>.</p>

    <p>Alternatively, we could have found <m>f(3)</m> and <m>g(3)</m> and then subtracted the results to obtain our answer.</p>
                </solution>
            </example>
<p>Note: If multiple values are to be evaluated, it is best to find the sum or difference in general first and then use it to evaluate.</p>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        Evaluate <m>f(-1)+g(-1)</m> given <m>f(x)=x^3+x-8</m> and <m>g(x)=2x^2-x+9</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
<p>The solution is <m>f(-1)+g(-1)=2</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Multiplying and Dividing Polynomials</title>

<p>The notation that is sometimes used to indicate multiplication and division of functions follows:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\text{Multiplication of functions: }(f\cdot g)(x)=f(x)\cdot g(x)</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Division of functions: }\left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)=\frac{f(x)}{g(x)}, \text{ where }g(x)\neq 0.</mrow>
</md>
    <p>In this book we will simply consider multiplication notated by <m>f(x)\cdot g(x)</m> and division notated by <m>\frac{f(x)}{g(x)}, \text{ where }g(x)\neq 0.</m></p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=15x^4-9x^3+6x^2</m> and <m>g(x)=3x^2</m>, find <m>f(x)\cdot g(x)</m> and <m>\frac{f(x)}{g(x)}</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p> Apply the distributive property and simplify.
        </p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        f(x)\cdot g(x)\amp = (15x^4-9x^3+6x^2)(3x^2)\\
        \amp = 15x^4\cdot\alert{3x^2}-9x^3\cdot \alert{3x^2}+6x^2\cdot\alert{3x^2}\\
        \amp = 45x^6-27x^5+18x^4
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>For this quotient, assume <m>x\neq 0</m>.
    </p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
         \frac{f(x)}{g(x)}\amp = \frac{15x^4-9x^3+6x^2}{3x^2}\\
        \amp = \frac{15x^4}{3x^2}-\frac{9x^3}{3x^2}+\frac{6x^2}{3x^2}\\
        \amp = 5x^2-3x+2
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Our solutions are <m>f(x)\cdot g(x)=45x^6-27x^5+18x^4</m> and <m>\frac{f(x)}{g(x)}= 5x^2-3x+2</m>.</p>

    </solution>
</example>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=6x-5</m> and <m>g(x)=3x^2-2x-1</m>, find <m>f(0)\cdot g(0)</m> and <m>f(-1)\cdot g(-1)</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>Begin by finding <m>f(x)\cdot g(x)</m>.
    </p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}

 		f(x)\cdot g(x)\amp = (6x-5)(3x^2-2x-1)\\
        \amp = 18x^3-12x^2-6x-15x^2+10x+5\\
        \amp = 18x^3-27x^2+4x+5
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Now we substitute <m>0</m> and <m>-1</m> in for the variable <m>x</m>.
    </p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
       f(0)\cdot g(0)\amp = 18(0)^3-27(0)^2+4(0)+5\\
        \amp =5
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

   <me>
       \begin{aligned}
     f(-1)\cdot g(-1)\amp = 18(-1)^3-27(-1)^2+4(-1)+5\\
       \amp = -18-27-4+5\\
       \amp=-44
       \end{aligned}
   </me>

    <p>Our solutions are <m>f(0)\cdot g(0)=5</m> and <m>f(-1)\cdot g(-1)=-44</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>
       Evaluate <m>f(-1)\cdot g(-1)</m> given <m>f(x)=x^3+x-8</m> and <m>g(x)=2x^2-x+9</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>The solution is <m>f(-1)\cdot g(-1)=-120</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

</subsection>

</section>


<section  xml:id="Factoring-Polynomials"><title>Factoring Polynomials</title>

   <introduction>
    <p>The process of writing a number or expression as a product is called <term>factoring</term>. If we write the monomial <m>8x^7=2x^5\cdot 4x^2</m>, we say that the product <m>2x^5\cdot 4x^2</m> is a factorization of <m>8x^7</m> and that <m>2x^5</m> and <m>4x^2</m> are <term>factors</term>. Typically there are many ways to factor a monomial. Some factorizations of <m>8x^7</m> are</p>

    <md>
        \begin{aligned}
        <mrow>8x^7 \amp =2x^5\cdot 4x^2\text{,}</mrow>
        <mrow>8x^7 \amp =8x^6\cdot x \text{, and}</mrow>
        <mrow>8x^7 \amp =2x\cdot 2x^2\cdot 2x^4\ \text{.}</mrow>
        \end{aligned}
        </md>

    <p>Given two or more monomials, it will be useful to find the <term>greatest common factor (GCF)</term> of each. The GCF of the monomials is the product of the common variable factors and the GCF of the coefficients.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Find the GCF of <m>25x^7y^2z</m> and <m> 15x^3y^4z^2</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>

    <p>We begin by finding the GCF of the coefficients. In this case, <m>25=5\cdot 5</m> and <m>15=3\cdot 5</m>.
         It should be clear that GCF<m>(25,15)=5</m>.</p>

    <p>Next we determine the common variable factors with the smallest exponents.</p>

    <me> 25x^7\alert{y^2z}\, \, \text{ and }\, \, 15\alert{x^3}y^4z^2</me>

    <p>The common variable factors are <m>x^3</m>, <m>y^2</m> and <m>z</m>.
        Therefore, given the two monomials,</p>

    <me>\text{GCF}(25x^7y^2z,\, 15x^3y^4z^2)=5x^3y^2z.</me>

    </solution>
    </example>

    <p>It is worth pointing out that the GCF divides both expressions evenly.</p>

    <me>
        \frac{25x^7y^2z}{\alert{5x^3y^2z}}=5x^4 \text{ and }\frac{15x^3y^4z^2}{\alert{5x^3y^2z}}=3y^2z
        </me>

    <p>Furthermore, we can write the following:</p>

        <me>25x^7y^2z=\alert{5x^3y^2z}\cdot 5x^4 \text{ and }15x^3y^4z^2=\alert{5x^3y^2z}\cdot 3y^2z\text{.}
            </me>

        <p>The factors <m>5x^4</m> and <m>3y^2z</m> share no common factors other than 1; they are <term>relatively prime</term>.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Determine the GCF of the following three expressions: <m>12a^5b^2(a+b)^5,\, 60a^4b^3c(a+b)^3</m>, and <m>24a^2b^7c^3(a+b)^2</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>

        <p>We begin by finding the GCF of the coefficients. To do this, determine the prime factorization of each and then multiply the common factors with the smallest exponents.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            12\amp = 2^2\cdot 3\\
            60\amp = 2^2\cdot 3\cdot 5\\
            24\amp = 2^3\cdot 3
            \end{aligned}</me>

        <p>Therefore, the GCF of the coefficients of the three monomials is</p>

        <me>\text{GCF}(12,\, 60\, 24)=2^2\cdot 3=12\text{.}</me>

        <p>Next, we determine the common factors of the variables.</p>

        <me>12a^5\alert{b^2}(a+b)^5 \, \text{ and }\, 60a^4b^3c(a+b)^3\, \text{ and }\, 24\alert{a^2}b^7c^3\alert{(a+b)^2}</me>

        <p>The variable factors in common are <m>a^2\, b^2</m> and <m>(a+b)^2</m>. Therefore,</p>

        <me>\text{GCF}(12a^5b^2(a+b)^5,\, 60a^4b^3c(a+b)^3, \, 24a^2b^7c^3(a+b)^2)=12a^2b^2(a+b)^2\text{.}</me>

    </solution>
    </example>
</introduction>
    <subsection><title>Factoring Out the GCF</title>


    <p>The application of the distributive property is the key to multiplying polynomials. For example,</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \alert{6xy^2}(2xy+1)\amp = \alert{6xy^2}\cdot 2xy +\alert{6xy^2}\cdot 1\\
        \amp = 12x^2y^3+6xy^2\text{.}
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>The process of factoring a polynomial involves applying the distributive property in reverse to write each polynomial as a product of polynomial factors.</p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        \alert{a}(b+c)\amp =\alert{a}b+\alert{a}c\\
        \alert{a}b+\alert{a}c\amp =\alert{a}(b+c)
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    Consider factoring the result of the opening example:

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        12x^2 y^3+6xy^2\amp =\alert{6xy^2}\cdot 2xy+\alert{6xy^2}\cdot 1\\
        \amp = \alert{6xy^2}(\text{ ? })\\
        \amp =\alert{6xy^2}(2xy+1)\text{.}
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>We see that the distributive property allows us to write the polynomial <m>12x^2y^3+6xy^2</m> as a product of two factors <m>6xy^2</m> and <m>(2xy+1)</m>. Note that in this case, <m>6xy^2</m> is the GCF of the terms of the polynomial: GCF<m>(12x^2y^3,6xy^2)=6xy^2</m>.</p>

    <p>Factoring out the greatest common factor (GCF) of a polynomial involves rewriting it as a product where a factor is the GCF of all of its terms.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        8x^3+4x^2-16x \amp = \alert{4x}(2x^2+x-4)\\
        9ab^2-18a^2b-3ab \amp= \alert{3ab}(3b-6a-1)
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>To factor out the GCF of a polynomial, we first determine the GCF of all of its terms. Then we can divide each term of the polynomial by this factor as a means to determine the remaining factor after applying the distributive property in reverse.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p> Factor out the GCF of the polynomial <m>18x^7-30x^5+6x^3</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    <solution>
        <p>In this case, the GCF<m>(18,\, 30,\, 6) = 6</m>, and the common variable factor with the smallest exponent is <m>x^3</m>. The GCF of the polynomial is <m>6x^3</m>.</p>

        <me>18x^7-30x^5+6x^3=\alert{6x^3}(\: \: \: ? \: \: \: )</me>

        <p>The missing factor can be found by dividing each term of the original expression by the GCF.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \frac{18x^7}{\alert{6x^3}}\amp =3x^4\\
            \frac{-30x^5}{\alert{6x^3}}\amp =-5x^2\\
            \frac{6x^3}{\alert{6x^3}}\amp =1
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>Now we apply the distributive property (in reverse) using the terms found in the previous step.</p>

        <me>18x^7-30x^5+6x^3=\alert{6x^3}(3x^4-5x^2+1)</me>

        <p>If the GCF is the same as one of the terms, then, after the GCF is factored out, a constant term 1 will remain. The importance of remembering the constant term becomes clear when performing the check using the distributive property.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \alert{6x^3}(3x^4-5x^2+1)\amp = \alert{6x^3}\cdot 3x^4-\alert{6x^3}\cdot 5x^2+\alert{6x^3}\cdot 1\\
            \amp = 18x^7-30x^5+6x^3
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>Factoring out the GCF results in <m>6x^3(3x^4-5x^2+1)</m>.</p>

    </solution>
    </example>

<example><statement>
    <p> Factor out the GCF of the polynomial <m>27^5y^5z+54x^5yz-63x^3y^4</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The GCF of the terms is <m>9x^3y</m>. The last term does not have a variable factor of <m>z</m>, and thus <m>z</m> cannot be a part of the greatest common factor. If we divide each term by <m>9x^3y</m>, we obtain</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        \frac{27x^5y^5z}{\alert{9x^3y}}\amp = 3x^2y^4z\\
        \frac{54x^5yz}{\alert{9x^3y}}\amp = 6x^2z\\
        \frac{-63x^3y^4}{\alert{9x^3y}}\amp = -7y^3\text{.}\\
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    Now we have

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        27^5y^5z+54x^5yz-63x^3y^4\amp =\alert{9x^3y}(\: \: \: ? \: \: \: )\\
        \amp = 9x^3y(3x^2y^4z+6x^2z-7y^3)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Factoring out the GCF results in <m>9x^3y(3x^2y^4z+6x^2z-7y^3)</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>


<exercise><statement>
    <p> Factor out the GCF of the polynomial <m>12x^3y^4-6x^2y^3-3xy^2</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Factoring out the GCF results in <m>3xy^2(4x^2y^2-2xy-1)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>



    </subsection>


<subsection><title>Factoring by Grouping</title>

    <p>In this section, we outline a technique for factoring polynomials with four terms. First, review a preliminary example where the terms have a common binomial factor.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p> Factor <m>7x(3x-2)-(3x-2)</m>.</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
        <p>We begin by rewriting the second term <m>-(3x-2)</m> as <m>-1(3x-2)</m>.
          Next, consider <m>(3x-2)</m> as a common binomial factor and factor it out as follows:</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            7x(3x-2)-(3x-2)\amp = 7x\alert{(3x-2)}-1\alert{(3x-2)}\\
            \amp = \alert{(3x-2)}(\, ?\, )\\
            \amp =(3x-2)(7x-1).
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Factoring results in <m>7x(3x-2)-(3x-2)=(3x-2)(7x-1)</m>.</p>

    </solution>
    </example>


    <p>Factoring by grouping is a technique that enables us to factor polynomials with four terms into a product of binomials. This involves an intermediate step where a common binomial factor will be factored out. For example, suppose we wish to factor</p>

    <me> 3x^3-12x^2+2x-8\text{.}</me>

    <p>We begin by grouping the first two terms and the last two terms. Then factor out the GCF of each grouping:</p>

    <me>\underbrace{3x^3-12x^2}+\underbrace{2x-8}=\alert{3x^2}(x-4)+\alert{2}(x-4)</me>

    <p>In this form, the polynomial is a binomial with a common binomial factor, <m>(x-4)</m>.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            3x^3-12x^2+2x-8 \amp = (x-4)(\text{ ? })\\
            \amp = (x-4)(\alert{3x^2+2})
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>We can check our answer by multiplying:</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            (x-4)(3x^2+2)\amp = 3x^3+2x-12x^2-8\\
            \amp = 3x^3-12x^2+2x-8\text{.}
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <example><statement>
            <p> Factor the polynomial <m>24a^4-18a^3-20a+15</m> by grouping.</p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>The GCF for the first group, <m>24a^4-18a^3</m>, is <m>6a^3</m>. We have to choose <m>5</m> or <m>-5</m> to factor out of the second group.</p>

            <p>Factoring out <m>+5</m> does not result in a common binomial factor. If we choose to factor out <m>-5</m>, then we obtain a common binomial factor and can proceed. Note that when factoring out a negative number, we change the signs of the factored terms.</p>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                24a^4-18a^3-20a+15\amp = 6a^3(\, ?\, )-5(\, ?\, )\\
                \amp = 6a^3(4a-3)-5(4a-3)\\
                \amp = (4a-3)(\, ?\, )\\
                \amp =(4a-3)(6a^3-5)
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

            <p>Factoring <m>24a^4-18a^3-20a+15</m> results in <m>24a^4-18a^3-20a+15=(4a-3)(6a^3-5)</m>.</p>

        </solution>
        </example>


    <p>Sometimes we must first rearrange the terms in order to obtain a common factor.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p> Factor <m>ab-2a^2b+a^3-2b^2</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>If we simply factor the GCF out of the first group and last group, we do not get a common binomial factor.</p>

    <p>We must rearrange the terms, searching for a grouping that produces a common factor. In this example, we have a workable grouping if we switch the terms <m>a^3</m> and <m>ab</m>. </p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        ab-2a^2b+a^3-2b^2\amp = a^3-2a^2b+ab-2b^2\\
        \amp = a^2(a-2b)+b(a-2b)\\
        \amp = (a-2b)(a^2+b)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Factoring <m>ab-2a^2b+a^3-2b^2</m> results in <m>ab-2a^2b+a^3-2b^2= (a-2b)(a^2+b)</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p> Factor <m>x^3-x^2y-xy+y^2</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Factoring <m>x^3-x^2y_xy+y^2</m> results in <m>x^3-x^2y_xy+y^2=(x-y)(x^2-y)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<p>Not all factorable four-term polynomials can be factored with this technique. For example,</p>

<me>3x^3+5x^2-x+2.</me>

<p>This four-term polynomial cannot be grouped in any way to produce a common binomial factor. Despite this, the polynomial is not prime and can be written as a product of polynomials. It can be factored as follows:</p>

<me>3x^3+5x^2-x+2=(x+2)(3x^2-x+1)\text{.}</me>

<p>Factoring such polynomials is a topic for a more advanced algebra course. For now, we will limit our attempt to factor four-term polynomials to using the factor by grouping technique.</p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection><title>Factoring Special Binomials</title>

    <p>We begin with the special binomial called <term>difference of squares</term>:</p>

    <me>a^2-b^2=(a+b)(a-b)\text{.}</me>

    <p>To verify the above formula, multiply.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        (a+b)(a-b)\amp =a^2-ab+ba-b^2\\
        \amp = a^2 \alert{-ab+ab}-b^2\\
        \amp = a^2-b^2
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>We use this formula to factor certain special binomials.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p> Factor <m>x^2-9y^2</m>.</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
        <p>Identify the binomial as difference of squares and determine the square factors of each term.</p>

        <p>Here we can write </p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            x^2-9y^2=(\alert{x})^2-(\alert{3y})^2\text{.}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Substitute <m>a=x</m> and <m>b=3y</m> into the difference of squares formula.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            a^2-b^2\amp=(a+b)(a-b)\\
            x^2-9y^2\amp = (x+3y)(x-3y)
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>We can multiply to check.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            (x+3y)(x-3y)\amp = x^2-3xy+3xy-9y^2\\
            \amp = x^2-9y^2
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Factoring <m>x^2-9y^2</m> results in <m>x^2-9y^2=(x+3y)(x-3y)</m>.</p>

    </solution>
    </example>

    <example><statement>
        <p> Factor <m>x^2-(2x-1)^2</m>.</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
        <p>First, we identify this expression as a difference of squares.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            x^2-(2x-1)^2=(\alert{x})^2-(\alert{2x-1})^2
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Substitute <m>a=x</m> and <m>b=2x-1</m> into the difference of squares formula.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            a^2-b^2\amp=(a+b)(a-b)\\
            x^2-(2x-1)^2\amp = (x+(2x-1))(x-(2x-1))\\
            \amp=(x+2x-1)(x-2x+1)\\
            \amp = (3x-1)(-x+1)
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Factoring <m>x^2-(2x-1)^2</m> results in <m>x^2-(2x-1)^2=(3x-1)(-x+1)</m>.</p>

    </solution>
    </example>

        <p>The sum of squares <m>a^2+b^2</m> does not have a general factored equivalent over the real numbers. Care should be taken not to confuse this with the difference of squares.</p>

        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
            (a+b)^2\amp = (a+b)(a+b)\\
            \amp = a^2+ab+ba+b^2\\
            \amp = a^2+2ab+b^2
            \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>Therefore,</p>

        <me>(a+b)^2\neq a^2+b^2\text{.}</me>


        <p>It may be the case that the terms of a binomial have a common factor. If so, it will be difficult to identify it as a special binomial until we first factor out the GCF.</p>



        <p>When the degree of the special binomial is greater than two, we may need to apply the formulas multiple times to obtain a complete factorization. A polynomial is completely factored when it is prime or is written as a product of prime polynomials.</p>

           <!--

          <p>EXAMPLE</p>

          <p>When factoring, always look for resulting factors to factor further.</p>

          <p>EXAMPLE</p>

          <p>As an exercise, factor the previous example as a difference of cubes first and then compare the results. Why do you think we make it a rule to factor using difference of squares first?</p>
-->
    </subsection>

</section>

 <section  xml:id="Factoring-Trinomials"><title>Factoring Trinomials</title>
<introduction>
<p>Some trinomials of the form <m>x^2+bx+c</m> can be factored as a product of binomials. If a trinomial of this type factors, we have</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    x^2+bx+c \amp =(x+m)(x+n)\\
    \amp =x^2+nx+mx+mn\\
    \amp =x^2+(n+m)x+mn\text{.}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>This gives us</p>

<me>b=n+m \text{ and }c=mn.</me>

<p>In short, if the leading coefficient of a factorable trinomial is <m>1</m>, then the factors of the last term must add up to the coefficient of the middle term.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p> Factor <m>x^2+12x+20</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>

    <p>Determine the factors of the last term whose sum equals the coefficient of the middle term. To do this, list all of the factorizations of <m>20</m> and search for factors whose sum equals <m>12</m>.</p>



                <table><caption>Factors of<m>20</m></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>1\cdot 20</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>1 +20=21</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><m>2\cdot 10</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\alert{2 +10=12}</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><m>4\cdot 5</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>4 +5=9</m></cell>
                    </row>
                </tabular></table>



    <p>Choose <m>20 = 2 \cdot 10</m> because <m>2 + 10 = 12</m>. Therefore, <m>12=2x+10x</m>, and we can write <me>x^2+\alert{12x}+20=x^2+\alert{2x+10x}+20.</me>  </p>

    <p>We factor the equivalent expression by grouping.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         x^2+12x+20\amp = x^2+2x+10x+20\\
         \amp = x(x+2)+10(x+2)\\
         \amp = (x+10)(x+2)
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p> Our factored form is <m>(x+10)(x+2)</m>.</p>

    <p>We check by multiplying the two binomials.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        (x+2)(x+10)\amp =x^2+10x+2x+20\\
        \amp = x^2+12x+20
        \end{aligned}
        </me>
        
 <p>
 Note: We made a choice in the above problem to write <m>12x=2x+10x</m>.  What would happen if we instead had written <m>12x=10x+2x</m>?  Notice that in the following calculation the answer is equivalent.
 </p>
    <me>x^2+\alert{12x}+20=x^2+\alert{10x+2x}+20.</me>  </p>

    <p>We factor the equivalent expression by grouping.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         x^2+12x+20\amp = x^2+10x+2x+20\\
         \amp = x(x+10)+2(x+10)\\
         \amp = (x+2)(x+10)\\
         \amp = (x+10)(x+2)
         \end{aligned}
     </me>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Since multiplication is commutative, the order of the factors does not matter.</p>

   <me>
       \begin{aligned}
       x^2+12x+20 \amp = (x+2)(x+10)\\
       \amp = (x+10)(x+2)
       \end{aligned}
   </me>


   <p> If the last term of the trinomial is positive, then either both of the constant factors must be negative or both must be positive.</p>


   <example><statement>
       <p> Factor <m>x^2y^2-7xy+12</m>.</p>
   </statement>
   <solution>
       <p>We first factor <m>x^2y^2=xy\cdot xy</m>.</p>

       <me>\begin{aligned}
           x^2y^2-7xy+12= (xy\: \: \: )(xy\: \: \: )
           \end{aligned}
       </me>

       <p>Next, we search for factors of <m>12</m> whose sum is <m>-7</m>.</p>

       <md>
           <mrow> 12\amp = (-1)\cdot (-12) \: \rightarrow \: (-1) +(-12)=-13</mrow>
           <mrow> \amp = (-2)\cdot (-6) \: \rightarrow \: (-2) +(-6)=-8</mrow>
           <mrow> \amp = (-3)\cdot (-4) \: \rightarrow \: (-3) +(-4)=-7</mrow>
       </md>

       <p>We choose <m>-3</m> and <m>-4</m> because <m>-3 + (-4) = -7</m>. </p>

       <me>\begin{aligned}
             x^2y^2-7xy+12\amp = (xy\: \: \: )(xy\: \: \: )\\
             \amp =(xy-3)(xy-4)
             \end{aligned}
            </me>

       <p>We check by multiplying the two binomials.</p>

       <me>\begin{aligned}
           (xy-3)(xy-4)\amp =x^2y^2-4xy-3xy+12\\
           \amp =x^2y^2-7xy+12
           \end{aligned}
       </me>
   </solution>
   </example>

<p>Often our first guess will not produce a correct factorization. This process may require repeated trials. For this reason, the check is very important and is not optional.</p>

<p>If we choose the factors wisely, then we can reduce much of the guesswork in this process. However, if a guess is not correct, do not get discouraged; just try a different set of factors. Keep in mind that some polynomials are prime. For example, consider the trinomial <m>x^2+3x+20</m> and the factors of 20:</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    20\amp =1\cdot 20\\
    \amp = 2\cdot 10\\
    \amp=4\cdot 5
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>There are no integer factors of 20 whose sum is 3. Therefore, the original trinomial cannot be factored as a product of two binomials with integer coefficients. The trinomial is prime.</p>
</introduction>


<!--
  <subsection  xml:id="Factoring-Trinomials-Part2"><title>Factoring Trinomials of the Form <m>ax^2+bx+c</m></title>

<p>Factoring trinomials of the form <m>ax^2+bx+c</m> can be challenging because the middle term is affected by the factors of both <m>a</m> and <m>c</m>. In general,</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    \alert{a}x^2+\alert{b}x+\alert{c}\amp = (px+m)(qx+n)\\
    \amp = pqx^2+pnx+qmx+mn\\
    \amp =\alert{pq}x^2+\alert{(pn+qm)}x+\alert{mn}\text{.}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>This gives us</p>

<me>a=pq\text{ and }b=pn+qm,\text{ where }c=mn\text{.}</me>

      <p>In short, when the leading coefficient of a trinomial is something other than <m>1</m>, there will be more to consider when determining the factors using the trial and error method. The key lies in the understanding of how the middle term is obtained. Multiply <m>(5x+3)(2x+3)</m> and carefully follow the formation of the middle term.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    (5x+3)(2x+3)\amp = 5x\cdot 2x \stackrel{middle\: \: term}{\overbrace{\alert{+5x\cdot 3+3\cdot 2x}}}+3\cdot 3\\
    \amp = 10x^2\alert{+15x+6x}+9\\
    \amp=15x^2\alert{+21x}+9
    \end{aligned}
    </me>


<p>As we have seen before, the product of the first terms of each binomial is equal to the first term of the trinomial. The middle term of the trinomial is the sum of the products of the outer and inner terms of the binomials. The product of the last terms of each binomial is equal to the last term of the trinomial. Visually, we have the following.</p>

  <p> <image source="images/FactoringTrinomials1.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>For this reason, we need to look for products of the factors of the first and last terms whose sum is equal to the coefficient of the middle term. For example, to factor <m>6x^2+29x+35</m>, we look at the factors of <m>6</m> and <m>35</m>.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    6\amp =1\cdot 6\\
    6\amp = \alert{2\cdot 3}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    35\amp =1\cdot 35\\
    35\amp = \alert{5\cdot 7}
    \end{aligned}
</me>

<p>The combination that produces the coefficient of the middle term is <m> 2\cdot 7 +3\cdot 5=14+15=29</m>. Make sure that the outer terms have coefficients <m>2</m> and <m>7</m>, and that the inner terms have coefficients <m>5</m> and <m>3</m>. Use this information to factor the trinomial.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    6x^2+29x+35 \amp = (2x\: \: \: \: )(3x\: \: \: \: )\\
    \amp =(2x+5)(3x+7)
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>5x^2+16xy+3y^2</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                Since the leading coefficient and the last term are both prime, there is only one way to factor each.
            </p>

            <me> 5=1\cdot 5 \text{ and } 3=1\cdot 3</me>

            <p>We begin by writing the factors of the first term, <m>5x^2</m>, as follows.</p>

            <me>5x^2+16xy+3y^2=(x\: \: \: )(5x\: \: \: )</me>

            <p>The middle and last term are both positive; therefore, the factors of 3 are chosen as positive numbers. In this case, the only choice is in which grouping to place these factors: <m>(x+y)(5x+3y)</m> or <m>(x+3y)(5x+y)</m>.</p>

            <p> We will determine which grouping is correct by multiplying each expression.</p>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                (x+y)(5x+3y)\amp = 5x^2+3xy+5xy+3y^2\\
                \amp =5x^2+8xy+3y^2 \: \alert{\text{Incorrect}}\\
                (x+3y)(5x+y)\amp =5x^2+xy+15xy+3y^2\\
                \amp = 5x^2+16xy+3y^2
                \end{aligned}
                </me>

            <p> Our factored form is <m>5x^2+16xy+3y^2=(x+3y)(5x+y)</m>.</p>

        </solution>
    </example>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>18a^2b^2-ab-4</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        First, we consider the factors of the coefficients of the first and last terms.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        18\amp =1\cdot 18\\
        \amp = \alert{2\cdot 9}\\
        \amp =3\cdot 6\\
        4\amp =\alert{1\cdot 4}\\
        \amp =2\cdot 2
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>We are searching for products of factors whose sum equals the coefficient of the middle term, <m>-1</m>. After some thought, we can see that the sum of <m>8</m> and <m>-9</m> is <m>-1</m> and the combination that gives this follows.</p>

    <me>2(4)+9(-1)=8-9=-1</me>

    <p>We will use <m>2ab</m> and <m>9ab</m> as factors of <m>18a^2b^2</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        18a^2b^2-ab-4=(2ab \: \:)(9ab\: \: )
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Next we use the factors <m>1</m> and <m>4</m> in the correct order so that the inner and outer products are <m>-9ab</m> and <m>8ab</m> respectively.</p>

    <me>18a^2b^2-ab-4=(2ab-1)(9ab+4)</me>

    <p> Our factored form is <m>(2ab-1)(9ab+4)</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>


<p>It is a good practice to first factor out the GCF, if there is one. Doing this produces a trinomial factor with smaller coefficients. As we have seen, trinomials with smaller coefficients require much less effort to factor. This commonly overlooked step is worth identifying early.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>12y^3-26y^2-10y</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        First, we will factor out the GCF.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        12y^3-26y^2-10y=2y(6y^2-13y-5)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>After factoring out <m>2y</m>, the coefficients of the resulting trinomial are smaller and have fewer factors. We can factor the resulting trinomial using <m>6=2(3)</m> and <m>5=(5)(1)</m>. Notice that these factors can produce <m>-13</m> in two ways:</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        2(-5)+3(-1)=-10-3\amp =-13\\
        2(\alert{1})+3(\alert{-5})=2-15\amp =-13
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Since the last term is <m>-5</m>, the correct combination requires the factors <m>1</m> and <m>5</m> to be opposite signs. Here we use <m>2(1) = 2</m> and <m>3(-5) = -15</m> because the sum is <m>-13</m> and the product of <m>(1)(-5) = -5</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        12y^3-26y^2-10y\amp =2y(6y^2-13y-5)\\
        \amp = 2y(2y \: \: )(3y\: \: )\\
        \amp = 2y(2y-5)(3y+1)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>We check as follows.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        2y(2y-5)(3y+1) \amp =2y(6y^2+2y-15y-5)\\
        \amp = 2y(6y^2-13y-5)\\
        \amp =12y^3-26y^2-10y
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The factor <m>2y</m> is part of the factored form of the original expression; be sure to include it in the answer.</p>

    <p> Our factored form is <m>2y(2y-5)(3y+1)</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>



<p>It is also a good practice to consistently work with trinomials where the leading coefficient is positive. If the leading coefficient is negative, factor it out along with any GCF. Note that sometimes the factor will be <m>-1</m>.</p>

<exercise>
    <statement>
        <p>Factor <m>-2x^2+13x-20</m>.</p>
        </statement>

    <solution>
        <p>The factored form is <m>-(2x-5)(x-4)</m>.</p>
        </solution>
    </exercise>

</subsection>
-->

 <subsection  xml:id="Factoring-Trinomials-AC-Method"><title>Factoring Trinomials Using the <m>ac</m>-method</title>

 <p>An alternate technique for factoring trinomials, called the <m>ac</m> method, makes use of the grouping method for factoring four-term polynomials. If a trinomial in the form <m>ax^2+bx+c</m> can be factored, then the middle term, <m>bx</m>, can be replaced with two terms with coefficients whose sum is <m>b</m> and whose product is <m>ac</m>. This substitution results in an equivalent expression with four terms that can be factored by grouping.</p>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         Factor <m>18x^2-31x+6</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.
     </p></statement>
 <solution>
     <p>
         Here <m>a=18,\, b=-31</m>, and <m>c=6</m>.
     </p>

     <me> \begin{aligned}
         ac=18(6)=108
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p>Now we factor <m>108</m>, and search for factors whose sum is <m>-31</m>.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         108\amp = -1(-108)\\
         \amp = -2(-54)\\
         \amp= -3(-36)\\
         \amp = \alert{-4(-27)}\\
         \amp = -6(-18)\\
         \amp = -9(-12)
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p>In this case, the sum of the factors <m>-27</m> and <m>-4</m> equals the middle coefficient, <m>-31</m>. Therefore, <m>-31x=-27x-4x</m>, and we can write</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         18x^2\alert{-31x}+6=18x^2\alert{-27x-4x}+6\text{.}
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p>We factor the equivalent expression by grouping.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         18x^2-31x+6\amp = 18x^2-27x-4x+6\\
         \amp = 9x(2x-3)-2(2x-3)\\
         \amp = (2x-3)(9x-2)
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p> Our factored form is <m>(2x-3)(9x-2)</m>.</p>

 </solution>
 </example>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         Factor <m>4x^2y^2-7xy-15</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.
         </p></statement>
         <solution>
             <p>
                 Here <m>a=4,\, b=-7</m>, and <m>c=-15</m>.
             </p>

             <me> \begin{aligned}
                 ac=4(-15)=-60
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>Now we factor <m>-60</m>, and search for factors whose sum is <m>-7</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 -60\amp = 1(-60)\\
                 \amp = 2(-30)\\
                 \amp= 3(-20)\\
                 \amp = 4(-15)\\
                 \amp = \alert{5(-12)}\\
                 \amp = 6(-10)
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>In this case, the sum of the factors <m>5</m> and <m>-12</m> equals the middle coefficient, <m>-7</m>. Therefore, we replace <m>-7xy</m> with <m>5xy-12xy</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 4x^2y^2-7xy-15\amp = 4x^2y^2+5xy-12xy-15\\
                 \amp =xy(4xy+5)-3(4xy+5)\\
                 \amp = (4xy+5)(xy-3)
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p> Our factored form is <m>(4xy+5)(xy-3)</m>.</p>

         </solution>
     </example>
     
start here
     
     <example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>5x^2+16xy+3y^2</m>.
        </p></statement>
        
        <solution>
             <p>
                 Here <m>a=5,\, b=16y</m>, and <m>c=3y^2</m>.
             </p>

             <me> \begin{aligned}
                 ac=5(3y^2)=15y^2
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>Now we factor <m>15y^2</m>, and search for factors whose sum is <m>16y</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 15y^2\amp = \alert{1y(15y)}\\
                 \amp = 1y^2(15)\\
                 \amp = 1(15y^2)\\
                 \amp= 3y(5y)\\
                 \amp = 3(5y^2)\\
                 \amp = 3y^2(5)\\
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>In this case, the sum of the factors <m>1y</m> and <m>15y</m> equals the middle coefficient, <m>16y</m>. 
             Therefore, we replace <m>16xy</m> with <m>15xy+1xy</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 5x^2+16xy+3y^2\amp = 5x^2+15xy+1xy+3y^2\\
                 \amp =5x(x+3y)+1y(x+3y)\\
                 \amp = (5x+1y)(x+3y)\\
                 \amp = (5x+y)(x+3y)
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p> Our factored form is <m>(5x+y)(x+3y)</m>.</p>

         </solution>
        
    </example>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>18a^2b^2-ab-4</m>.
    </p></statement>
    
    <solution>
             <p>
                 Here <m>a=18,\, b=-1</m>, and <m>c=-4</m>.
             </p>

             <me> \begin{aligned}
                 ac=18(-4)=-72
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>Now we factor <m>-72</m>, and search for factors whose sum is <m>-1</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 -72\amp = -1(72)\\
                 \amp = 1(-72)\\
                 \amp = -2(36)\\
                 \amp = 2(-36)\\
                 \amp = -4(18)\\
                 \amp = 4(-18)\\
                 \amp = -8(9)\\
                 \amp = \alert{8(-9)}\\
                 \amp = -24(3)\\
                 \amp = 24(-3)\\
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p>In this case, the sum of the factors <m>8</m> and <m>-9</m> equals the middle coefficient, <m>-1</m>. 
             Therefore, we replace <m>-ab</m> with <m>8ab-9ab</m>.</p>

             <me>\begin{aligned}
                 18a^2b^2-ab-4\amp = 18a^2b^2+(8ab-9ab)-4\\
                 \amp =18a^2b^2+(-9ab+8ab)-4\\
                 \amp =18a^2b^2-9ab+8ab-4\\
                 \amp =9ab(2ab-1)-4(2ab-1)\\
                 \amp = (9ab+4)(2ab-1)\\
                 \end{aligned}
             </me>

             <p> Our factored form is <m>(9ab+4)(2ab-1)</m>.</p>

         </solution>
    
    
<!--<solution>
    <p>
        First, we consider the factors of the coefficients of the first and last terms.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        18\amp =1\cdot 18\\
        \amp = \alert{2\cdot 9}\\
        \amp =3\cdot 6\\
        4\amp =\alert{1\cdot 4}\\
        \amp =2\cdot 2
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>We are searching for products of factors whose sum equals the coefficient of the middle term, <m>-1</m>. After some thought, we can see that the sum of <m>8</m> and <m>-9</m> is <m>-1</m> and the combination that gives this follows.</p>

    <me>2(4)+9(-1)=8-9=-1</me>

    <p>We will use <m>2ab</m> and <m>9ab</m> as factors of <m>18a^2b^2</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        18a^2b^2-ab-4=(2ab \: \:)(9ab\: \: )
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Next we use the factors <m>1</m> and <m>4</m> in the correct order so that the inner and outer products are <m>-9ab</m> and <m>8ab</m> respectively.</p>

    <me>18a^2b^2-ab-4=(2ab-1)(9ab+4)</me>

    <p> Our factored form is <m>(2ab-1)(9ab+4)</m>.</p>

</solution>-->
</example>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Factor <m>12y^3-26y^2-10y</m>.
    </p></statement>
<!--<solution>
    <p>
        First, we will factor out the GCF.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        12y^3-26y^2-10y=2y(6y^2-13y-5)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>After factoring out <m>2y</m>, the coefficients of the resulting trinomial are smaller and have fewer factors. We can factor the resulting trinomial using <m>6=2(3)</m> and <m>5=(5)(1)</m>. Notice that these factors can produce <m>-13</m> in two ways:</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        2(-5)+3(-1)=-10-3\amp =-13\\
        2(\alert{1})+3(\alert{-5})=2-15\amp =-13
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Since the last term is <m>-5</m>, the correct combination requires the factors <m>1</m> and <m>5</m> to be opposite signs. Here we use <m>2(1) = 2</m> and <m>3(-5) = -15</m> because the sum is <m>-13</m> and the product of <m>(1)(-5) = -5</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        12y^3-26y^2-10y\amp =2y(6y^2-13y-5)\\
        \amp = 2y(2y \: \: )(3y\: \: )\\
        \amp = 2y(2y-5)(3y+1)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>We check as follows.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        2y(2y-5)(3y+1) \amp =2y(6y^2+2y-15y-5)\\
        \amp = 2y(6y^2-13y-5)\\
        \amp =12y^3-26y^2-10y
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The factor <m>2y</m> is part of the factored form of the original expression; be sure to include it in the answer.</p>

    <p> Our factored form is <m>2y(2y-5)(3y+1)</m>.</p>

</solution>-->
</example>
     
     
     

 <exercise>
     <statement>
         <p>Factor <m>2x^2-9x-5</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.</p>
     </statement>

     <solution>
         <p>The factored form is <m>(2x+1)(x-5)</m>.</p>
     </solution>
 </exercise>

<exercise>
    <statement>
        <p>Factor <m>6x^2+7x-10</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.</p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
        <p>The factored form is <m>(6x-5)(x+2)</m>.</p>
    </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
    <statement>
        <p>Factor <m>9x^2+6x-8</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.</p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
        <p>The factored form is <m>(3x-2)(3x+4)</m>.</p>
    </solution>
</exercise>

<p>If factors of <m>ac</m> cannot be found to add up to <m>b</m> then the trinomial is prime.</p>



</subsection>


 </section>

 <section  xml:id="Solving-Polynomial-Equations"><title>Solving Polynomial Equations by Factoring</title>

<subsection><title>Reviewing General Factoring Strategies</title>

<p>We have learned various techniques for factoring polynomials with up to four terms. The challenge is to identify the type of polynomial and then decide which method to apply. The following outlines a general guideline for factoring polynomials:</p>

<p>
    <ol label="1">
        <li><p>Check for common factors. If the terms have common factors, then factor out the greatest common factor (GCF).</p></li>
        <li><p>Determine the number of terms in the polynomial.</p>
            <ol label="a">
                <li><p>Factor four-term polynomials by grouping.</p></li>
                <li><p>Factor trinomials (3 terms) using “trial and error” or the <m>ac</m> method.</p></li>
                <li><p>Factor binomials (2 terms) using the special product difference of squares.</p></li>
            </ol></li>
        <li><p>Look for factors that can be factored further.</p></li>
        <li><p>Check by multiplying.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p>

<p>If an expression has a GCF, then factor this out first. Doing so is often overlooked and typically results in factors that are easier to work with. Furthermore, look for the resulting factors to factor further; many factoring problems require more than one step. A polynomial is completely factored when none of the factors can be factored further.</p>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Solving Polynomial Equations by Factoring</title>
<p>In this section, we will review a technique that can be used to solve certain polynomial equations. We begin with the <term>zero product property</term>:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>a\cdot b=0 \text{ if and only if }a=0\text{ or }b=0</mrow>
    </md>

<p>The zero-product property is true for any number of factors that make up an equation. In other words, if any product is equal to zero, then at least one of the variable factors must be equal to zero. If an expression is equal to zero and can be factored into linear factors, then we will be able to set each factor equal to zero and solve each equation.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Solve <m>2x(x-4)(5x+3)=0</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
               We set each variable factor equal to zero and solve.
            </p>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                2x\amp= 0\\
                \frac{2x}{\alert{2}}\amp =\frac{0}{\alert{2}}\\
                x\amp =0
                \end{aligned}
                </me>
            <p>OR</p>
            <me>\begin{aligned}
                x-4\amp= 0\\
                x\amp =4
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

            <p>OR</p>
            <me>\begin{aligned}
                5x+3\amp= 0\\
                5x\amp = -3\\
                \frac{5x}{\alert{5}}\amp =\frac{-3}{\alert{5}}\\
                x\amp = -\frac{3}{5}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

            <p>To check that these are solutions we can substitute back into the original equation to see if we obtain a true statement. Note that each solution produces a zero factor. </p>

            <p> The solutions are <m>x=0,4,-\frac{3}{5}</m>.</p>

        </solution>
    </example>

<p>Of course, most equations will not be given in factored form.</p>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Solve <m>x^2-2x-35=0</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We will first factor <m>x^2-2x-35</m> using the <m>ac</m>-method.
    </p>

    <p>
        Here <m>a=1,\, b=-2</m>, and <m>c=-35</m>.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        ac=1(-35)=-35
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Now we factor <m>-35</m>, and search for factors whose sum is <m>-2</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        -35\amp = -1(35)\\
        \amp = -5(7)\\
        \amp = \alert{-7(5)}\\
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>In this case, the sum of the factors <m>-7</m> and <m>5</m> equals the middle coefficient, <m>-2</m>. Therefore, <m>-2x=5x-7x</m>, and we can write</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        x^2-2x-35+6=x^2+5x-7x-35.
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>We factor the equivalent expression by grouping.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
          x^2-2x-35+6\amp =x^2+5x-7x-35\\
        \amp = x(x+5)-7(x+5)\\
        \amp = (x+5)(x-7)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p> Our factored form is <m>(x+5)(x-7)</m>. Now we can use the zero factor property to solve by setting each variable factor equal to zero.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        x+5\amp= 0\\
        x\amp =-5
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    <p>OR</p>
    <me>\begin{aligned}
        x-7\amp= 0\\
        x\amp =7
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>To check that these are solutions we can substitute back into the original equation to see if we obtain a true statement. Note that each solution produces a zero factor. </p>

    <p> The solutions are <m>x=-5,7</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>


<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        Solve <m>x^2-8x-33=0</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p> The solutions are <m>x=-3,11</m>.</p>

</solution>
</exercise>


<p>Using the zero-product property after factoring an expression that is equal to zero is the key to this technique. However, the expression may not be given equal to zero, and so there may be some preliminary steps before factoring. The steps required to solve by factoring are outlined in the following example.</p>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Solve <m>15x^2+3x-8=5x-7</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We will first express the equation in standard form, with zero on the right hand side.
    </p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        15x^2+3x-8\amp =5x-7\\
        15x^2-5x+3x-8+7\amp =0\\
        15x^2-2x-1\amp =0
        \end{aligned}
        </me>

    <p>
        Now we can factor.
    </p>

    <me> \begin{aligned}
        (3x-1)(5x+1)=0
        \end{aligned}
    </me>


    <p> Now we can use the zero factor property to solve by setting each variable factor equal to zero.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        3x-1\amp= 0\\
        3x\amp =1\\
        x\amp =\frac{1}{3}
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    <p>OR</p>
    <me>\begin{aligned}
        5x+1\amp= 0\\
        5x\amp =-1\\
        x\amp=-\frac{1}{5}
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>To check that these are solutions we can substitute back into the original equation to see if we obtain a true statement. Note that each solution produces a zero factor. </p>

    <p> The solutions are <m>x=\frac{1}{3},-\frac{1}{5}</m>.</p>

</solution>
</example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        Solve <m>(3x+2)(x+1)=4</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p> The solutions are <m>x=\frac{1}{3}, -2</m>.</p>

</solution>
</exercise>



</subsection>

<subsection><title>Finding Roots of Functions</title>
<p>Any polynomial with one variable is a function and can be written in the form,</p>

<me>f(x)=a_nx^n+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\cdots +a_1x+a_0.</me>

<p>A <term>root</term> of a function is a value in the domain that results in zero. In other words, the roots occur when the function is equal to zero, <m>f(x)=0</m>.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Find the roots of <m>f(x)=(x+2)^2-4</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                To find the roots we set the function equal to zero and solve.
            </p>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                f(x)\amp = 0\\
                (x+2)^2-4\amp =0\\
                x^2+4x+4-4\amp =0\\
                x^2+4x\amp =0\\
                x(x+4)\amp =0
                \end{aligned}
                </me>

            <p>Next, we set each factor equal to zero and solve.</p>

            <me> \begin{aligned}
                x=0 \: \: \: \: \: \amp \text{ or }\amp x+4\amp =0\\
                \amp\amp x\amp = -4
                \end{aligned}
                </me>

            <p>We can show that these <m>x</m>-values are roots by evaluating.</p>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                f(0)\amp = (0+2)^2-4\\
                \amp =4-4\\
                \amp =0
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

            <me>\begin{aligned}
                f(-4)\amp = (-4+2)^2-4\\
                \amp =(-2)^2-4\\
                \amp =4-4\\
                \amp =0
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

            <p>The roots are <m>0</m> and <m>-4</m>.</p>

        </solution>
    </example>


    <p>If we graph the function in the previous example we will see that the roots correspond to the <m>x</m>-intercepts of the function. Here the function <m>f</m>
        is a basic parabola shifted 2 units to the left and 4 units down. Note: Shifts will be covered later but we include the description here so you can get used to the language.</p>

      <p> <image source="images/SolvingPolynomials1.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Find the roots of <m>f(x)=-x^2+10x-25</m>.
            </p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    To find the roots we set the function equal to zero and solve.
                </p>

                <me>\begin{aligned}
                    f(x)\amp = 0\\
                    -x^2+10x-25\amp =0\\
                   -(x^2-10x+25)\amp =0\\
                    -(x-5)(x-5)\amp =0\\
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>

                <p>Next, we set each variable factor equal to zero and solve.</p>

                <me> \begin{aligned}
                    x-5\amp=0\: \: \: \: \: \amp \text{ or }\: \: \: \: \: x-5\amp =0\\
                    x\amp =5\amp x\amp = 5.
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>

                <p>A solution that is repeated twice is called a double root. The double root is <m>5</m>.</p>

            </solution>
        </example>

        <p>The previous example shows that a function of degree <m>2</m> can have one root. From the factoring step, we see that the function can be written</p>

        <me>f(x)=-(x-5)^2.</me>

        <p>As we see below, the vertex on the graph is the <m>x</m>-intercept, illustrating the fact that there is only one root.</p>

          <p> <image source="images/SolvingPolynomials2.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

        <exercise><statement>
            <p>
                Solve <m>(6x-5)(x+7)=0</m>.
                </p></statement>
                <solution>
                    <p>
                        The solutions are <m>x=\frac{5}{6},/, -7</m>.
                    </p>
                </solution>
            </exercise>

  <exercise><statement>
      <p>
          Solve <m>(6x+1)(x+1)=6</m>.
      </p></statement>
  <solution>
      <p>
          The solutions are <m>x=-\frac{5}{3},/, \frac{1}{2}</m>.
      </p>
  </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise><statement>
      <p>
          Solve <m>4x^2+5x-5=15(3-2x)</m>.
      </p></statement>
  <solution>
      <p>
          The solutions are <m>x=\frac{5}{4},/, -10</m>.
      </p>
  </solution>
  </exercise>

  <example><statement>
      <p>
          Assuming dry road conditions and average reaction times, the safe stopping distance in feet is given by <m>d(x)=\frac{1}{20}x^2+x</m>, where <m>x</m> represents the speed of the car in miles per hour. Determine the safe speed of the car if you expect to stop in <m>40</m> feet.
          </p></statement>
          <solution>
              <p>
                  We are asked to find the speed <m>x</m> where the safe stopping distance is <m>d(x)=40</m>
                  feet.
              </p>

              <me>\begin{aligned}
                  d(x)\amp = 40\\
                  \frac{1}{20}x^2+x\amp =40
                  \end{aligned}
                  </me>

              <p>To solve for <m>x</m>, we rewrite the resulting equation in standard form. In this case, we will first multiply both sides by <m>20</m> to clear the fraction.</p>

              <me>
                  \begin{aligned}
                  \alert{20}\left(\frac{1}{20}x^2+x\right)\amp =\alert{20}(40)\\
                  x^2+20x\amp = 800\\
                  x^2+20x-800\amp =0
                  \end{aligned}
                  </me>

            <p>Next, we factor and then set each factor equal to zero.</p>

            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                x^2+20x-800\amp =0\\
                (x+40)(x-20)\amp =0
                \end{aligned}
            </me>

        <p>This means</p>

        <me> \begin{aligned}
            x+40\amp =0 \: \: \: \: \: \amp \text{ or }\amp x-20\amp =0\\
            x\amp =-40\amp\amp x\amp =20.
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>Since the negative answer does not make sense in the context of this problem, we consider <m>x=20</m> miles per hour to be the only solution.</p>
          </solution>
      </example>


</subsection>

 </section>

 <section  xml:id="Algebraic-Fractions"><title>Algebraic Fractions</title>

     <subsection><title>Identifying Restrictions and Simplifying</title>

 <p><term>Algebraic fractions</term>, or rational functions, have the form</p>

 <me>r(x)=\frac{p(x)}{q(x)}</me>,

 <p>where <m>p(x)</m> and <m>q(x)</m> are polynomials and <m>q(x)\neq 0</m>. The domain of an algebraic fraction consists of all real numbers <m>x</m> except those where the denominator <m>q(x)=0</m>. <term>Restrictions</term> on the domain are real numbers for which the expression is undefined. For example, consider the function</p>

 <me>f(x)=\frac{(x-1)(x-3)}{(x-2)(x-3)}.</me>

 <p>Since rational expressions are undefined when the denominator is <m>0</m>, we wish to find the values for <m>x</m> that make it <m>0</m>. To do this, apply the zero-product property. Set each factor in the denominator equal to <m>0</m> and solve.</p>

 <me> \begin{aligned}
     x-2\amp =0 \: \: \: \: \: \amp \text{ or }\: \: \: \: \: x-3\amp =0\\
     x\amp =2\amp x\amp =3
     \end{aligned}
 </me>

 <p>Therefore, the original function is defined for any real number except <m>2</m> and <m>3</m>. We can express its domain using notation as follows:</p>

 <me>x\neq 2,3 \: \: \: \: \: \text{ or }\: \: \: \: \: (-\infty, 2)\cup(2,3)\cup(3,\infty)</me>

 <p>The restrictions to the domain of an algebraic fraction are determined by the denominator. Once the restrictions are determined we can cancel factors and obtain an equivalent function as follows:</p>

   <p> <image source="images/RationalFunctions1.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

 <p>It is important to note that <m>1</m> is not a restriction to the domain because the expression is defined as <m>0</m> when the numerator is <m>0</m>. In fact, <m>x=1</m> is a root. This function is graphed below:</p>

    <p> <image source="images/RationalFunctions2.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

 <p>Notice that there is a vertical asymptote at the restriction <m>x=2</m> and the graph is left undefined at the restriction <m>x=3</m> as indicated by the open dot, or hole, in the graph. Graphing algebraic fractions in general is beyond the scope of this course. However, it is useful at this point to know that the restrictions are an important part of the graph of algebraic fractions.</p>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         State the restrictions and simplify the algebraic fraction <m>g(x)=\frac{24x^7}{6x^5}</m>.
         </p></statement>
         <solution>
             <p>Since <m>g(x)</m> is an algebraic fraction, it is undefined, or restricted, where its denominator, <m>6x^5</m> is zero.
                 This means the function is undefined where <m>x</m> is <m>0</m>.
             </p>

             <me>g(0)=\frac{24(0)^7}{6(0)^5}=\frac{0}{0} \: \: \: \alert{\text{Undefined}}</me>

             <p>Therefore, the domain consists of all real numbers <m>x</m>, where <m>x\neq 0</m>. With this understanding, we can simplify by reducing the rational expression to lowest terms. Cancel common factors.</p>

             <me>g(x)=\frac{24x^7}{6x^5}=\frac{4\cdot 6 x^2\cdot x^5}{6x^5}=4x^2</me>

             <p> Our answer is <m>g(x)=4x^2</m>, where <m>x\neq 0</m>.</p>
         </solution>
     </example>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         State the restrictions and simplify the algebraic fraction <m>g(x)=\frac{2x^2+5x-3}{4x^2-1}</m>.
     </p></statement>
 <solution>
     <p>First, we factor the numerator and denominator.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         g(x)\amp =\frac{2x^2+5x-3}{4x^2-1}\\
         \amp =\frac{(2x-1)(x+3)}{(2x+1)(2x-1)}
         \end{aligned}
         </me>

     <p>Since <m>g(x)</m> is an algebraic fraction, it is undefined, or restricted, where its denominator is zero.
     </p>

     <me> \begin{aligned}
         2x+1\amp =0 \: \: \: \: \: \amp \text{ or }\: \: \: \: \: 2x-1\amp =0\\
         2x\amp =-1\amp 2x\amp =1\\
         x\amp =-\frac{1}{2}\amp x\amp =\frac{1}{2}
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p>Therefore, the domain consists of all real numbers <m>x</m>, where <m>x\neq -\frac{1}{2},\frac{1}{2}</m>. With this understanding, we can simplify by reducing the rational expression to lowest terms. Cancel common factors.</p>

     <me>g(x)=\frac{(2x-1)(x+3)}{(2x+1)(2x-1)}=\frac{x+3}{2x+1}</me>

     <p> Our answer is <m>g(x)=\frac{x+3}{2x+1}</m>, where <m>x\neq -\frac{1}{2},\frac{1}{2}</m>.</p>
 </solution>
 </example>

 <p>Occasionally we will have to factor out a negative one to simplify an algebraic fraction as much as possible.</p>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         State the restrictions and simplify the algebraic fraction <m>g(x)=\frac{25-x^2}{x^2-10x+25}</m>.
     </p></statement>
 <solution>
     <p>First, we factor the numerator and denominator.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         g(x)\amp =\frac{25-x^2}{x^2-10x+25}\\
         \amp =\frac{(5-x)(5+x)}{(x-5)(x-5)}\\
         \amp = \frac{\alert{-1\cdot (x-5)}(5+x)}{(x-5)(x-5)}\\
         \amp=\frac{-1(5+x)}{(x-5)}\\
         \amp = -\frac{x+5}{x-5}\\
         \end{aligned}
     </me>


     <p> Our answer is <m>g(x)=-\frac{x+5}{x-5}</m>, where <m>x\neq 5</m>.</p>
 </solution>
 </example>

 <p>It is important to remember that we can only cancel factors of a product. A common mistake is to cancel terms. </p>


 <exercise><statement>
     <p>
         State the restrictions and simplify <m>f(x)=\frac{x-2x^2}{4x^4-x^2}</m>.
     </p></statement>
 <solution>

     <p> Our answer is <m>f(x)=-\frac{1}{x(2x+1)}</m>, where <m>x\neq 0,-\frac{1}{2},\frac{1}{2}</m>.</p>
 </solution>
 </exercise>

 <p>In some examples, we will make a broad assumption that the denominator is nonzero. When we make that assumption, we do not need to determine the restrictions.</p>

 <example><statement>
     <p>
         Given <m>f(x)=x^2-2x+5</m>, simplify <m>\frac{f(x)-f(3)}{ax-3a}</m>. Assume all denominators are nonzero.
     </p></statement>
 <solution>
     <p>First, we calculate <m>f(3)</m>.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         f(3)\amp = (3)^2-2(3)+5\\
         \amp = 9-6+5\\
         \amp =3+5\\
         \amp =8.
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p>Now we substitute into the quotient.</p>

     <me>\begin{aligned}
         \frac{f(x)-f(3)}{ax-3a}\amp = \frac{x^2-2x+5-8}{ax-3a}\\
         \amp = \frac{x^2-2x-3}{ax-3a}\\
         \amp =\frac{(x+1)(x-3)}{a(x-3)}\\
         \amp =\frac{x+1}{a}
         \end{aligned}
     </me>

     <p> Our answer is <m>\frac{f(x)-f(3)}{ax-3a}=\frac{x+1}{a}</m>.</p>
 </solution>
 </example>


 </subsection>

<subsection><title>Multiplying and Dividing Algebraic Fractions</title>
    <p>When multiplying fractions, we can multiply the numerators and denominators together and then reduce. Multiplying rational expressions is performed in a similar manner. In general, given polynomials <m>P, Q, R,</m> and <m>S</m>, where <m>Q\neq 0</m>
        and <m>S\neq 0</m>, we have</p>

    <me>\frac{P}{Q}\cdot\frac{R}{S}=\frac{PR}{QS}.</me>

    <p>The restrictions to the domain of a product consist of the restrictions of each function.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Given <m>f(x)=\frac{9x^2-25}{x-5}</m> and <m>g(x)=\frac{x^2-2x-15}{3x+5}</m>, find <m>(f\cdot g)(x)</m> and determine the restrictions on the domain.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>In this case, the domain of <m>f</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>5</m>, and the domain of <m>g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>-\frac{5}{3}</m>. Therefore, the domain of the product consists of all real numbers except <m>5</m> and <m>-\frac{5}{3}</m>. Multiply the functions and then simplify the result.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            (f\cdot g)(x)\amp = f(x)\cdot g(x)\\
            \amp =\frac{9x^2-25}{x-5}\cdot \frac{x^2-2x-15}{3x+5}\\
            \amp =\frac{(3x+5)(3x-5)}{x-5}\cdot\frac{(x-5)(x+3)}{3x+5}\\
            \amp=\frac{(3x-5)(x+3)}{1}\\
            \amp =(3x-5)(x+3)
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p> Our answer is <m>(f\cdot g)(x)=(3x-5)(x+3)</m> where <m>x\neq 5,-\frac{5}{3}</m>.</p>
    </solution>
    </example>

    <p>To divide two fractions, we multiply by the reciprocal of the divisor. Dividing rational expressions is performed in a similar manner. In general, given polynomials <m>P, Q, R</m>, and <m>S</m>, where <m>Q\neq 0</m>, <m>R\neq 0</m>, and <m>S\neq 0</m>, we have</p>

    <me>\frac{P}{Q}\div\frac{R}{S}=\frac{\frac{P}{Q}}{\frac{R}{S}}=\frac{P}{Q}\cdot \frac{S}{R}=\frac{PS}{QR}</me>

    <p>The restrictions to the domain of a quotient will consist of the restrictions of each function as well as the restrictions on the reciprocal of the divisor.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Given <m>f(x)=\frac{2x^2+13x-7}{x^2-4x-21}</m> and <m>g(x)=\frac{2x^2+5x-3}{49-x^2}</m>, find <m>\left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)</m> and determine the restrictions on the domain.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)\amp = f(x)\div g(x)\\
            \amp =\frac{2x^2+13x-7}{x^2-4x-21}\div \frac{2x^2+5x-3}{49-x^2}\\
            \amp =\frac{2x^2+13x-7}{x^2-4x-21}\cdot\frac{49-x^2}{2x^2+5x-3}\\
            \amp=\frac{(2x-1)(x+7)(7+x)(-1)(x-7)}{(x+3)(x-7)(2x-1)(x+3)}\\
            \amp =-\frac{(x+7)^2}{(x+3)^2}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p>In this case, the domain of <m>f</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>-3</m> and <m>7</m>, and the domain of <m>g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>7</m> and <m>-7</m>. In addition, the reciprocal of <m>g(x)</m> has a restriction of <m>-3</m> and <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>. Therefore, the domain of this quotient consists of all real numbers except <m>-3, \frac{1}{2}, 7</m> and <m>-7</m>.</p>

        <p> Our answer is <m>\left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)=-\frac{(x+7)^2}{(x+3)^2}</m> where <m>x\neq -3,\frac{1}{2},7,-7</m>.</p>
    </solution>
    </example>


    <exercise><statement>
        <p>
            Given <m>f(x)=\frac{2x+5}{3x^2+14x-5}</m> and <m>g(x)=\frac{6x^2+13x-5}{x+5}</m>, find <m>\left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)</m> and determine the restrictions on the domain.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>Our answer is <m>\left(\frac{f}{g}\right)(x)=\frac{1}{(3x-1)^2}</m> where <m>x\neq -5,-\frac{5}{2},\frac{1}{3}</m>.</p>
        </solution>
    </exercise>

    <p>If a cost function <m>C</m> represents the cost of producing <m>x</m> units, then the average cost <m>A</m> is the cost divided by the number of units produced.</p>

        <me>A(x)=\frac{C(x)}{x}</me>


    <example><statement>
        <p>
            A manufacturer has determined that the cost in dollars of producing sweaters is given by <m>C(x)=0.01x^2-3x+1200</m>, where <m>x</m> represents the number of sweaters produced daily. Determine the average cost of producing <m>100, 200</m>, and <m>300</m> sweaters per day.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>

        <p>First we set up a function representing the average cost.</p>

        <me>A(x)=\frac{C(x)}{x}=\frac{0.01x^2-3x+1200}{x}</me>

        <p> Next, we calculate <m>A(100), A(200)</m>, and <m>A(300)</m>.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            A(100)\amp =\frac{0.01(\alert{100})^2-3(\alert{100})+1200}{(\alert{100})}=\frac{100-300+1200}{100}=\frac{1000}{100}=10\\
            A(200)\amp =\frac{0.01(\alert{200})^2-3(\alert{200})+1200}{(\alert{200})}=\frac{400-600+1200}{200}=\frac{1000}{200}=5\\
            A(300)\amp =\frac{0.01(\alert{300})^2-3(\alert{300})+1200}{(\alert{300})}=\frac{900-900+1200}{300}=\frac{1200}{300}=4\\
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

            <p> The average cost of producing <m>100</m> sweaters per day is <m>$10.00</m> per sweater. If <m>200</m> sweaters are produced, the average cost per sweater is <m>$5.00</m>. If <m>300</m> are produced, the average cost per sweater is <m>$4.00</m>.</p>
        </solution>
    </example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Adding and Subtracting Algebraic Fractions</title>

    <p>Adding and subtracting rational expressions is similar to adding and subtracting fractions. Recall that if the denominators are the same, we can add or subtract the numerators and write the result over the common denominator. When working with rational expressions, the common denominator will be a polynomial. In general, given polynomials <m>P, Q</m>, and <m>R</m>, where <m>Q\neq 0</m>, we have the following:</p>

    <me>\frac{P}{Q}\pm\frac{R}{Q}=\frac{P\pm R}{Q}</me>

    <p>The set of restrictions to the domain of a sum or difference of rational expressions consists of the restrictions to the domains of each expression.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Subtract: <m>\frac{4x}{x^2-64}-\frac{3x+8}{x^2-64}</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>

        <p>Since the denominators are the same, we can subtract the numerators and write the result over the common denominator. Take care to distribute the negative <m>1</m>.</p>

        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \frac{4x}{x^2-64}-\frac{3x+8}{x^2-64}\amp = \frac{4x-(3x+8)}{x^2-64}\\
            \amp = \frac{4x-3x-8}{x^2-64}\\
            \amp = \frac{x-8}{(x+8)(x-8)}\\
            \amp = \frac{1}{x+8}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>

        <p> Our solution is <m>\frac{1}{x+8}</m> for all real numbers <m>x\neq \pm 8</m>.</p>
    </solution>
    </example>

    </subsection>
    <conclusion>

<p>To add or subtract rational expressions with unlike denominators, we first find equivalent expressions with common denominators. We do this just as we have with fractions. If the denominators of fractions are relatively prime, then the least common denominator (LCD) is their product. For example,</p>

<me>\frac{1}{x}+\frac{1}{y} \implies \text{LCD}=x\cdot y=xy.</me>

<p>Multiply each fraction by the appropriate form of <m>1</m> to obtain equivalent fractions with a common denominator.</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    \frac{1}{x}+\frac{1}{y}\amp =\frac{1}{x}\cdot\alert{\frac{y}{y}}+\frac{1}{y}\cdot\alert{\frac{x}{x}}\\
    \amp = \frac{y}{xy}+\frac{x}{xy}\\
    \amp = \frac{y+x}{xy}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>In general, given polynomials <m>P, Q, R</m>, and <m>S</m>, where <m>Q\neq 0</m> and <m>S\neq 0</m>, we have the following:</p>

<me>\frac{P}{Q}\pm\frac{R}{S}=\frac{PS\pm QR}{QS}</me>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=\frac{5x}{3x+1}</m> and <m>g(x)=\frac{2}{x+1}</m>, find <m>f+g</m> and determine the restrictions.
    </p></statement>
<solution>

    <p>Here the LCD is the product of the denominators <m>(3x+1)(x+1)</m>. We multiply by the appropriate factors to obtain rational expressions with a common denominator before adding.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        (f+g)(x)\amp = f(x)+g(x)\\
        \amp =\frac{5x}{3x+1}+\frac{2}{x+1}\\
        \amp =\frac{5x}{3x+1}\cdot\alert{\frac{(x+1)}{(x+1)}}+\frac{2}{x+1}\cdot\alert{\frac{(3x+1)}{(3x+1)}}\\
        \amp = \frac{5x(x+1)}{(3x+1)(x+1)}+\frac{2(3x+1)}{(x+1)(3x+1)}\\
        \amp=\frac{5x(x+1)+2(3x+1)}{(3x+1)(x+1)}\\
        \amp = \frac{5x^2+5x+6x+2}{(3x+1)(x+1)}\\
        \amp =\frac{5x^2+11x+2}{(3x+1)(x+1)}\\
        \amp =\frac{(5x+1)(x+2)}{(3x+1)(x+1)}\\
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The domain of <m>f</m> consists all real numbers except <m>-\frac{1}{3}</m>, and the domain of <m>g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>-1</m>. Therefore, the domain of <m>f + g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>-1</m> and <m>-\frac{1}{3}</m>.</p>

    <p> Our solution is <m>\frac{(5x+1)(x+2)}{(3x+1)(x+1)}</m> for all real numbers <m>x\neq -1,-\frac{1}{3}</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>It is not always the case that the LCD is the product of the given denominators. Typically, the denominators are not relatively prime; thus determining the LCD requires some thought. Begin by factoring all denominators. The LCD is the product of all factors with the highest power.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Given <m>f(x)=\frac{3x}{3x-1}</m> and <m>g(x)=\frac{4-14x}{3x^2-4x+1}</m>, find <m>f-g</m> and determine the restrictions.
    </p></statement>
<solution>

    <p>To determine the LCD, factor the denominator of <m>g</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        (f-g)(x)\amp = f(x)-g(x)\\
        \amp =\frac{3x}{3x-1} -\frac{4-14x}{3x^2-4x+1}\\
        \amp=\frac{3x}{3x-1} -\frac{4-14x}{(3x-1)(x-1)}\\
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>In this case the LCD<m>=(3x-1)(x-1)</m>. Multiply <m>f</m> by <m>1</m> in the form of <m>\frac{(x-1)}{(x-1)}</m> to obtain equivalent algebraic fractions with a common denominator and then subtract. </p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        (f-g)(x)\amp = f(x)-g(x)\\
        \amp =\frac{3x}{3x-1}\cdot\alert{\frac{(x-1)}{(x-1)}} -\frac{4-14x}{(3x-1)(x-1)}\\
        \amp=\frac{3x(x-1)-4+14x}{(3x-1)(x-1)}\\
        \amp =\frac{(3x-1)(x+4)}{(3x-1)(x-1)}\\\\
        \amp = \frac{(x+4)}{(x-1)}
        \end{aligned}
    </me>


    <p>The domain of <m>f</m> consists all real numbers except <m>\frac{1}{3}</m>, and the domain of <m>g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>1</m> and <m>\frac{1}{3}</m>. Therefore, the domain of <m>f - g</m> consists of all real numbers except <m>1</m> and <m>\frac{1}{3}</m>.</p>

    <p> Our solution is <m>\frac{x+4}{x-1}</m> for all real numbers <m>x\neq 1, \frac{1}{3}</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{-2x}{x+6}-\frac{3x}{6-x}-\frac{18(x-2)}{x^2-36}</m> and determine the restrictions.
    </p></statement>
<solution>

    <p> Our solution is <m>\frac{1}{x-1}</m> for all real numbers <m>x\neq \pm 1</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>


<exercise><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{x+1}{(x-1^2)}-\frac{2}{x^2-1}-\frac{4}{(x+1)(x-1)^2}</m> and determine the restrictions.
    </p></statement>
<solution>

<p> Our solution is <m>\frac{1}{x-1}</m> for all real numbers <m>x\neq \pm 1</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>



</conclusion>

</section>

</chapter>








<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
