<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>


<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <personname>Michelle Homp</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</institution>
        </author>

        <author>
            <personname>Alyssa Seideman</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</institution>
        </author>

        <author>
            <personname>Sean Gravelle</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</institution>
        </author>


<author><department>This work is supported in part by a grant from the Mabel Elizabeth Kelly Fund  to promote the improvement of teaching at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln </department></author>
        <date><today /></date>

<!--
	<p>The Intermediate Algebra portion of the text is based heavily on the text <em>Intermediate Algebra</em> published by Saylor Academy in 2012.
	</p>
-->

    </titlepage>

    <colophon>
    <p>This text represents some original work by the listed authors and content by the authors cited below. It is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 United States License, viewable at <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us/ </url>. </p>

    <p> 2013 MATH IN SOCIETY by David Lippman, comprises a majority of this work, except as noted below. Licensed under Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 United States License, viewable at <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us/ </url>. </p>


    <p> 2011 MARK-RECAPTURE ACTIVITY, originally developed by Holly Gaff (Old Dominion University) and John Jungck (University of Delaware), served as the basis for the content in Section 1.1. Used by permission. </p>

    <p> 2018 PROBABILITY AND EXPECTED VALUE, or Chapter 3, was written by Glenn Ledder (University of Nebraska-Lincoln), as was Section 7.2 on the Adjusted Winner method of fair division. Used by permission. </p>

    <p> 2019 ADVANCED HIGH SCHOOL STATISTICS, by David Diez (OpenIntro), Mine Cetinkaya-Rundel (Duke University), Leah Dorazio (San Fransisco University High School), and Christopher D Barr (Varadero Capital), provided much of the content for Chapter 4. Also licensed under Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 United States License, viewable at <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us/ </url>. </p>

    <p> 2014 MODELING THE SPREAD OF A DISEASE, by Glenn Ledder and Michelle Homp, originally written as an activity for middle-level students, was adapted for Chapter 8. Most of the content of this chapter appears in the accompanying Math 203 Course Manual.</p>

    <p> Though most are from <em> Math in Society </em>, a few of the homework problems included in this text are adapted from exercises found in <em> Excursions in Modern Mathematics</em>, 8th Edition, by Peter Tannenbaum (California State Univeristy - Fresno).
    </p>



    </colophon>


    <preface>
      <p> MATH 203 <em>Contemporary Mathematics</em> is designed for students who are not majoring in mathematics and is intended to serve as a general education math class.  The standard high school progression of algebra - geometry - more algebra - precalculus - calculus can leave many students with a distaste for math, partly because it gives the impression that mathematics is all about algebraic manipulations, and partly because it omits many areas of interesting mathematics needed for personal use or informed citizenship.  MATH 203 tries to fill those gaps by covering a wide range of mathematical topics, of which algebra is only a small piece. The mathematical content that we hope students will find both interesting and useful has been divided into four units: statistics, social choice (such as voting theory and fair division),  growth and finance, and graph theory. </p>

      <p>The text is intended to be supplemented for the Math 203 Course Manual available for purchase at the UNL Bookstore. </p>




</preface>

</frontmatter>
