<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-4-condorcet">
<title>Pairwise Comparisons and the Condorcet Criterion</title>

<subsection><title>The Method of Pairwise Comparisons</title>

	<assemblage><title>The Method of Pairwise Comparisons</title>
		<p>
			The <term>Method of Pairwise Comparisons</term> is like a round robin tournament: we compare how candidates perform one-on-one, as we've done above. It has the following steps:
			<ol>
				<li>List all possible pairs of candidates.</li>
				<li><p>For each pair, determine who would win if the election were only between those two candidates.
					<ol>
						<li>To do so, we must look at all the voters. Each voter casts their ballot for whichever candidate they ranked higher <em>of the pair being considered</em> (even if they didn't rank that candidate first).</li>
						<li>The winner of each pair is given 1 point, and the loser, 0 points. If it is a tie, they both get <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> point. </li>
						</ol>
					</p></li>
				<li>After finding each pairwise winner, add up the points for each candidate. The candidate with the most points is the winner.</li>
			</ol>
			Note that this method results in ties a little more often than some of the other methods.
		</p>
	</assemblage>

<example xml:id="eg-vt-condorcet"><title>The 2009 mayoral election in Burlington, VT</title>

	<p>
		In 2009, the city of Burlington, Vermont used IRV to elect their mayor. The results of this election are shown below, in a simplified form to include only the three main candidates.
		<fn>More complete details can be found at <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2009_Burlington_mayoral_election">the Wikipedia article</url>.</fn>
		These three candidates were Bob Kiss, Kurt Wright, and Andy Montroll.
	</p>

	<table><caption></caption>
	<tabular top="none" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
		<row left="none">
			<cell bottom="none" right="medium"></cell>
			<cell colspan="5">Percent of voters</cell>
		</row>
		<row bottom="medium">
			<cell right="medium">Rankings</cell>
			<cell>34</cell>
			<cell>37</cell>
			<cell>15</cell>
			<cell>9</cell>
			<cell>5</cell>
		</row>
		<row>
			<cell right="medium">1st choice</cell>
			<cell>K</cell>
			<cell>W</cell>
			<cell>M</cell>
			<cell>M</cell>
			<cell>M</cell>
		</row>
		<row>
			<cell right="medium">2nd choice</cell>
			<cell>M</cell>
			<cell>M</cell>
			<cell>K</cell>
			<cell>W</cell>
			<cell></cell>
		</row>
		<row>
			<cell right="medium">3rd choice</cell>
			<cell>W</cell>
			<cell>K</cell>
			<cell>W</cell>
			<cell>K</cell>
			<cell></cell>
		</row>
	</tabular>
	</table>

	<p>
		Using this information, we can find the winner of this election using the method of pairwise comparisons as follows.
	</p>

	<sidebyside>
		<tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
			<row>
				<cell colspan="2">Pair</cell>
				<cell>Percent of votes</cell>
				<cell>Winner/points</cell>
			</row>
			<row bottom="minor">
				<cell bottom="none">1</cell>
				<cell>Kiss</cell>
				<cell>34+15=49</cell>
				<cell>Win=1</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell></cell>
				<cell>versus Wright</cell>
				<cell>37+9=46</cell>
				<cell>Lose=0</cell>
			</row>
			<row bottom="minor">
				<cell bottom="none">2</cell>
				<cell>Kiss</cell>
				<cell>34</cell>
				<cell>Lose=0</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell></cell>
				<cell>versus Montroll</cell>
				<cell>37+15+9+5=66</cell>
				<cell>Win=1</cell>
			</row>
			<row bottom="minor">
				<cell bottom="none">3</cell>
				<cell>Wright</cell>
				<cell>37</cell>
				<cell>Lose=0</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell></cell>
				<cell>versus Montroll</cell>
				<cell>34+15+9+5=63</cell>
				<cell>Win=1


				</cell>
			</row>
		</tabular>
	</sidebyside>

	<p>
		We see that Montroll wins two pairs for 2 points, while Kiss and Wright each won one pair for 1 point each. Thus, Montroll would win this election using the method of pairwise comparisons.
	</p>
</example>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>The Condorcet Criterion</title>

	<p>
		In <xref ref="eg-vt-condorcet"/>, we saw that Montroll was the pairwise winner because he won the most pairs of any candidate. We can say more, however: not only did Montroll win <em>the most</em> pairs, he actually won <em>every</em> pair in which he was one of the options. In other words, Montroll would never lose a one-on-one contest against any of his opponents. A candidate that satisfies this property is called a <term>Condorcet candidate</term>, named after Nicolas, Marquis de Condorcet.
		<biographical><p>
			Condorcet was a French philosopher and mathematician who lived during the 18th century. His ideas were influencial during the earlier part of the French Revolution, and he was a major author of a proposed constitution. However, his ideas were not adopted, and he became a target during the Reign of Terror. After unsuccessfully attempting to flee, Condorcet was arrested and died in prison in 1794. It is still unknown whether his death was suicide or murder. You can read more about his interesting life at the <url href="https://www-history.mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk/Biographies/Condorcet.html">MacTutor History of Mathematics</url> and, of course, <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquis_de_Condorcet">Wikipedia</url>.
		</p></biographical>
		A Condorcet candidate would seem to be strongly supported by voters; this leads to our next fairness criterion:
	</p>

	<assemblage><title>The Condorcet Criterion</title>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li>A candidate who would defeat any other candidate in a one-on-one contest is called a <term>Condorcet winner</term> (also called a <term>Condorcet candidate</term>), pronounced <q>condor-say</q>.</li>
				<li>The <term>Condorcet criterion</term> states that, if a Condorcet winner exists, then that candidate should be the winner of the election.</li>
				<li>Note that not every election may have a Condorcet winner! If there is no Condorcet winner, then the Condorcet criterion does not apply; that is, it does not state that any candidate ought to win.</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</assemblage>

</subsection>

</section>
