<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-7-2-adj-win">
<title>The Adjusted Winner Procedure for Fair Division</title>

	<p>
		Suppose you share an apartment with a friend. You have bought several appliances together, like a microwave oven, a coffee maker, and a vacuum cleaner. At the end of the year, you must somehow divide up these items, which are worth more to you than the tiny amount of money you could get by selling them. How do you divide the items? If one of you suggests a split of items, how do you decide if the division is fair?
	</p>
	<p>
		It is easy to divide a cake<mdash/>just have one person cut and the other choose. A cake is a continuous quantity, so it can be divided anywhere; and because all pieces of a given size are virtually identical, it is easy to see if you are getting a fair share. Fair division problem involving unequal discrete items are much harder. Examples like this occur in many settings. A married couple getting divorced have to divide their property but do not wish to sell everything. Two roommates have to divide up a list of chores. Two real estate partners decide to divide their business and have to allocate the property between them. Fair division issues of this sort are contentious and frequently result in hard feelings or end up being decided in court, where the principle (with license for exaggeration) is that found in Benjamin Franklin's poem, <em>The Benefit of Going to Law</em>: <q>A shell for him, a shell for thee; the middle is the lawyer's fee.</q>
	</p>
	<p>
		The adjusted winner procedure is a mathematical attempt to achieve a <q>fair</q> division of unequal discrete items between two entities, referred to in mathematical terms as <q>players.</q> As an example, consider a hypothetical divorce settlement between Caesar and Cleopatra, in which the valuable property consists of the port of Alexandria, a palace, a legion of soldiers, and an exotic poison collection. The players place different values on each item, so it seems reasonable that a division could be achieved that is <term>envy-free</term>, which means that neither player would want to trade their share with the other. A more ambitious goal is to produce a division that is <term>equitable</term>, meaning that each player is equally satisfied with his/her share. We'll have to define this term more carefully in the context of a given method.
	</p>
	<p>
		The adjusted winner procedure is one way to guarantee a division that is envy-free, and (if an item can be subdivided) at least close to equitable. It is conducted via a sequence of 6 steps:

		<ol>
			<!--Step 1-->
			<li>
				Each player uses whatever means (s)he wishes to assign values to each item so that the total is 100 points. In the example, let's say Cleopatra places a value of 40 points on the legion of soldiers and 20 points on each of the other items. Caesar is not interested in the poison collection, so he chooses scores of 50 for the legion, 30 for the port, 20 for the palace, and 0 for the poisons.

				<sidebyside>
					<tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
						<row bottom="none">
							<cell right="major"></cell>
							<cell>Score for</cell>
							<cell>Score for</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell right="major">Item</cell>
							<cell>Caesar</cell>
							<cell>Cleopatra</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Port of Alexandria</cell>
							<cell>30</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Palace</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Legion of soldiers</cell>
							<cell>50</cell>
							<cell>40</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell right="major">Exotic poisons</cell>
							<cell>0</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
						</row>
					</tabular>
				</sidebyside>
			</li>

			<!--Step 2-->
			<li>

				<sidebyside>
					<tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
						<row bottom="none">
							<cell right="major"></cell>
							<cell>Score for</cell>
							<cell>Score for</cell>
							<cell left="major">Ratio</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell right="major">Item</cell>
							<cell>Caesar</cell>
							<cell>Cleopatra</cell>
							<cell left="major">Caesar <solidus/> Cleo</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Port of Alexandria</cell>
							<cell>30</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
							<cell left="major">1.50</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Palace</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
							<cell left="major">1.00</cell>
						</row>
						<row bottom="minor">
							<cell right="major">Legion of soldiers</cell>
							<cell>50</cell>
							<cell>40</cell>
							<cell left="major">1.25</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell right="major">Exotic poisons</cell>
							<cell>0</cell>
							<cell>20</cell>
							<cell left="major">0.00</cell>
						</row>
					</tabular>
				</sidebyside>

			</li>

			<!--Step 3-->
			<li>
			</li>

			<!--Step 4-->
			<li>
			</li>

			<!--Step 5-->
			<li>
			</li>

			<!--Step 6 is optional.-->
			<li>
			</li>
		</ol>
	</p>



  </section>
