<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-4-E-exercises">

<title>Chapter 4 Exercises</title>

<!--comment here-->

<p><ol>

	<li><p>Cumulative SAT scores are normally distribute with mean 1100 and standard
deviation 200. Use this information to sketch a diagram and answer each of the questions below.
			<ol>
				<li>Approximately what percent of SAT scores are at or between 700 and 1500? </li>
				<li>What percent of SAT scores are less than or equal to 1500? What percent of the scores of 1500 or more?</li>
				<li>The scores of 68% of test takers are expected to be at or between what two values?</li>
				<li>What percent of SAT scores are at or between 1100 and 1300? </li>
				<li>The top 2.5% of the students will have a score greater than or equal to what value?</li>
				<li>What is the probability that a randomly selected student has an SAT score of 1300 or greater? </li>
				<li>What percent of SAT scores are 500 or less?</li>
				<li>What is the probability that a randomly selected student has an SAT score at or between 900 and 1500? </li>
				<li>What is the probability that a randomly selected student has an SAT score at or between 1300 and 1700? </li>
			</ol></p>
	</li>


	<li><p>Suppose 460 high school seniors in a particular school district took the SAT exam.
		<ol>
			<li>Approximately how many of the seniors in the district are expected to earn scores at or between 900 and 1500?</li>
			<li>Approximately how many of these students are expected to earn scores of 1300 or greater?</li>
			<li>Approximately 320 of the students are expected to earn a minimum score of what value?</li>
			<li>Approximately how many of the students are expected to earn scores or 1700 or higher?</li>
			<li>Approximately how many of the students are expected to earn scores at or between 700 and 1300?</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>


	<li>
	Suppose 60\% of voters favor candidate A over candidate B.  Determine the standard deviation and 95\% confidence interval for a polling sample of 1000 individuals.
	</li>

	<li><p>
	Suppose 52\% of voters favor candidate A over candidate B.
  <ol>
  	<li>Determine the standard deviation and 95\% confidence interval for a polling sample of 1000 individuals.</li>
		<li>Find the probability that the poll will predict a majority in favor of candidate B.</li>
		<li>Explain why the size of the actual voting population does not need to be given in this problem.</li>
  </ol></p>
  </li>

</ol></p>


<!--
<table xml:id="eg-table"><caption>This is a caption</caption>
  <tabular top="major" left="minor">
    <row>
      <cell left="medium" right="medium" bottom="medium">
        a
      </cell>
      <cell bottom="medium">
        b
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium" right="medium" bottom="medium">
        c
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        e
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">
        f
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium" right="medium" bottom="medium">
        d
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">
        g
      </cell>
    </row>
  </tabular>
</table>

<p>Look at <xref ref="eg-table"/>.</p> -->

</section>
