<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-6-1-banzhaf">

	<title>Weighted Voting</title>

<introduction>
	<p>
		In a corporate shareholders meeting, each shareholder's vote counts proportionally to the amount of shares they own.  An individual with one share gets the equivalent of one vote, while someone with 100 shares gets the equivalent of 100 votes.  This is called <term>weighted voting</term>, where each vote has some weight attached to it.  Weighted voting is sometimes used to vote on candidates, but more commonly to decide <q>yes</q> or <q>no</q> on a proposal, sometimes called a motion.  Weighted voting is applicable in corporate settings, as well as decision making in a legislative body and voting in the United Nations Security Council.
			<aside><p>The UN Security Council rules are not explicitly defined as a weighted voting system. However, its voting system is mathematically equivalent to a weighted voting system.</p></aside>
	</p>

	<p>
		In weighted voting, we are most often interested in the power each voter has in influencing the outcome.
	</p>
</introduction>


<subsection><title>Beginnings</title>
	<p>
		We'll begin with some basic vocabulary for weighted voting systems.
	</p>

	<assemblage><title>Vocabulary for Weighted Voting</title>
		<p>Each individual or entity casting a vote is called a player in the election.  They’re often notated as <m>P_1,P_2,P_3,\ldots,P_N</m> where <m>N</m> is the total number of voters.</p>

		<p>Each player is given a weight, which usually represents how many votes they get.</p>

		<p>The quota is the minimum weight needed for the votes or weight needed for the proposal to be approved.</p>

		<p>A weighted voting system will often be represented in a shorthand form:

		<me>[q: w_1, w_2, w_3,\ldots, w_n]</me>

		In this form, <m>q</m> is the quota, <m>w_1</m> is the weight for player 1, and so on.</p>
	</assemblage>

<example>
	<p>
		In a small company, there are 4 shareholders.  Mr. Smith has a 30% ownership stake in the company, Mr. Garcia has a 25% stake, Mrs. Hughes has a 25% stake, and Mrs. Lee has a 20% stake.   They are trying to decide whether to open a new location.  The company by-laws state that more than 50% of the ownership has to approve any decision like this.  This could be represented by the weighted voting system:

		<me>[51:  30, 25, 25, 20]</me>

		Here we have treated the percentage ownership as votes, so Mr. Smith gets the equivalent of 30 votes, having a 30% ownership stake.  Since more than 50% is required to approve the decision, the quota is 51, the smallest whole number over 50.
	</p>
</example>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>A Look at Power</title>
	<p>
		Text here.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Calculating Power: Banzhaf Power Index</title>
	<p>
		Text here.
	</p>
</subsection>
  </section>
