<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-9-1-linear-growth">

<title>Linear Growth</title>

<subsection>
	<title>Linear Growth</title>

<p>Marco is a collector of antique soda bottles.  His collection currently contains 437 bottles.  Every year, he budgets enough money to buy 32 new bottles.  Can we determine how many bottles he will have in 5 years, and how long it will take for his collection to reach 1000 bottles?</p>

<p>While both of these questions you could probably solve without an equation or formal mathematics, we are going to formalize our approach to this problem to provide a means to answer more complicated questions.</p>

<p>Suppose that <m>P_n</m> represents the number, or population, of bottles Marco has after n years.  So <m>P_0</m> would represent the number of bottles now, <m>P_1</m> would represent the number of bottles after 1 year, <m>P_2</m> would represent the number of bottles after 2 years, and so on.  We could describe how Marco’s bottle collection is changing using: </p>

<p><m>P_0 = 437</m></p>
<p><m>P_n = P_{n-1} + 32</m></p>

<p>This is called a <term>recursive relationship</term>. A recursive relationship is a formula which relates the next value in a sequence to the previous values.  Here, the number of bottles in year n can be found by adding 32 to the number of bottles in the previous year, <m>P_{n-1}.</m>  Using this relationship, we could calculate: </p>

<me> P_1 = P_0 + 32 = 437 + 32 = 469 </me>

<me> P_2 = P_1 + 32 = 469 + 32 = 501 </me>

<me> P_3 = P_2 + 32 = 501 + 32 = 533 </me>

<me> P_4 = P_3 + 32 = 533 + 32 = 565 </me>

<me> P_5 = P_4 + 32 = 565 + 32 = 597 </me>

<p>We have answered the question of how many bottles Marco will have in 5 years.  However, solving how long it will take for his collection to reach 1000 bottles would require a lot more calculations.  </p>

<p>While recursive relationships are excellent for describing simply and cleanly how a quantity is changing, they are not convenient for making predictions or solving problems that stretch far into the future.  For that, a closed or explicit form for the relationship is preferred.  An <term>explicit equation</term> allows us to calculate <m>P_n</m> directly, without needing to know <m>P_{n-1}</m>.  While you may already be able to guess the explicit equation, let us derive it from the recursive formula.  We can do so by selectively not simplifying as we go:</p>

<me>P_1 = 437 + 32 = 437 + 1(32)</me>
<me>P_2 = P_1 + 32 = 437 + 32 + 32 = 437 + 2(32)</me>
<me>P_3 = P_2 + 32 = (437 + 2(32)) + 32 = 437 + 3(32)</me>
<me>P_4 = P_3 = 32 = (437 + 3(32)) + 32 = 437 + 4(32)</me>

<p>You can probably see the pattern now, and generalize that</p>

<me>P_n = 437 + n(32) = 437 + 32n</me>

<p>Using this equation, we can calculate how many bottles he’ll have after 5 years:</p>

<me>P_5 = 437 + 32(5) = 437 + 160 = 597</me>

<p>We can now also solve for when the collection will reach 1000 bottles by substituting in 1000 for <m>P_n</m> and solving for n</p>

<me>1000 = 437 + 32n</me>

<me>563 = 32n</me>

<me>n = 563/32 = 17.59</me>

<p>So Marco will reach 1000 bottles in 18 years.</p> 

<sidebyside>
	<p>In the previous example, Marco’s collection grew by the <emph>same number</emph> of bottles every year.  This constant change is the defining characteristic of linear growth. Plotting the values we calculated for Marco’s collection, we can see the values form a straight line, the shape of linear growth.</p>
	<image source="images/linear-bottles.png" width="70%" />
</sidebyside>

<assemblage>
	<title>Linear Growth</title>
	<p>If a quantity starts at size <m>P_0</m> and grows by <m>d</m>every time period, then the quantity after n time periods can be determined using either of these relations:</p>

	<p>Recursive form: <m>P_n = P_{n-1} + d</m></p>

	<p>Explicit form: <m>P_n = P_0 = dn</m></p>

</assemblage>

<p>You may recognize the common difference, d, in our linear equation as slope.  In fact, the entire explicit equation should look familiar – it is the same linear equation you learned in algebra, probably stated as <m>y = mx + b.</m></p>

<p>In the standard algebraic equation <m>y = mx + b</m>, b was the y-intercept, or the y value when x was zero.  In the form of the equation we’re using, we are using <m>P_0</m> to represent that initial amount.</p>

<p>In the <m>y = mx + b</m> equation, recall that m was the slope.  You might remember this as “rise over run”, or the change in y divided by the change in x.  Either way, it represents the same thing as the common difference, d, we are using – the amount the output <m>P_n</m> changes when the input n increases by 1.</p>

<p>The equations<m>y = mx + b</m> and <m>P_n = P_0 + d n</m> mean the same thing and can be used the same ways, we’re just writing it somewhat differently.</p>

<example>
	<p>The population of elk in a national forest was measured to be 12,000 in 2003, and was measured again to be 15,000 in 2007.  If the population continues to grow linearly at this rate, what will the elk population be in 2014?</p>

</example>

</subsection>

</section>