<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-7-1-seal-bid">

	<title>The Sealed Bids Method of Fair Division</title>

	<p>The Sealed Bids method provides a method for discrete fair division, allowing for the division of items that cannot be split into smaller pieces, like a house or a car.  Because of this, the method requires that all parties have a large amount of cash at their disposal to balance out the difference in item values.  </p>

	<assemblage>
		<p>
			The method begins by compiling a list of items to be divided.  Then:
		<ol>
			<li>Each party involved lists, in secret, a dollar amount they value each item to be worth.  This is their sealed bid.</li>
			<li>The bids are collected.  For each party, the value of all the items is totaled, and divided by the number of parties.  This defines their fair share.</li>
			<li>Each item is awarded to the highest bidder.</li>
			<li>For each party, the value of all items received is totaled.  If the value is more than that party’s fair share, they pay the difference into a holding pile.  If the value is less than that party’s fair share, they receive the difference from the holding pile.  This ends the initial allocation.</li>
			<li>In most cases, there will be a surplus, or leftover money, in the holding pile.  The surplus is divided evenly between all the players.  This produces the final allocation.</li>
		</ol>
		</p>
	</assemblage>

	<p>
		While the assumptions we made for fair division methods specified that an arbitrator should not be necessary, it is common for an independent third party to collect the bids and announce the outcome.  While not technically necessary, since the method can be executed without a third party involved, this protects the secrecy of the bids, which can sometimes help avoid resentment or bad feelings between the players.
	</p>

	<example xml:id="sam-omar-sealedbid">
		<statement>
			<p>Sam and Omar have lived together for the last 3 years, during which time they shared the expense of purchasing several items for their home.  Sam has accepted a job in another city, and now they find themselves needing to divide their shared assets.</p>

			<p>Each records their value of each item, as shown below.</p>

			<sidebyside>
				<tabular top="minor" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell right="medium"></cell>
						<cell>Sam</cell>
						<cell>Omar</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Couch</cell>
						<cell>$150</cell>
						<cell>$100</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">TV</cell>
						<cell>$200</cell>
						<cell>$250</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Video game system</cell>
						<cell>$250</cell>
						<cell>$150</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Surround sound system</cell>
						<cell>$50</cell>
						<cell>$100</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</sidebyside>

			<p>Use the sealed bids procedure to allocate the items between Sam and Omar.</p>
		</statement>

		<solution>
			<p>Sam’s total valuation of the items is $150+$200+$250+$50 = $650, making a fair share for Sam $650/2 = $325.</p>
			<p>Omar’s total valuation of the items is $100+$250+$150+$100 = $600, making a fair share for Omar $600/2 = $300.</p>
			<p>Each item is now awarded to the highest bidder.  Sam will receive the couch and video game system, providing $150+$250 = $400 of value to Sam.  Since this exceeds his fair share, he has to pay the difference, $75, into a holding pile.</p>
			<p>Omar will receive the TV and surround sound system, providing $250+$100=$350 in value.  This is more than his fair share, so he has to pay the difference, $50, into the holding pile.</p>
			<p>Thus, in the initial allocation, Sam receives the couch and video game system and pays $75 into the holding pile.  Omar receives the TV and surround sound system and pays $50 into the holding pile.  At this point, both players would feel they have received a fair share.</p>
			<p>There is now $125 remaining in the holding pile.  This is the surplus from the division.  This is now split evenly, and both Sam and Omar are given back $62.50.  Since Sam had paid in $75, the net effect is that he paid $12.50.   Since Omar had originally paid in $50, the net effect is that he receives $12.50.</p>
			<p>Thus, in the final allocation, Sam receives the couch and video game system and pays $12.50 to Omar.  Omar receives the TV and surround sound system and receives $12.50.  At this point, both players feel they have received more than a fair share.</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<example xml:id="merger-sealedbid">
		<statement>
			<p>Four small graphic design companies are merging operations to become one larger corporation.  In this merger, there are a number of issues that need to be settled.  Each company is asked to place a monetary value (in thousands of dollars) on each issue:</p>

			<sidebyside>
				<tabular top="minor" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell right="medium"></cell>
						<cell>Super Designs</cell>
						<cell>DesignByMe</cell>
						<cell>LayoutPros</cell>
						<cell>Graphix</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Company name</cell>
						<cell>$5</cell>
						<cell>$3</cell>
						<cell>$3</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Company location</cell>
						<cell>$8</cell>
						<cell>$9</cell>
						<cell>$7</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">CEO</cell>
						<cell>$10</cell>
						<cell>$5</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
						<cell>$7</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Chair of the board</cell>
						<cell>$7</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
						<cell>$8</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</sidebyside>

			<p>We can use the method of sealed bids to resolve these issues. We can allocate the issues as if they were items, using the usual sealed bids rules. Then, whichever company <q>wins</q> each issue can make the decision on that issue.</p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<p>We calculate the following values:</p>

			<sidebyside>
				<tabular top="minor" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell right="medium"></cell>
						<cell>Super Designs</cell>
						<cell>DesignByMe</cell>
						<cell>LayoutPros</cell>
						<cell>Graphix</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Total value of all issues</cell>
						<cell>$30</cell>
						<cell>$23</cell>
						<cell>$22</cell>
						<cell>$27</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Fair share</cell>
						<cell>$7.50</cell>
						<cell>$5.75</cell>
						<cell>$5.50</cell>
						<cell>$6.75</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">Total value of issues awarded</cell>
						<cell>$10</cell>
						<cell>$9</cell>
						<cell>$0</cell>
						<cell>$14</cell>
					</row>
					<row rowspan="2">
						<cell right="medium">Amount they pay/get</cell>
						<cell>Hi!
							<!--<p><m>7.50-10=-2.50</m></p><p>Pay $2.50</p>-->
						</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
						<cell>$6</cell>
						<cell>$8</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell right="medium">After surplus</cell>
						<cell>Pay $0.625</cell>
						<cell>Pay $1.375</cell>
						<cell>Get $7.375</cell>
						<cell>Pay $5.375</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</sidebyside>

		</solution>
	</example>

<exploration xml:id="jam-mag-ken-sealedbid">
	<statement>
	</statement>
	<solution>
	</solution>
</exploration>

	<example xml:id="chores-sealedbid">
		<statement>
		</statement>
		<solution>
		</solution>
	</example>
  </section>
