<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-11E-exercises">

<title>Chapter 11 Exercises</title>


<!--comment here-->

<subsection><title>Section 11.1 Homework</title>

<figure xml:id="section-11-1"><caption></caption>
				<image source="images/def-loop.png" width="100%"/>
		</figure>
<p>

		<ol>

		<li>To deliver mail in a particular neighborhood, the postal carrier needs to walk along each of the streets with houses (the dots). See Figure A.  Create a graph with edges showing where the carrier must walk to deliver the mail.
					</li>






				<li>Suppose that a town has 7 bridges as pictured in Figure B. Create a graph that could be used to determine if there is a path that crosses all bridges once. </li>

				<li>The table below shows approximate driving times (in minutes, without traffic) between five cities in the Dallas area. Create a weighted graph representing this data. </li>

				<p>
			<!--<figure xml:id=" "><caption></caption>-->
					<image source="images/Dallas-area-drive-times.png" width="100%"/>
			<!--</figure>-->
				</p>

		   <li> Identify the bridges (if any) in each of the graphs below. </li>

			 <p>
		 <!--<figure xml:id=" "><caption></caption>-->
				 <image source="images/Check-bridges.png" width="100%"/>
		 <!--</figure>-->
			 </p>


				<li><p>Draw a graph to fit each of the descriptions below.  Label each vertex. Then for each graph, provide the following information:  (i) next to each vertex, write its degree; (ii) give the total number of edges; (iii) give the total number of components.
					<ol>
						<li> It has at least 7 vertices and exactly one bridge. </li>
						<li> It has at least six edges and at least two components.</li>
					</ol></p>
					</li>



					<sidebyside>
						<image source="images/nhood-diagram.png" width="45%"/>
						<image source="images/nhood-graph.png" width="45%"/>
					</sidebyside>

					<figure xml:id="easy-graph"><caption>Two representations of the same graph</caption>
					<sidebyside widths="30% 40%">
					<image source="images/easy-graph-square.png"/>
					<image source="images/easy-graph-triangle.png"/>
					</sidebyside>
					</figure>


				</ol></p>

	</subsection>

<!--NEXT SECTION OF HOMEWORK #############################################################-->

<subsection><title>Section 11.2 Homework</title>

<p><ol>

	<li> For each of the graphs below, if one exists, find an Euler circuit or an Euler path.  If an Euler circuit or path do not exists, explain why.
	</li>
	<p>
<!--<figure xml:id=" "><caption></caption>-->
		<image source="images/Check-Euler-circuits-or-paths.png" width="100%"/>
<!--</figure>-->
	</p>


	<li>After a storm, the city crew inspects for trees or brush blocking the road. For the two neighborhoods below, find an efficient route for the crew by finding an Euler circuit. If necessary, Eulerize the graph in an efficient way.
	</li>
	<p>
<!--<figure xml:id=" "><caption></caption>-->
		<image source="images/Street-crew-eulerize-graphs.png" width="100%"/>
<!--</figure>-->
	</p>


	<li>For the graphs below, do each of the following: (i) identify whether the graph has an Euler
circuit, an Euler path, or neither and explain why using theorems from this chapter; (ii) if the graph does have either an Euler path or circuit, find one; (iii) if the graph does not have an Euler path or circuit, Eulerize it so that it has an Euler circuit.
	</li>
	<p>
<!--<figure xml:id=" "><caption></caption>-->
		<image source="images/Euler-graphs-theorems-check.png" width="100%"/>
<!--</figure>-->
	</p>

</ol></p>



</subsection>


</section>
