<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-2-1-graphically">

<title>Frequency Tables and Bar Graphs</title>

<subsection>
  <title>Categorizing Data</title>

  <p>Once we have gathered data, we might wish to classify it.  Roughly speaking, data can be classified as categorical data or quantitative data.</p>

  <assemblage>
    <title>Quantitative and categorical data</title>

    <p><term>Categorical (qualitative) data</term> are pieces of information that allow us to classify the objects under investigation into various categories.</p>

    <p><term>Quantitative data</term> are responses that are numerical in nature and with which we can perform meaningful arithmetic calculations.</p>
  </assemblage>

  <example> 
    <p>We might conduct a survey to determine the name of the favorite movie that each person in a math class saw in a movie theater.</p>

    <p>When we conduct such a survey, the responses would look like: <em>Finding Nemo, The Hulk, or Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines.</em>  We might count the number of people who give each answer, but the answers themselves do not have any numerical values: we cannot perform computations with an answer like "<em>Finding Nemo.</em>"  This would be categorical data.</p>
  </example>

  <example>
    <p>A survey could ask the number of movies you have seen in a movie theater in the past 12 months (0, 1, 2, 3, 4, ...)</p>

    <p>This would be quantitative data.</p>
  </example>

  <p>Other examples of quantitative data would be the running time of the movie you saw most recently (104 minutes, 137 minutes, 104 minutes, ...) or the amount of money you paid for a movie ticket the last time you went to a movie theater ($5.50, $7.75, $9, ...).</p>

  <p>Sometimes, determining whether or not data is categorical or quantitative can be a bit trickier.</p> 

  <example> 
    <p>Suppose we gather respondents' ZIP codes in a survey to track their geographical location.</p>

    <p>ZIP codes are numbers, but we can't do any meaningful mathematical calculations with them (it doesn't make sense to say that 98036 is "twice" 49018 — that's like saying that Lynnwood, WA is "twice" Battle Creek, MI, which doesn't make sense at all), so ZIP codes are really categorical data. </p>
  </example>

  <example>
    <p>A survey about the movie you most recently attended includes the question "How would you rate the movie you just saw?" with these possible answers:</p>

      <p><cd>
        1 - it was awful
        2 - it was just OK
        3 - I liked it
        4 - it was great 
        5 - best movie ever!</cd></p>

<p>Again, there are numbers associated with the responses, but we can't really do any calculations with them: a movie that rates a 4 is not necessarily twice as good as a movie that rates a 2, whatever that means; if two people see the movie and one of them thinks it stinks and the other thinks it's the best ever it doesn't necessarily make sense to say that "on average they liked it."</p>

  </example>

  <p>As we study movie-going habits and preferences, we shouldn't forget to specify the population under consideration.  If we survey 3-7 year-olds the runaway favorite might be <em>Finding Nemo</em>.  13-17 year-olds might prefer <em>Terminator 3</em>.  And 33-37 year-olds might prefer...well, <em>Finding Nemo</em>.</p>

<exploration>
  <statement> <p>Classify each measurement as categorical or quantitative
    <ol>
      <li> Eye color of a group of people</li>
      <li> Daily high temperature of a city over several weeks</li>
      <li> Annual income</li>
    </ol></p>
  </statement>
<solution> <ol>
      <li>Categorical</li>
      <li>Quantitative</li>
      <li>Quantitative</li>
    </ol>
</solution>
</exploration>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Frequency Tables and Bar Graphs</title>

<p> Categorical, or qualitative, data are pieces of information that allow us to classify the objects under investigation into various categories.  We usually begin working with categorical data by summarizing the data into a <term>frequency table.</term></p>

<assemblage>
	<title>Frequency Table</title>
	<p>A <term>frequency table</term> is a table with two columns.  One column lists the categories, and another for the frequencies with which the items in the categories occur (how many items fit into
	each category).</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
	<p>An insurance company determines vehicle insurance premiums based on known risk factors.  If a person is considered a higher risk, their premiums will be higher.  One potential factor is the color of your car.  The insurance company believes that people with some color cars are more likely to get in accidents.  To research this, they examine police reports for recent total-loss collisions.  The data is summarized in the frequency table below. </p>



<sidebyside>
  <tabular top="minor" left="minor" right="minor" halign="center">
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Color
      </cell>
      <cell>
        Frequency
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Blue
      </cell>
      <cell>
        25
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Green
      </cell>
      <cell>
        52
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Red
      </cell>
      <cell>
        41
      </cell>
    </row>
 	<row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        White
      </cell>
      <cell>
        36
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Black
      </cell>
      <cell>
        39
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
      <cell>
        Grey
      </cell>
      <cell>
        23
      </cell>
    </row>
  </tabular>
</sidebyside>

</example>

<p> Sometimes we need an even more intuitive way of displaying data.  This is where charts and graphs come in.  There are many, many ways of displaying data graphically, but we will concentrate on one very useful type of graph called a bar graph.  In this section we will work with bar graphs that display categorical data; the next section will be devoted to bar graphs that display quantitative data.  </p>

<assemblage>
	<title>Bar graph</title>
	<p>A <term>bar graph</term> is a graph that displays a bar for each category with the length of each bar indicating the frequency of that category.</p>
</assemblage>

<p>To construct a bar graph, we need to draw a vertical axis and a horizontal axis.  The vertical direction will have a scale and measure the frequency of each category; the horizontal axis has no scale in this instance.  The construction of a bar chart is most easily described by use of an example.</p>

<example>
	<p>Using our car data from above, note the highest frequency is 52, so our vertical axis needs to go from 0 to 52, but we might as well use 0 to 55, so that we can put a hash mark every 5 units: </p>

	<sidebyside>
		<image source="images/vehicle-bar-graph" />
	</sidebyside>

</example>

</subsection>


</section>
