<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-E-exercises">

<title>Chapter 1 Exercises</title>

<!--comment here-->

<p><ol>

	<li>This year, Cunningham Lake in Omaha has been fighting an infestation of zebra mussels, an invasive species. Suppose that the Nebraska Game and Parks Commission wants to estimate their population. They capture and mark 194 zebra mussels, then release them back into the lake. After waiting a month, they capture 84 mussels, of  which 13 had previously been marked. Using this data, estimate the number of zebra mussels in Cunningham Lake.
	</li>

	<li><p>Your class of Math 203 students decides to conduct a study to estimate the number of students at UNL who study abroad. You survey a random group of 75 students from among the current sections of Math 203, of whom 21 have studied abroad while at UNL.
		<ol>
			<li>What is the target population in this experiment? What is the parameter (described in words)?</li>
			<li>Is the sample a random collection of students from the target population? Why or why not?  (Use the definition of a random sample to explain.)</li>
			<li>Identify possible ways in which the outcome might be biased.</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>

	<li><p>The UNL Office of Global Strategies conducts its own experiment to find out how many students study abroad. They know that there are 26,000 students in total at UNL. They survey 700 randomly selected students, of whom 95 have studied abroad while at UNL. The surveys take place in person on campus.
		<ol>
			<li>To use this data to approximate the total number of UNL students who have studied abroad, which enumeration method would we use: one sample estimation or mark-recapture? </li>
			<li>Use the method you chose in part (a) to compute an approximation of the number of students who have studied abroad.</li>
			<li>Identify the parameter and the statistic in this problem.</li>
			<li>Identify possible sources of sampling bias.</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>

	<li><p>A group of Math 203 students has been asked to find out which type of coffee is preferred by students at UNL:  Starbucks, Scooter’s, Dunkin Donuts or coffee from The Mill.  Since it is not feasible to contact every UNL student, the group needs to gather information using only a sample of UNL students, so they decide to interview students as they exit the Learning Commons, at the entrance by Dunkin Donuts.  Of the 124 students interviewed, 38 prefer Starbucks, 16 prefer Scooter’s, 66 prefer Dunkin Donuts, and 4 prefer coffee from The Mill.  Using this information, the group makes the claim that 31% of all UNL students prefer Starbucks, 13% prefer Scooter’s, 53% prefer Dunkin Donuts, and 3% prefer coffee from The Mill.
		<ol>
			<li>How did the group arrive at these percentages?</li>
			<li>What is the target population? What are the parameters? What are the statistics?</li>
			<li>What type of sampling method did the group use? How do you know?</li>
			<li>Do you believe the group’s claim about UNL students is legitimate?  Why or why not?</li>
			<li>Describe a simple random sampling method that would give a more accurate estimate of the preferred type of coffee among all UNL students.</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>

	<li><p>	A political scientist surveys 28 of the current 106 representatives in a state's legislature.
		Of them, 14 said they were supporting a new education bill, 12 said there were not
		supporting the bill, and 2 were undecided.
		<ol>
			<li>What is the population of this survey?</li>
			<li>What is the size of the population?</li>
			<li>What is the size of the sample?</li>
			<li>Give the sample statistic for the proportion of representatives surveyed who said they
			were supporting the education bill.</li>
			<li>Based on this sample, we might expect how many of the representatives to
			support the education bill?</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>


	<li><p>The city of Raleigh has 9500 registered voters. There are two candidates for city
		council in an upcoming election: Brown and Feliz. The day before the election, a
		telephone poll of 350 randomly selected registered voters was conducted. 112 said
		they'd vote for Brown, 207 said they'd vote for Feliz, and 31 were undecided.
		<ol>
			<li>What is the population of this survey?</li>
			<li>What is the size of the population?</li>
			<li>What is the size of the sample?</li>
			<li>Give the sample statistic for the proportion of voters surveyed who said they'd
			vote for Brown.</li>
			<li>Based on this sample, we might expect how many of the 9500 voters to vote
			for Brown?</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>



	<li>Identify the most relevant source of bias in this situation: A survey asks the question, <q>Should the mall prohibit loud and annoying rock music in clothing stores catering to teenagers?</q>
	</li>


	<li>Identify the most relevant source of bias in this situation: To determine opinions on voter support for a downtown renovation project, a surveyor randomly questions	people working in downtown businesses.
	</li>


	<li><p>A team of researchers is testing the effectiveness of a new HPV vaccine. They
		randomly divide the subjects into two groups. Group 1 receives new HPV vaccine,
		and Group 2 receives the existing HPV vaccine. The patients in the study do not
		know which group they are in.
		<ol>
			<li>Which is the treatment group?</li>
			<li>Which is the control group (if there is one)?</li>
			<li>Is this study blind, double-blind, or neither?</li>
			<li>Is this best described as an experiment, a controlled experiment, or a placebo
			controlled experiment?</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>


	<li><p>For the clinical trials of a weight loss drug containing Garcinia cambogia the subjects
		were randomly divided into two groups. The first received an inert pill along with an
		exercise and diet plan, while the second received the test medicine along with the
		same exercise and diet plan. The patients do not know which group they are in, nor
		do the fitness and nutrition advisors.
		<ol>
			<li>Which is the treatment group?</li>
			<li>Which is the control group (if there is one)?</li>
			<li>Is this study blind, double-blind, or neither?</li>
			<li>Is this best described as an experiment, a controlled experiment, or a placebo
				controlled experiment?</li>
		</ol></p>
	</li>



<!--A possible question to add here is #53-56 on page 442 of the 8th edition of the tannenbaum text (the blue blue)-->


</ol></p>


</section>
