<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="trig"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Trigonometric Functions</title>
<introduction>
<p>In this chapter we define trigonometric functions.  For a more extensive treatment of trigonometric functions we refer the reader to <url href="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/part-3.html">PreCalculus at Nebraska: College Trigonometry</url>.</p>

</introduction>

<subsection><title>Periodic Functions</title>

<assemblage>
    <p>
        A <term>periodic function</term><idx>periodic function</idx> is a function whose output values repeat on a regular interval. In mathematical terms, we say that a periodic function is a function for which a specific horizontal shift, <m>P</m>, results in the original function: <m>f(x+P)=f(x)</m> for all values of <m>x</m>. </p>
    <p>
        The <term>period</term><idx>period</idx> of a periodic function is how long it takes for the output values to begin repeating, or the smallest horizontal shift with <m>P>0</m>, such that <m>f(x+P)=f(x)</m> for all values of <m>x</m>. </p>
    <sidebyside>
    	<image source="images/period.png"><description>figure showing the period of a periodic function</description></image> </sidebyside>
</assemblage>

<p>In addition to the period we also define the midline and amplitude of a periodic function.</p>

<assemblage>
    <p>
    	The <term>midline</term><idx>midline</idx> of a periodic function is the horizontal line halfway, or midway, between the function's maximum and minimum output values.</p>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
    	The <term>amplitude</term><idx>amplitude</idx> of a periodic function is the distance between the function's maximum (or minimum) output value and the midline. </p>
    <sidebyside>
    <image source="images/midlineamp.png"><description>figure showing midline and amplitude of a periodic function</description></image> </sidebyside>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
    	The midline often represents the average value of a wave-like periodic function and should always be written as the equation of a horizontal line. The amplitude of a periodic function represents how "large" the function's oscillations are. </p>
</assemblage>

<p>
    While measuring angles in degrees may be familiar to many students, doing so often complicates matters since the units of measure can get in the way of calculations. For this reason, another measure of angles is commonly used. This measure is based on the distance around the unit circle. </p>

<assemblage>
    <title>The Unit Circle</title>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
        The <term>unit circle</term><idx>unit circle</idx> is a circle of radius 1, centered at the origin of the <m>xy</m>-plane. When measuring an angle around the unit circle, we travel in the counterclockwise direction, starting from the positive <m>x</m>-axis. A negative angle is measured in the opposite, or clockwise, direction. A complete trip around the unit circle amounts to a total of 360 degrees.</p>
    <sidebyside width="70%">
            <image source="images/blankUnitCircle.png"><description>blank unit circle</description></image> </sidebyside>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
        A <term>radian</term><idx>radian</idx> is a measurement of an angle that arises from looking at angles as a fraction of the circumference of the unit circle. A complete trip around the unit circle amounts to a total of <m>2\pi</m> radians. </p>
    <sidebyside width="70%">
            <image source="images/radians.png"><description>unit circle with 2pi radians labeled</description></image> </sidebyside>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
        Radians are a <term>unitless measure</term>. Therefore, it is not necessary to write the label "radians" after a radian measure, and if you see 
an angle that is not labeled with "degrees" or the degree symbol, you should assume that it is a radian measure. </p>
</assemblage>

<p>
    Radians and degrees both measure angles. Thus, it is possible to convert between the two. Since one rotation around the unit circle equals 360 degrees or <m>2\pi</m> radians, we can use this as a conversion factor. </p>

<assemblage>
    <title>Converting Between Radians and Degrees</title>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
        Since <m>360 \text{ degrees} = 2\pi \text{ radians}</m>, we can divide each side by 360 and conclude that
        <me>\displaystyle 1 \text{ degree} = \frac{2\pi \text{ radians}}{360} = \frac{\pi \text{ radians}}{180}</me> </p>
    <p> So, to convert from degrees to radians, we can multiply by <m>\displaystyle \ \frac{\pi \text{ radians}}{180^\circ}</m> </p>
    <p> </p>
    <p>
        Similarly, we can conclude that
        <me>\displaystyle 1 \text{ radian} = \frac{360^\circ}{2\pi} = \frac{180^\circ}{\pi}</me> </p>
    <p> So, to convert from radians to degrees, we can multiply by <m>\displaystyle \ \frac{180^\circ}{\pi \text{ radians}}</m> </p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>The Common Trigonometric Functions</title>
<assemblage>
    <title> The Sine and Cosine Functions </title>
    <p></p>

    <sidebyside widths="50% 45%">
        <paragraphs>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
        		Given an angle <m>\theta \ </m> (in either degrees or radians) and the <m>(x,y)</m> coordinates of the corresponding point on the unit circle, we define cosine and sine as </p>
        	<p> <me>\cos(\theta)=x \hspace{.25in} \text{and} \hspace{.25in} \sin(\theta)=y</me> </p> 
        	<p>
       			Note that sine and cosine are <term>functions</term> that take angles as inputs. </p> </paragraphs>
		    <image source="images/SineandCosineDefinition.png"><description>unit circle with (x,y) and theta</description></image> </sidebyside>

</assemblage>

<p> Using the <m>(x,y)</m> coordinates we can find the cosine and sine values of common angles on the unit circle. </p>
<p>
	The applet below shows how the graphs of sine and cosine relate to the <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> coordinates of the point <m>P</m> on the unit circle. Move the slider to change the angle <m>\theta</m> and observe how the <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> values of point <m>P</m> relate to the outputs of <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and <m>\sin(\theta)</m>. </p>

<figure>
    <caption>How the Graphs of Sine and Cosine Relate to the Unit Circle</caption>
    <interactive geogebra="pJqvn9pR" width="100%" />
</figure>

<p>In addition to sine and cosine it is also useful to define several additional trigonometric functions.</p>
<assemblage>
	<title>The Tangent Function</title>
	<p> </p>
	
	<sidebyside widths="50% 40%">
	<paragraphs>
	    <p>
        	Given an angle <m>\theta \ </m> (in either degrees or radians) and the <m>(x,y)</m> coordinates of the corresponding point on the unit circle, we define tangent as
        <me>\tan(\theta)=\frac{y}{x}</me>
       		Just like sine and cosine, tangent is a <term>function</term> that takes angles as inputs. </p> </paragraphs>
    <image source="images/SineandCosineDefinition.png"><description>unit circle with (x,y) and theta</description></image> </sidebyside>
    <p>
    		Note that since <m>\sin(\theta)=y</m> and <m>\cos(\theta)=x</m>, we can also define tangent as
        <me>\tan(\theta)=\frac{\sin(\theta)}{\cos(\theta)}</me> </p> </assemblage>
        
<p>
	We can find the tangent values of common angles on the unit circle by using the sine and cosine values of the angles (or the corresponding <m>y</m> and <m>x</m> coordinates). </p>

<p>
	There are times when it can be useful to consider functions like <m>\frac{1}{\sin(\theta)}</m> or <m>\frac{1}{\cos(\theta)}</m>. This happens often enough that mathematicians have created special names for these types of functions. Generally, these functions are called reciprocal trigonometric functions, and they can be defined in terms of the sine, cosine, and tangent functions. </p>
	
<assemblage>
    <title>The Reciprocal Trigonometric Functions</title>
    <p></p>
    <p>
        Given an angle <m>\theta</m>, we define:
        <md>
        	<mrow>\amp \text{the secant function as } \amp\amp \sec(\theta)=\frac{1}{\cos(\theta)}</mrow>
        	<mrow></mrow>
        	<mrow>\amp \text{the cosecant function as } \amp\amp \csc(\theta)=\frac{1}{\sin(\theta)}</mrow>
        	<mrow></mrow>
        	<mrow>\amp \text{the cotangent function as } \amp\amp \cot(\theta)=\frac{1}{\tan(\theta)}</mrow>
        </md> </p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Inverse Trigonometric Functions</title>
<p>
    In the previous subsection, we evaluated trigonometric functions at various angles, but what if we needed to know what angle yields a specific sine, cosine, or tangent value. To find angles, we need inverse trigonometric functions.</p>

<assemblage>
	<title>The Inverse Sine, Inverse Cosine, and Inverse Tangent Functions</title>
	<p></p>
    <p>
        If <m>\sin(\theta)=a</m>, then <m>\sin^{-1}(a)=\theta</m> for <m>-1\leq a \leq 1</m> </p>
    <p>
        If <m>\cos(\theta)=a</m>, then <m>\cos^{-1}(a)=\theta</m> for <m>-1 \leq a \leq 1</m> </p>
    <p>
        If <m>\tan(\theta)=a</m>, then <m>\tan^{-1}(a)=\theta</m> for <m> -\infty \lt a \lt \infty </m> </p>
	<p> Note that the <em>output</em> of each of these inverse functions is an <em>angle</em>. </p>
        </assemblage>
  
<remark> <p>Do not confuse <m> \sin^{-1}(a) </m> with <m> \frac{1}{\sin(a)}</m> as they are not equivalent. The same can be said with <m> \cos^{-1}(a) </m> and <m> \tan^{-1}(a) </m>. As a result, we introduce an alternative (common) notation for the inverse trigonometric functions. 
</p></remark>        
        <note>
	<title>Common Notation for the Inverse Trigonometric Functions</title>
	<p></p>
    <p>
		The inverse sine function, <m>\sin^{-1}(a)</m> is sometimes called the <term>arcsine</term> function, and notated <m>\arcsin(a)</m>.</p>
	<p>
		The inverse cosine function, <m>\cos^{-1}(a)</m> is sometimes called the <term>arccosine</term> function, and notated <m>\arccos(a)</m>.</p>
	<p>
		The inverse tangent function, <m>\tan^{-1}(a)</m> is sometimes called the <term>arctangent</term> function, and notated <m>\arctan(a)</m>.</p>
</note>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Generalized Trigonometric Functions</title>
<p>
	Like all functions, trigonometric functions can be transformed by changing properties like the period, midline, and amplitude of the function. In this subsection, we explore transformations of the sine and cosine functions and use them to model real life situations. </p>
    
    
    <assemblage>
	<title>Transformations of Sine and Cosine</title>
	<p></p>
    <p>
        Given an equation in the form
        <me> f(t) = A\sin(Bt)+k \hspace{.25in} \text{ or } \hspace{.25in} g(t) = A\cos(Bt)+k </me> </p>
    <p>
    	<m>|A| \ </m> is the vertical stretch/compression and the <term>amplitude</term> of the function. </p>
    <p>
    	<m>|B| \ </m> is the horizontal stretch/compression and is <term>related</term> to the <term>period</term> of the function, <m>P</m>, by the formula <me>P=\frac{2\pi}{|B|}</me> </p>
    <p>
    	<m>k \ </m> is the vertical shift and determines the <term>midline</term> of the function. </p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>



<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-0-3" permid="QSl0-3">
    <exercise>
    <title>Period and Amplitude</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec5/Q17.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Period and Amplitude</title>
    <webwork source="local/setMath106/3-1.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Finding Trigonometric Functions</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec5/Q27.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
        <exercise>
    <title>Finding Trigonometric Functions</title>
    <webwork source="local/setMath106/W-3-2.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
        <exercise>
    <title>The Unit Circle</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec5/Q45.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Trigonometric Functions as Compositions</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec5/Q36.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      

</exercises>  
  
  </section>


<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
