<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-2-10-MVT" permid="kOT">
  <title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
  <objectives permid="pyM">
    <ul permid="hUn">
      <li permid="uiF">
        <p permid="eZH">
          Can we use global information about a function (average rate of change) to say anything about the local behavior of the function (instantaneous rate of change)?
        </p>
      </li>

    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction><p>
  If you know how a function behaves at every point then you know quite a lot about a function.  In fact, this is the whole idea behind plotting points on a coordinate plane in order to determine what the graph of a function looks like.  Indeed, given enough local information about a function we can describe it very well globally.  However, the opposite is not obviously true.  If you know how a function behaves overall, can you say anything about how the function behaves at a specific point?  For example, if you knew that <m>f(x)</m> was a parabola, can you determine the value of <m>f(3)</m>?  No! In order to determine the value of <m>f(3)</m> you need more information.  In general, global information is not enough to determine local information.  However, there are some special cases and one such special case is the mean value theorem.
  
</p>
  </introduction>
<subsection><title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
<example>
<p>
Imagine you have driven a car between Lincoln and Omaha Nebraska, a distance of 59 miles.  Suppose that it took you exactly three quarters of an hour to drive this distance.  Is it possible that you drove less than 75 miles per hour the entire trip?  The average rate of change was 78.67 miles per hour our intuition tells us that at some point on the trip you must have driven at least 78.67 miles per hour.  In fact, this is exactly the mean value theorem.
</p>
</example>
<assemblage><title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
Let <m>f</m> be a continuous function on the interval <m>[a,b]</m> and differentiable on the interval <m>(a,b)</m>, then there exists a number <m>c</m>, with <m>a\lt c \lt b</m>, such that <me>f'(c)=\dfrac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}.</me>  In other words, <m>f(b)-f(a)=f'(c)(b-a)</m>.
</assemblage>

<p>A proof of the mean value theorem is outside the scope of the text book.  However, it is worth noting that the mean value theorem essentially states that given any secant line between two points on a continuous curve, there is a line tangent to the curve at a point in-between those two points with the property that the slope of the tangent line and slope of the secant line are identical.  A geometric representaiton of the theorem is located in <xref ref="mvt">Figure</xref>.

</p>
<figure xml:id="mvt">
    <caption>To understand this theorem geometrically, look at the figure. Join the points on the curve where <m>x = a</m> and <m>x = b</m> with a secant line and observe that the slope of secant line <m> (f(b) - f(a))/(b - a)</m>. Notice that there appears to be at least one point between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> where the slope of the tangent line to the curve is precisely the same as the slope of the secant line.</caption>
    <image source="images/2-10-MVT.pdf" />
</figure>


</subsection>



</section>

