<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-3-4-applied-opt" permid="ZGh">
  <title>Applied Optimization</title>
  <objectives permid="SbI">
    <ul permid="qEs">
      <li permid="CSK">
        <p permid="zYe">
          In a setting where a situation is described for which optimal parameters are sought,
          how do we develop a function that models the situation and then use calculus to find the desired maximum or minimum?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="yiR">
    <p permid="dkH">
      Near the conclusion of <xref ref="sec-3-3-optimization">Section</xref>,
      we considered two optimization problems in which determining the function to be optimized was part of the problem.
      <xref ref="Ex-3-3-1">Example</xref> sought to maximize the total area enclosed by the combination of 
      an equilateral triangle and a square built from a single piece of wire (cut in two).
      <xref ref="act-3-3-3">Example</xref> subsequently investigated how the volume of 
      a box constructed by removing squares from the corners of a piece of cardboard 
      is dependent on the size of the squares removed.
    </p>

    <p permid="JrQ">
      Neither of these problems explicitly provided a function to optimize.
      Instead, we first tried to understand the problem by
      drawing a figure and introducing variables,
      and then sought to develop a formula for a function that modeled the quantity
      to be optimized.
      Upon establishing a function, we chose an appropriate domain and then 
      were finally ready to apply the ideas of calculus to determine the absolute minimum or maximum.
    </p>

    <p permid="pyZ">
      In this section
      the primary emphasis is on the reader solving problems.
      Initially, some substantial guidance is provided,
      but the problems progress to require greater independence as we move along.
    </p>

<example xml:id="PA-3-4" permid="uUz">
<statement>
  <p permid="iGh">
    According to U.S.<nbsp />postal regulations,
    the girth plus the length of a parcel sent by mail may not exceed 108 inches,
    where by <q>girth</q> we mean the perimeter of the smallest end.
    What is the largest possible volume of a rectangular parcel with a square end that can be sent by mail?
    What are the dimensions of such a package?
    The process of answering these questions has been broken up into a sequence of tasks:
  </p>

  <p permid="ONq">
    <ol label="a." permid="ovt">
      <li permid="UCC">
        <p permid="lAN">
          Let <m>x</m> represent the length of one side of the square end and <m>y</m> the length of the longer side.
          Label these quantities appropriately on an image like the one shown in <xref ref="F-3-4-PA1">Figure</xref> below.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-3-4-PA1" permid="RHW">
          <caption>A rectangular parcel with a square end.</caption>
          <image width="47%" source="images/3_4_PA1" />
        </figure>

      </li>

      <li permid="AJL">
        <p permid="xPf">
          What is the quantity to be optimized in this problem?
          Find a formula for this quantity in terms of <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="gQU">
        <p permid="dWo">
          The problem statement tells us that the parcel's girth plus length may not exceed 108 inches.
          In order to maximize volume,
          we assume that we will actually need the girth plus length to equal 108 inches.
          What equation does this produce involving <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="MYd">
        <p permid="Kdx">
          Solve the equation you found in (c) for one of <m>x</m> or <m>y</m>
          (whichever is easier).
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="tfm">
        <p permid="qkG">
          Now use your work in (b) and (d) to determine a formula for the volume of the parcel so that this formula is a function of a single variable.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Zmv">
        <p permid="WrP">
          Over what domain should we consider this function?
          Note that both <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> must be positive;
          how does the constraint that girth plus length is 108 inches produce intervals of possible values for <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="FtE">
        <p permid="CyY">
          Find the absolute maximum of the volume of the parcel on the domain you established in (f) and hence also determine the dimensions of the box of greatest volume.
          Justify that you've found the maximum using calculus.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </p>
</statement>
<hint>
  <p>
  <ol label="a">
    <li>
    <p>
    Sketch a picture of a box with a square end; you'll want to add to it as the 
    problem progresses. Note that the question's wording suggests the square end should 
    be the smallest end. What does that tell you about which of <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> 
    is bigger?
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    What are you trying to maximize or minimize?
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Recall that the girth is the perimeter of the smallest end. 
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Pick a variable to isolate and use basic algebra to solve for it.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Substitute your answer to (d) into your formula from (b).
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Each term in the sum has to be between <m>0</m> and <m>108</m>. 
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Find the critical numbers of the volume function and use the first or second 
    derivative test to ascertain which is a maximum.
    Once you have an answer, don't forget to check that it actually works: the fact that 
    the girth measures the <em>smallest</em> end of the box tells you which of <m>x</m>
    or <m>y</m> should be bigger (based on the formulas you used). Does that relationship 
    hold with the dimensions you found? If not, you'll need to rework the problem.
    </p>
    </li>
  </ol>
  </p>
</hint>
<answer>
  <p>
  <ol label="a">
    <li>
    <p>
    Since the problem says <m>y</m> is the length of the <em>longer</em> side, we assume
    <m>x\le y</m> and that the square end is smallest.
    <figure>
      <caption>A rectangular parcel with smallest end a square.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/3_3_labeledbox.pdf" />
    </figure>
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    We want to maximize volume: <m>V=x^2y</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    If the square end is smallest, then <m>4x+y=108</m> and <m>x\le y</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    <m>y=108-4x</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    <m>V(x)=x^2(108-4x)</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    <m>0\lt x\le 21.6</m>, and <m>x\le y\lt 108</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    The maximum volume is <m>11,664\text{ in}^3</m> when the box is 
    <m>18''\times18''\times36''</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
  </ol>
  </p>
</answer>
<solution>
  <p>
  <ol label="a">
    <li>
    <p>
    Since the problem says <m>y</m> is the length of the <em>longer</em> side, we assume
    <m>x\le y</m> and that the square end is smallest. However, we recognize that this 
    may not end up being the case, and if necessary are prepared to rework the problem 
    with the square end as the largest side.
    <figure>
      <caption>A rectangular parcel with smallest end a square.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/3_3_labeledbox.pdf" />
    </figure>
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    We are asked to maximize the volume of the box. Since the box has a square end with 
    side length <m>x</m> inches and is <m>y</m> inches long, the volume formula is 
    <me>V=x^2y</me>, measured in cubic inches.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    We are working under the assumption that the square end is the smallest end, which 
    means the perimeter of the square face will be the girth and the other side will 
    be the length. This yields the relation <me>4x+y=108</me>. We note again that we have 
    the assumed constraint <m>x\le y</m>. 
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Since <m>4x+y=108</m>, we can say that <m>y=108-4x</m>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    Since <m>V=x^2y</m> and <m>y=108-4x</m>, an alternate expression for the parcel's 
    volume is <me>V(x)=x^2(108-4x)=108x^2-4x^3</me>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    We know that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> must both be positive, so we have <m>0\lt x,y</m>. 
    Additionally, because the girth is given by <m>4x</m> rather than by <m>2x+2y</m> 
    (the perimeter of the other sides), we can say that <m>x\le y</m>.
    Finally, since <m>4x+y=108</m> and <m>x\le y</m>, it must be the case that 
    <m>5x\le4x+y=108</m>, so <m>x\le 108/5=21.6</m>. Likewise, since <m>x</m> is positive, we must 
    have <m>y\lt 108</m>. 
    In sum, we have the intervals: <me>0\lt x\le21.6 \text{ and }x\le y\lt108</me>.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>
    <p>
    We now need to maximize the function <m>V(x)=108x^2-4x^3</m> on the interval <m>(0,21.6]</m>. 
    We begin by differentiating <m>V</m>, finding <me>V'(x)=216x-12x^2=12x(18-x)</me>.
    As <m>V'(x)</m> is a polynomial, it is defined everywhere; to find the critical numbers 
    of <m>V</m>, then, we need only solve the equation <m>V'(x)=0</m>. 
    Doing so yields the critical numbers <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=18</m>. On the interval 
    <m>0\lt x\le21.6</m>, the only critical number is <m>18</m>. 
    </p>
    <p>
    Testing to check that this is a maximum, the first derivative test says <m>V'(x)\gt0</m>
    for <m>0\lt x\lt 18</m> and <m>V'(x)\lt0</m> for <m>18\lt x</m>. Thus <m>V(18)</m> is
    a relative maximum and, on the interval <m>(0,21.6]</m> (or more generally, the 
    interval <m>(0,\infty)</m>), an absolute maximum. 
    Further supporting this conclusion is the second derivative test, where <m>V''(x)=216-24x</m> 
    is zero only when <m>x=9</m>, and <m>V''(18)\lt0</m>, showing that <m>V</m> is concave 
    down on (at least) the interval <m>(9,21.6)</m>.
    </p>
    <p>
    We have firmly established that the maximum volume occurs when <m>x=18</m>. This coincides 
    with the length <m>y=108-4(18)=36</m> and the volume <m>V=(18)^2(36)=11,664</m>. Therefore the maximum volume 
    of a parcel with a square end (provided that end is the smallest end of the box<fn>
    It turns out that when we assume the square end is the larger end, we end up with 
    the dimensions <m>24\times24\times18</m> and a volume of <m>10,368\text{ in}^3</m>, 
    so our process did indeed find the maximum volume of a parcel with a square end.</fn>) subject 
    to the dimension constraints of the USPS is <m>11,664</m> cubic inches. This volume 
    is achieved when the package is <m>18</m> inches by <m>18</m> inches by <m>36</m> inches. 
    </p>
    </li>
  </ol>
  </p>
</solution>
</example>
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="FNq">
    <title>More Applied Optimization Problems</title>
    <p permid="VGi">
      Many of the steps in <xref ref="PA-3-4">Example</xref>
      are ones that we will execute in any applied optimization problem.
      We briefly summarize those here to provide an overview of our approach in subsequent questions:
    </p>

      <p permid="xdy">
        <ol permid="Kxj">
          <li permid="iZT">
            <p permid="gfn">
              <em>Draw a picture and introduce variables.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              It is essential to first understand what quantities are allowed to vary in the problem and then to represent those values with variables.
              Constructing a figure with these variables labeled is a particularly helpful way to accomplish this;
              in some cases, drawing several diagrams might be useful.
              A nice example of this can be seen at <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/99">http://gvsu.edu/s/99</url>,
              where the choice of where to bend a piece of wire into the shape of a rectangle determines both the rectangle's shape and area.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="Phc">
            <p permid="Mmw">
              <em>Identify the quantity to be optimized as well as any key relationships among the variable quantities.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              Essentially this step involves writing equations that involve the variables that have been introduced:
              one equation will represent the quantity whose minimum or maximum is sought;
              there may be additional equations showing how multiple variables in the problem are interrelated.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="vol">
            <p permid="stF">
              <em>Determine a function of a single variable that models the quantity to be optimized.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              It may be necessary to eliminate one or more variables in the function formula 
              using the secondary equations that were found in the previous step.
              For example, in <xref ref="PA-3-4">Example</xref>
              we initially found that <m>V = x^2 y</m>;
              the additional relationship that <m>4x + y = 108</m>
              allowed us to substitute <m>108-4x</m> for <m>y</m> in the volume equation, thus
              expressing the volume as a function of the single variable <m>x</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="bvu">
            <p permid="YAO">
              <em>Decide the domain on which to consider the function being optimized.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              Often the physical constraints of the problem will limit the possible values that the independent variable can take on.
              Thinking back to the picture that describes the overall situation and any relationships among variables in the problem often helps identify the smallest and largest values of the input variable.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="HCD">
            <p permid="EHX">
              <em>Use calculus to identify the absolute maximum and/or minimum of the quantity being optimized.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              This always involves finding the critical numbers of the function first.
              Then depending on the domain,
              we either construct a first derivative sign chart
              (for an open or unbounded interval)
              or evaluate the function at the endpoints and critical numbers
              (for a closed, bounded interval).
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="nJM">
            <p permid="kPg">
              <em>Finally, we make certain we have answered the question that was posed.</em>
            </p>
            <p>
              Does the question seek the absolute maximum of a quantity,
              or do we need the values of the variables that produce the maximum?
              In other words, 
              finding the maximum volume of a parcel is different from finding the dimensions of the parcel that yield that volume.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    <p>
    The remaining examples involve a variety of quantities to be optimized.
    Each task presents an opportunity to practice the above steps, possibly with some 
    adaptations to suit the context of the problem.
    </p>
    
<example xml:id="act-3-4-1" permid="LZK">
  <statement>
    <p permid="nxa">
      A soup can in the shape of a right circular cylinder is to be made from two materials.
      The material for the side of the can costs <dollar />0.015 per square inch and the material for the lids costs <dollar /><m>0.027</m> per square inch.
      Suppose that we desire to construct a can that has a volume of 16 cubic inches.
      What dimensions minimize the cost of the can?

      <ol label="a." permid="ayO">
        <li permid="GFX">
          <p permid="AQL">
            Draw a picture of the can and label its dimensions with appropriate variables.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="mNg">
          <p permid="gXU">
            Use your variables to determine expressions for the volume,
            surface area, and cost of the can.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="SUp">
          <p permid="Nfd">
            Determine the total cost function as a function of a single variable.
            What is the domain on which you should consider this function?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="zby">
          <p permid="tmm">
            Find the absolute minimum cost and the dimensions that produce this value.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="BWe">
    <p permid="HpR">
      <ol label="a." permid="urF">
        <li permid="fiH">
          <p permid="Ztv">
            Note that both the radius and the height of the can are variable.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="LpQ">
          <p permid="FAE">
            Remember that volume is the area of the base times the height,
            while surface area can be thought of in terms of the area of the two lids,
            plus the area of the <q>side</q> of the can.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="rwZ">
          <p permid="lHN">
            Use the fact that <m>V = 16</m> to write one of the variables in terms of the other.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="XEi">
          <p permid="ROW">
            Differentiate the total cost function and find its critical number(s) first.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="VOV">
    <p permid="biI">
      <ol label="a." permid="Okw">
        <li permid="DLr">
          <p permid="xWf">
            Let the can have radius <m>r</m> and height <m>h</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="jSA">
          <p permid="edo">
            The volume is <m>V = \pi r^2 h</m>;
            the surface area is <m>S = 2 \pi r^2 + 2 \pi r h</m>;
            the total cost is <m> C = 2 \pi r^2 \cdot 0.027 + 2 \pi r h \cdot 0.015</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="PZJ">
          <p permid="Kkx">
            The cost as a single-variable function is <m>C(r) = 0.054 \pi r^2 + 0.48 \frac{1}{r}</m>,
            considered on the interval <m>r \gt 0</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="wgS">
          <p permid="qrG">
            The minimizing radius is <m>r = \sqrt[3]{ \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} } \approx 1.123</m> inches;
            the minimizing height is <m>h \approx 4.041</m> inches;
            the minimum cost is <m>C(1.12259) \approx \$0.642</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="pHM">
    <p permid="vbz">
      <ol label="a." permid="idn">
        <li permid="cob">
          <p permid="WyP">
            We let <m>r</m> be the radius of the base of the cylindrical can and <m>h</m> be its height.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Ivk">
          <p permid="CFY">
            The volume of a cylinder is the area of the base times the height,
            so <m>V = \pi r^2 h</m>.
            Surface area is the area of the lids plus the area of the <q>side</q>;
            we can think of the side as a rectangle (if we were to cut it and unroll it)
            with height <m>h</m> and width <m>2\pi r</m>, the perimeter of the base. 
            Hence the surface area of the can is <me>S = 2 \pi r^2 + 2 \pi r h</me>.
            Finally,
            the total cost (in dollars) is the cost of the lids plus the cost of the sides, which is
            <me permid="TEj">
              C = 2 \pi r^2 \cdot 0.027 + 2 \pi r h \cdot 0.015
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="oCt">
          <p permid="iNh">
            Because the volume is fixed at 16 cubic inches,
            we know that <m>16 =  \pi r^2 h</m>.
            Choosing to solve for <m>h</m>, we find that <m>h = \frac{16}{\pi r^2}</m>.
            We can then substitute this expression into the total cost formula in 
            place of <m>h</m>, yielding 
            <md permid="zLs">
              <mrow>C(r) =\mathstrut\amp 2 \pi r^2 \cdot 0.027 + 2 \pi r \left( \frac{16}{\pi r^2} \right) \cdot 0.015</mrow> 
              <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp 0.054 \pi r^2 + \frac{0.48}{r}</mrow>
            </md>.
            We note that the only constraint on <m>r</m> is that <m>r \gt 0</m>,
            hence this is the domain on which we seek to minimize <m>C</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="UJC">
          <p permid="OUq">
            To differentiate the cost function, we first recall that <m>\frac1r=r^{-1}</m> 
            and then find 
            <md>
            <mrow>C'(r)=\mathstrut\amp 0.108\pi r-0.48r^{-2}</mrow>
            <mrow>=\mathstrut\amp 0.108 \pi r - \frac{0.48}{r^2}</mrow>
            </md>.
            Note that <m>C'(r)</m> is undefined at <m>r=0</m>, but this point is not in 
            the domain of <m>C</m>,<fn>
            Here, we mean both that <m>C(0)</m> is undefined and that contextually we 
            require <m>r\gt0</m> as discussed in (c). Because <m>C(0)</m> is undefined, 
            <m>0</m> is not a true critical number of <m>C</m>; however, it is still a 
            value at which the sign of <m>C'</m> can change, and we can only disregard 
            it here because the contextual supposition that <m>r\gt0</m> stipulates 
            that we need only find critical numbers on the interval <m>(0,\infty)</m>.
            </fn> so we only need to consider critical numbers at 
            which the derivative is zero. 
            Hence we set <m>C'(r) = 0</m> and solve for <m>r</m>, finding that
            <me permid="fSB">
              0.108 \pi r = \frac{0.48}{r^2}
            </me>,
            so that <m>r^3 = \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} \approx 1.415</m>,
            from which it follows that
            <m>r = \sqrt[3]{ \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} } \approx 1.123</m> is the only critical number of <m>C</m>.
            At this point
            we can use either the first or second derivative test to justify that <m>C</m> 
            has an absolute minimum at <m>r = \sqrt[3]{ \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} }</m>.
            We choose to use the second derivative test;
            note that <m>C''(r) = 0.108 \pi + 0.96 \frac{1}{r^3}</m>,
            which is always positive for <m>r \gt 0</m>.
            Thus <m>C</m> is always concave up on the relevant domain (<m>r \gt 0</m>),
            and consequently <m>r = \sqrt[3]{ \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} } \approx 1.123</m> 
            is where the absolute minimum of <m>C</m> occurs.
            In addition, we note that since <m>h = \frac{16}{\pi r^2}</m>,
            the corresponding <m>h</m> value is <m>h \approx 4.041</m>,
            and the overall minimum value is <m>C\left(\sqrt[3]{ \frac{0.48}{0.108 \pi} }\right) \approx 0.641</m>.
          </p>
          <p>
          Thus a can with radius approximately <m>1.123</m> inches and height approximately 
          <m>4.041</m> inches will be cheapest among all cans with a volume of <m>16</m> 
          cubic inches. The cost of constructing a can with these dimensions is about 
          <m>\$0.641</m>, or roughly <m>64</m> cents.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

    <p permid="BNr">
      Familiarity with common geometric formulas is particularly helpful in problems such as the one in <xref ref="act-3-4-1">Example</xref>.
      Sometimes those involve perimeter,
      area, volume, or surface area.
      At other times,
      the constraints of a problem introduce right triangles
      (where the Pythagorean Theorem applies)
      or other functions whose formulas provide relationships among the variables.
    </p>

<example xml:id="act-3-4-2" permid="eNi">
  <statement>
    <p permid="NOX">
      A hiker starting at a point <m>P</m> on a straight road walks east towards point <m>Q</m>,
      which is on the road and three kilometers from point <m>P</m>.
    <!--</p>-->
    <!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">-->
    <!--<p permid="tWg">-->
      Two kilometers due north of point <m>Q</m> is a cabin.
      The hiker will walk down the road for a while,
      at a pace of <m>8</m> kilometers per hour.
      At some point <m>Z</m> between <m>P</m> and <m>Q</m>,
      the hiker leaves the road and makes a straight line towards the cabin through the woods,
      hiking at a pace of <m>3</m> kph,
      as pictured below in <xref ref="F-3-4-Act2">Figure</xref>.
      In order to minimize the time to go from <m>P</m> to <m>Z</m> to the cabin,
      where should the hiker turn into the forest?
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-3-4-Act2" permid="adp">
      <caption>A hiker walks from <m>P</m> to <m>Z</m> to the cabin, as pictured.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/3_4_Act2" />
    </figure>
<!--</sidebyside>-->
  </statement>
  <hint permid="Evl">
    <p permid="hHO">
      Let <m>x</m> be the distance from <m>Z</m> to <m>Q</m>.
      What is the distance from <m>P</m> to <m>Z</m> in terms of <m>x</m>?
      How about the distance from <m>Z</m> to the cabin?
      How does time depend on distance and walking speed?
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="Yoc">
    <p permid="BAF">
      The absolute minimum time the hiker can achieve is about <m>0.993</m> hours,
      which is attained by hiking about <m>2.2</m> km from <m>P</m> towards <m>Q</m> 
      and then turning into the woods for the remainder of the trip.
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="sgT">
    <p permid="kCu">
      We begin by letting <m>x</m> be the distance from <m>Z</m> to <m>Q</m>.
      Since it is <m>3</m> km from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m>,
      the distance from <m>P</m> to <m>Z</m> is <m>3-x</m> km.
      Furthermore, we can use the Pythagorean Theorem to find that
      the distance from <m>Z</m> to the cabin is <m>\sqrt{4+x^2}</m> km.
    </p>

    <p permid="QJD">
      Next we want to determine the hiker's time as a function of <m>x</m>.
      Because distance equals rate times time,
      it follows that time is distance divided by rate.
      The hiker travels along the road for <m>3-x</m> km at a pace of <m>8</m> km/hr,
      thus her time on the road is
      <me permid="Gky">
        T_r = \frac{3-x}{8} \text{ hr}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="wQM">
      Once she enters the woods,
      her pace drops to <m>3</m> km/hr and she continues for <m>\sqrt{4+x^2}</m> km 
      before reaching the cabin.
      She spends a total of 
      <me permid="mrH">
        T_w = \frac{\sqrt{4+x^2}}{3}
      </me>
      hours hiking in the woods.
    </p>

    <p permid="cXV">
      Altogether, the time it takes the hiker to reach the cabin is given by the function 
      <me permid="SyQ">
        T(x) = \frac{3-x}{8} + \frac{\sqrt{4+x^2}}{3}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Jfe">
      Because the only values of <m>x</m> that make sense to use are <m>0 \le x \le 3</m>
      (since walking away from or past <m>Q</m> before turning to the cabin both add unnecessary time to the trip),
<!--      (using either negative values or values greater than <m>3</m> add unnecessary time to the trip),-->
      we use this domain for <m>T</m> and now seek the absolute minimum of <m>T</m> on <m>[0,3]</m>.
      We find that
      <me permid="yFZ">
        T'(x) = -\frac{1}{8} + \frac{1}{3} \cdot \frac{1}{2} \left(4+x^2\right)^{-1/2} (2x) = -\frac{1}{8} + \frac{x}{3\sqrt{4+x^2}}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="pmn">
      Note that since <m>4+x^2\ge2</m> for every value of <m>x</m>, <m>T'</m> is defined everywhere. 
      Setting <m>T'(x) = 0</m> and solving for <m>x</m>,
      we have <m>\frac{x}{3\sqrt{4+x^2}} = \frac{1}{8}</m>,
      so <m>8x = 3\sqrt{4+x^2}</m>.
      Squaring both sides yields <me>64x^2 = 9(4+x^2) = 36 + 9x^2</me>.
      Hence <m>55x^2 = 36</m>,
      so <m>x = \sqrt{\frac{36}{55}} \approx 0.809</m>.
      (We don't consider the critical number
      <m>x = -\sqrt{\frac{36}{55}}</m> because this doesn't lie in the relevant domain of <m>T</m>.)
    </p>

    <p permid="Vtw">
      Finally, we evaluate <m>T</m> at the only critical number in the interval and at the interval's endpoints.
      Doing so, we find <m>T(0) = \frac{3}{8} + \frac{2}{3} \approx 1.0417</m>,
      <m>T(3) = \frac{\sqrt{13}}{3} \approx 1.202</m>,
      and <m>T\left(\sqrt{\frac{36}{55}}\right) = \frac{3}{8} + \frac{\sqrt{55}}{12} \approx 0.993</m>.
      Thus the absolute minimum time the hiker can achieve is about <m>0.993</m> hours,
      which is attained by hiking about <m>2.2</m> km from <m>P</m> towards <m>Q</m> and then turning into the woods for the remainder of the trip.
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

    <p permid="hUA">
      In more geometric problems,
      we often use curves or functions to provide natural constraints.
      For instance,
      we could investigate which isosceles triangle that circumscribes a unit circle has the smallest area<fn>
      You can explore for this problem for yourself at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9b">http://gvsu.edu/s/9b</url>.
      </fn>,
      or we might seek the rectangle of largest area that fits within a region bounded by a parabola<fn>
      An example of this is shown at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9c">http://gvsu.edu/s/9c</url>.
      </fn>.
      The next example is similar to the latter problem.
    </p>

<example xml:id="act-3-4-3" permid="YXW">
  <statement>
    <p permid="Uod">
      Consider the region in the <m>xy</m>-plane that is bounded by the <m>x</m>-axis and the function <m>f(x) = 25-x^2</m>. 
      Construct a rectangle whose base lies on the <m>x</m>-axis and is centered at the origin,
      and whose sides extend vertically until they intersect the curve <m>y = 25-x^2</m>.
      Which such rectangle has the maximum possible area?
      Which such rectangle has the greatest perimeter?
      Which has the greatest combined perimeter and area? (Challenge:
      answer the same questions in terms of positive parameters <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> for the function <m>f(x) = b-ax^2</m>.)
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="XiJ">
    <p permid="ogU">
      Start with a sketch of the region and a rectangle within it that satisfies the description. 
      Let <m>x</m> represent half the width of the rectangle's base.
      How does the rectangle's height depend on <m>x</m>?
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="rbA">
    <p permid="HZL">
      The maximum area is <m>\frac{500}{3\sqrt3}\approx96.225</m> square units when the 
      rectangle's base is <m>\frac{10}{\sqrt3}</m> units long. 
      The maximum perimeter is <m>52</m> units when the rectangle's base is <m>2</m> units long. 
      The maximum combined perimeter and area is about <m>141.858</m>, occurring when the 
      rectangle's base is <m>\frac{2\sqrt{82}-2}3\approx5.370</m> units long.
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="KUr">
  <p> 
  We start by drawing a picture of the region described, along with a rectangle satisfying the 
  description in the problem. Shown below in <xref ref="F-3-3-region">Figure</xref>, this 
  picture will be a useful reference throughout the problem.
  </p>
  
    <figure xml:id="F-3-3-region">
      <caption>The region in the <m>xy</m>-plane bounded below by the <m>x</m>-axis and above by the graph of <m>y=25-x^2</m>.
      Within this region is a rectangle whose base lies on the <m>x</m>-axis and is centered at the origin, and whose top corners lie 
      on the curve. Note that if <m>x</m> represents half the width of the rectangle's base, 
      then the rectangle's height is <m>f(x)=25-x^2</m>.</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/3-3-region.pdf"/>
    </figure>
  
    <p permid="DpS">
      As shown in <xref ref="F-3-3-region">Figure</xref>, the area of the rectangle is 
      <me permid="Avm">
        A(x) = (2x)(25-x^2) = 50x - 2x^3
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="jxb">
      Based on the region and our definition of <m>x</m>, 
      the only possible values of <m>x</m> are for <m>0 \le x \le 5</m>;
      moreover, it is evident that for either <m>x = 0</m> or <m>x = 5</m>,
      the area of the corresponding rectangle is zero. 
      Thus the endpoints of the domain <m>[0,5]</m> both minimize the area.
      Differentiating <m>A</m> with respect to <m>x</m> yields
      <me permid="gCv">
        A'(x) = 50 - 6x^2
      </me>,
      so we find the critical numbers of <m>A</m> by solving <m>6x^2 = 50</m>.
      This yields <m>x = \pm\frac{5}{\sqrt{3}} \approx \pm2.8868</m>, but we need only 
      the positive value in this context.
      Taking <m>x=\frac5{\sqrt3}</m> gives the maximum possible area of 
      <me permid="MJE">
        A\left(\frac{5}{\sqrt{3}}\right) = \frac{500}{3\sqrt3} \approx 96.225
      </me>
      square units.
    </p>

    <p permid="PEk">
    We next want to maximize the perimeter. We can see in <xref ref="F-3-3-region">Figure</xref>
    that the rectangle's perimeter is
      <me permid="sQN">
        P(x) = 2(2x) + 2(25-x^2)= -2x^2 + 4x + 50
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="vLt">
      It is straightforward to show that the only critical number of the quadratic function <m>P</m> occurs when <m>x = 1</m> and that the corresponding (maximum) perimeter is <m>P(1) = 52</m> units.
    </p>

    <p permid="bSC">
      Finally, to consider combined area and perimeter,
      examine the function <m>C(x) = A(x) + P(x)</m> on the interval <m>0 \le x \le 5</m>.
      You should find that the only relevant critical number is
      <m>x = \frac{\sqrt{82}-1}{3}</m> and that the absolute maximum of <m>C</m> occurs at that value.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    To summarize, the rectangle with the largest area has vertices at <m>\left(0,\pm\frac5{\sqrt3}\right)</m> 
    and <m>\left(\frac{50}3,\pm\frac5{\sqrt3}\right)</m>, and has an area of <m>\frac{500}{3\sqrt3}\approx96.225</m> square units. 
    The rectangle with the largest perimeter has vertices at <m>\left(0,\pm1\right)</m> 
    and <m>\left(24,\pm1\right)</m>, and has a perimeter of <m>52</m> units. 
    The rectangle with the largest combined total of perimeter and area has vertices at 
    <m>\left(0,\pm\frac{\sqrt{82}-1}3\right)</m> and 
    <m>\left(\frac{142+2\sqrt{82}}9,\pm\frac{\sqrt{82}-1}3\right)</m>, and the 
    combined total is approximately <m>141.858</m>.
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

<example xml:id="act-3-4-4" permid="zpT">
  <statement>
    <p permid="OyR">
      A trough is being constructed by bending a <m>4 \times 24</m>
      (measured in feet)
      rectangular piece of sheet metal.
    </p>
    <!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">-->
    <p permid="uGa">
      Two symmetric folds <m>2</m> feet apart will be made parallel to the longest side of the rectangle so that the trough has cross-sections in the shape of a trapezoid,
      as pictured below in <xref ref="F-3-4-Act4">Figure</xref>.
      At what angle should the folds be made to produce the trough of maximum volume?
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-3-4-Act4" permid="aNj">
      <caption>A cross-section of the trough formed by folding each side to an angle of <m>\theta</m>.
      The base of the trough is two feet across; the angled sides are each a foot long.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/3_4_Act4" />
    </figure>
<!--</sidebyside>-->
  </statement>
  <hint permid="Rtx">
    <p permid="irI">
    How tall is the trough in terms of <m>\theta</m>? How wide is the top of the trough,
    also in terms of <m>\theta</m>? Find (or add) some useful right triangles to the given diagram to complete the picture.
    Also, is there a slightly simpler quantity that will be maximized at the same time as the volume? 
<!--      Drop altitudes from the top of the trough to the base of length 2.
      In the two triangles that are formed,
      what are the lengths of the legs in terms of <m>\theta</m>? -->
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="lmo">
    <p permid="Ckz">
<!--      <m>A(1.19606) \approx 2.2018</m> is the absolute maximum cross-sectional area,
      which leads to the absolute maximum volume. -->
      The volume is maximized when <m>\theta\approx1.196</m> radians.
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="Fff">
    <p permid="xAG">
      Once we choose the angle <m>\theta</m>,
      the two right triangles in the trapezoid are determined
      and each has a horizontal leg of length
      <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and a vertical leg of length <m>\sin(\theta)</m>.
      Thus the sum of the areas of the two triangles is <m>\cos(\theta) \sin(\theta)</m>,
      the area of the rectangle between them is <m>2\sin(\theta)</m>, 
      and the total area of the trapezoidal cross-section is <me>A(\theta) = \cos(\theta) \sin(\theta) + 2 \sin(\theta)</me>.
      Because the length of the trough is constant,
      the trough's volume will be maximized by maximizing cross-sectional area.
      Note, too, that the domain for <m>\theta</m> is <m>0 \le \theta \le \frac{\pi}{2}</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="dHP">
      Differentiating the area function, we find that
      <me permid="GUs">
        A'(\theta) =  -\sin^2(\theta) + \cos^2(\theta) + 2 \cos(\theta)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="JOY">
      Using the identity <m>\sin^2(\theta) = 1 - \cos^2(\theta)</m>,
      it follows that
      <md permid="nbB">
        <mrow>A'(\theta) =\mathstrut\amp \cos^2(\theta) - 1 + \cos^2(\theta) + 2 \cos(\theta)</mrow>
        <mrow> =\mathstrut\amp 2\cos^2(\theta) + 2 \cos(\theta) - 1</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p permid="pWh">
      This most recent equation is quadratic in <m>\cos(\theta)</m>,
      so we can solve the equation
      <m>A'(\theta) = 0</m> by letting <m>u=\cos(\theta)</m> and 
      first solving <m>2u^2 + 2u - 1 = 0</m>.<fn>
      Note that since <m>0\le\theta\le\frac{\pi}2</m>, we have <m>0\le u\le1</m>.</fn> 
      Doing so yields
      <me permid="TiK">
        u = \frac{-1 \pm \sqrt{3}}{2} \approx 0.366, -1.366
      </me>,
      so only <m>u = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{3}}{2}</m> might be a value of the cosine function from an angle that lies in the interval <m>[0,\frac{\pi}{2}]</m>.
      To find the corresponding critical number <m>\theta</m>,
      we solve <m>\cos(\theta) = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{3}}{2}</m>,
      which implies <m>\theta = \arccos\left(\frac{-1 + \sqrt{3}}{2}\right) \approx 1.196</m> radians,
      or <m>\theta \approx 68.529^\circ</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Wdq">
      Finally, to confirm that <m>A</m> has an absolute maximum at <m>\theta = \arccos\left(\frac{-1 + \sqrt{3}}{2}\right)</m>,
      we evaluate <m>A</m> at this value and at the interval endpoints
      to find that <m>A(0) = 0</m>,
      <m>A(\frac{\pi}{2}) = 2</m>,
      and <m>A(1.196) \approx 2.202</m> ft<m>^2</m>,
      which is the absolute maximum possible cross-sectional area.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Therefore the volume of the trough is maximized (at around <m>52.844</m> cubic feet) 
    when the sides are folded at an angle of approximately <m>1.196</m> radians. 
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="lUz">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="ObJ">
      <ul permid="WLB">
        <li permid="TQV">
          <p permid="QWp">
            While there is no single algorithm that works in every situation where optimization is used,
            the following steps are helpful in most of the problems we consider:
            draw a picture and introduce variables;
            identify the quantity to be optimized and find relationships among the variables;
            determine a function of a single variable that models the quantity to be optimized;
            decide the domain on which to consider the function being optimized;
            use calculus to identify the absolute maximum and/or minimum of the quantity being optimized;
            check that the question that was asked has indeed been answered.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"> 

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW1" permid="zsk">
    <title>Maximizing the volume of a box</title>
    <webwork source="Library/UVA-Stew5e/setUVA-Stew5e-C04S07-Optimization/4-7-08.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW2" permid="fzt">
    <title>Minimizing the cost of a container</title>
    <webwork source="Library/UVA-Stew5e/setUVA-Stew5e-C04S07-Optimization/4-7-12.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW3" permid="LGC">
    <title>Maximizing area contained by a fence</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP01.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW4" permid="rNL">
    <title>Minimizing the area of a poster</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP04.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW5" permid="XUU">
    <title>Maximizing the area of a rectangle</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP05.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="Ecd">
  <title>Maximizing the volume of a closed box</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="ELX">
        A rectangular box with a square bottom and closed top is to be made from two materials.
        The material for the side costs <dollar />1.50 per square foot and the material for the top and bottom costs <dollar />3.00 per square foot.
        If you are willing to spend <dollar />15 on the box,
        what is the largest volume it can contain?
        Justify your answer completely using calculus.
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="ILW">
      <p permid="gjn">
        The absolute maximum volume is <m>V\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right) = \frac{15}{12}\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right) - \frac{1}{4}\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right)^3 \approx 1.07583</m> cubic feet.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="cEN">
      <p permid="ZKh">
        Let <m>x</m> be the length of one side of the square bottom and <m>h</m> the height of one of the sides.
        We first note that the volume, <m>V</m>,
        of the box is <m>V = x^2 h</m>,
        and the surface area of the box is <m>S = 2x^2 +  4xh</m>,
        since there are two square sides
        (bottom and top)
        of area <m>x^2</m> and four identical sides of area <m>xh</m>.
        Since the material for the top and bottom costs <dollar />3.00 per square foot and the material for the sides costs <dollar />1.50 per square foot,
        it follows that the total cost of a box with surface area <m>S</m> is
        <me permid="doH">
          C = 1.50 (2x^2) +  3.00 (4xh) = 3x^2 + 12xh
        </me>.
      </p>

      <p permid="FRq">
        We are interested in building box of largest volume for which we spend <dollar />15.
        This cost constraint implies that
        <me permid="JvQ">
          15 = 3x^2 + 12xh
        </me>,
        which allows us to express <m>h</m> as a function of <m>x</m> by solving for <m>h</m>.
        Doing so, we see that <m>12xh = 15 - 3x^2</m>, so
        <me permid="pCZ">
          h = \frac{15-3x^2}{12x}
        </me>.
        Using this relationship, we are now able to express the volume,
        <m>V</m>,
        of the box as a function of the single variable <m>x</m>.
        Subsituting the expression for <m>h</m>, we have
        <me permid="VKi">
          V = x^2 h = x^2 \frac{15-3x^2}{12x} = \frac{1}{12}x(15 - 3x^2) = \frac{15}{12}x - \frac{1}{4}x^3
        </me>.
        Note particularly that in order to have a box,
        we require that both <m>x \gt 0</m> and <m>h \gt 0</m>.
        The latter condition along with the fact that
        <m>h = \frac{15-3x^2}{12x}</m> shows that we need <m>15 - 3x^2 \gt 0</m>,
        and thus <m>x^2 \lt 5</m>, so <m>x \lt \sqrt{5}</m>.
        Hence we are considering <m>V(x)</m> on the domain <m>0 \lt x \lt \sqrt{5}</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="lYz">
        It is apparent that the box vanishes
        (and its volume tends to zero)
        as either <m>x \to 0^+</m> or <m>x \to \sqrt{5}^-</m>,
        and thus the absolute maximum volume must appear between these values at a critical number.
        Differentiating <m>V</m>,
        we find that <m>V'(x) = \frac{15}{12} - \frac{3}{4}x^2</m>.
        Solving <m>V'(x) = 0</m> to find all critical numbers of <m>V</m> in the domain,
        we see that <m>x^2 = \frac{15}{12} \cdot \frac{4}{3} = \frac{5}{3}</m>,
        and thus <m>x = \pm \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}}</m>,
        so only <m>x = \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}}</m> is a critical number that lies in <m>0 \lt x \lt \sqrt{5}</m>.
        Noting that the absolute minimum volume <m>V = 0</m> occurs at each endpoint,
        it must be the case that the absolute maximum volume is <m>V\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right) = \frac{15}{12}\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right) - \frac{1}{4}\left( \sqrt{\frac{5}{3}} \right)^3 \approx 1.07583</m> cubic feet.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="kjm">
  <title>Maximizing pasture area with limited fencing</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="kTg">
        A farmer wants to start raising cows, horses, goats, and sheep,
        and desires to have a rectangular pasture for the animals to graze in.
        However, no two different kinds of animals can graze together.
        In order to minimize the amount of fencing she will need,
        she has decided to enclose a large rectangular area and then divide it into four equally sized pens by adding three segments of fence inside the large rectangle that are parallel to two existing sides.
        She has decided to purchase 7500 ft of fencing.
        What is the maximum possible area that each of the four pens will enclose?
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="Vao">
      <p permid="Mqw">
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="oTf">
      <p permid="SfI">
        The farmer will fence a rectangular area whose length <m>x</m> and width <m>y</m> are unknown.
        The total area of the rectangular area is composed of 4 equal area rectangles.
        There are two ways to do this as shown in the figure below.
      </p>

      <sidebyside permid="ndS">
        <image source="images/3_4_Ez2Soln" />
      </sidebyside>

      <p permid="ymR">
        We want to maximize the area of each subrectangular region,
        which is the same as maximizing the total area 
        <m>A = xy</m> of the entire rectangular region.
        Since <m>A</m> has two variables,
        we can't yet directly apply calculus techniques to it.
        We use the information about the amount of fencing to relate <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> in order to write <m>A</m> in terms of just one variable.
      </p>

      <p permid="eua">
        In the case of the fencing option on the left in the figure,
        the total amount of fencing that is needed to enclose the four grazing areas is <m>2x+5y</m>.
        We assume that all of the <m>7500</m> feet of fencing will be used,
        so <m>2x+5y=7500</m>.
        Solving for <m>x</m>, <m>x = 3750 - 2.5y</m>.
        Substituting this expression for <m>x</m> into the area formula allows us to write <m>A</m> in terms of <m>y</m> alone:
        <me permid="BRr">
          A(y) = (3750-2.5y)y = 3750y - 2.5y^2
        </me>.
        To enclose any area,
        we of course must have <m>y \gt 0</m> and <m>x \gt 0</m>,
        and since <m>x = 3750 - 2.5y</m>,
        it follows that we need to have
        <m>2.5y \lt 3750</m> so <m>y \lt 1500</m>.
        To find the maximum value of <m>A</m> on this domain,
        we find the critical numbers of <m>A</m>.
        Since <m>A'(y) = 3750 - 5y</m>,
        we see that <m>A'(y) = 0</m> when and only when <m>y = 750</m>.
        For <m>0 \lt y \lt 750</m>,
        we see that <m>A'(y) \gt 0</m> and for
        <m>750 \lt y \lt 1500</m> we have <m>A'(y) \lt 0</m>.
        So <m>A(750) = 1406250</m> square feet is the absolute maximum value of <m>A</m>.
        The maximum possible area that each of the four pens can enclose is one quarter of the total,
        or <m>351562.5</m> square feet.
      </p>

      <p permid="KBj">
        In the case of the fencing option on the right in the figure,
        the total amount of fencing that is needed to enclose the four grazing areas is <m>3x+3y</m>.
        We assume that all of the <m>7500</m> feet of fencing will be used,
        so <m>3x + 3y = 7500</m>.
        Solving for <m>x</m> and substituting into <m>A</m>,
        we find <m>x = 2500 - y</m> and
        <me permid="hYA">
          A(y) = (2500-y)y = 2500y - y^2
        </me>.
        To enclose any area,
        we of course must have <m>y \gt 0</m> and <m>x \gt 0</m>,
        and since <m>x = 2500 - y</m>,
        it follows that we need to have <m>y \lt 2500</m>.
        To find the maximum value of <m>A</m> on this domain,
        we find the critical numbers of <m>A</m>.
        Since <m>A'(y) = 2500 - 2y</m>,
        we see that <m>A'(y) = 0</m> when and only when <m>y = 1250</m>.
        For <m>0 \lt y \lt 1250</m>,
        we see that <m>A'(y) \gt 0</m> and for
        <m>1250 \lt y \lt 2500</m> we have <m>A'(y) \lt 0</m>.
        So <m>A(1250) = 1406250</m> square feet is the absolute maximum value of <m>A</m>.
        The maximum possible area that each of the four pens can enclose is one quarter of the total,
        or <m>390625</m> square feet.
      </p>

      <p permid="qIs">
        So the maximum possible area that each of the four pens can enclose is 390625 square feet.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="Qqv">
  <title>Minimizing cable length</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="Rap">
        Two vertical poles of heights 60 ft and 80 ft stand on level ground,
        with their bases 100 ft apart.
        A cable that is stretched from the top of one pole to some point on the ground between the poles,
        and then to the top of the other pole.
        What is the minimum possible length of cable required?
        Justify your answer completely using calculus.
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="hoG">
      <p permid="sxF">
        <m>172.047</m> feet of cable.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="Bhx">
      <p permid="WPB">
        We start by constructing a careful diagram of the overall situation.
        Let <m>x</m> be the distance from the first pole to the second pole where the cable touches the ground,
        and let <m>y</m> be the length of the cable from the top of the first tower to the ground,
        and <m>z</m> the length of cable from the ground to the top of the second tower,
        as pictured in the following figure.
        Note that we have included the given heights of the towers and the distance between them.
      </p>

      <sidebyside width="65%" permid="Tlb">
        <image source="images/3_4_Ez3Soln" />
      </sidebyside>

      <p permid="CWK">
        The total amount of cable, <m>L</m>, used
        (which we wish to minimize)
        is given by <m>L = y + z</m>.
        We can use the geometry of the situation to write both <m>y</m> and <m>z</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.
        In the first right triangle,
        by the Pythagorean Theorem we know that <m>x^2 + 60^2 = y^2</m>,
        and thus <m>y = \sqrt{x^2 + 3600}</m>.
        In the second right triangle,
        note that the horizontal leg of the triangle has length <m>100-x</m>,
        and thus <m>(100-x)^2 + 80^2 = z^2</m>,
        so <m>z = \sqrt{(100-x)^2 + 6400}</m>.
        It follows that with <m>L = y + z</m>,
        <me permid="OfJ">
          L(x) = \sqrt{x^2 + 3600} + \sqrt{6400 + (100-x)^2}
        </me>.
        It is also apparent from the given situation that the relevant domain for <m>L</m> is <m>0 \le x \le 100</m>.
        Given that we want to minimize <m>L</m> on this closed interval,
        it remains to find any critical numbers of <m>L</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="jdT">
        We note by the chain rule that
        <me permid="umS">
          L'(x) = \frac{2x}{2(x^2+3600)^{1/2}} + \frac{-2(100-x)}{2((100-x)^2 + 6400)^{1/2}}
        </me>
        We use technology to solve the equation
        <m>L'(x) = 0</m> and find that it has a single solution in the interval <m>0 \le x \le 100</m>:
        <m>x \approx 42.85714</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="Plc">
        To find the absolute minimum of <m>L</m> on the relevant domain,
        we evaluate <m>L</m> at the endpoints and the only critical number.
        Doing so, we fine <m>L(0) \approx 188.062</m>,
        <m>L(100) \approx 196.619</m>,
        and <m>L(42.85714) \approx 172.047</m>.
        Hence the least amount of cable we can use is approximately <m>172.047</m> feet and is accomplished by anchoring the cable about
        <m>42.85714</m> feet from the first tower.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="wxE">
  <title>Minimizing construction costs</title>
    <statement>
      <p permid="xhy">
        A company is designing propane tanks that are cylindrical with hemispherical ends.
        Assume that the company wants tanks that will hold 1000 cubic feet of gas,
        and that the ends are more expensive to make,
        costing <dollar />5 per square foot,
        while the cylindrical barrel between the ends costs <dollar />2 per square foot.
        Use calculus to determine the minimum cost to construct such a tank.
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="tCY">
      <p permid="YEO">
        The minimum cost is <dollar />1165.70.
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="NvP">
      <p permid="vsl">
        We let the length of the cylindrical part of the tank be <m>h</m> with the radius of the cylinder given by <m>r</m>.
        It follows that the radius of the hemispherical ends of the tank is also <m>r</m>.
        We first identify formulas for both the volume and surface area of the tank by looking at the cylindrical and hemispherical pieces.
      </p>

      <p permid="bzu">
        The cylindrical part of the tank has volume <m>V_c = \pi r^2 h</m>,
        and the surface area of its sides is <m>A_c = 2\pi r h</m>
        (which is the circumference of the cylinder's base times the cylinder's height -- think about how a cylinder unfurls to form a rectangle).
        The two hemispherical ends together constitute a full sphere,
        and the volume of a sphere is <m>V_s = \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m>,
        while the surface area of a sphere is <m>A_s = 4 \pi r^2</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="HGD">
        The overall volume of the tank is therefore
        <me permid="aub">
          V = V_c + V_s = \pi r^2 h + \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3
        </me>,
        and its total surface area is
        <me permid="GBk">
          A = A_c + A_s = 2\pi r h + 4 \pi r^2
        </me>.
        Moreover, taking into account the different costs of material for the cylindrical sides and hemispherical ends,
        we find that the total cost of the tank is
        <me permid="mIt">
          C = 2(2\pi r h) + 5(4 \pi r^2) = 4 \pi r h + 20 \pi r^2
        </me>.
      </p>

      <p permid="nNM">
        Our goal is to minimize the total cost of the tank given that we want it to hold 1000 cubic meters of volume.
        From this constraint,
        we have the equation <m>1000 = \pi r^2 h + \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m>,
        which we can solve for <m>h</m> to get <m>\pi r^2 h = 1000 - \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m>, so
        <me permid="SPC">
          h = \frac{1000 - \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3}{\pi r^2}
        </me>.
        This allows us to now write cost as a function of the single variable <m>r</m> by substituting the expression for <m>h</m> into the earlier formula we found for cost.
        In particular,
        <me permid="yWL">
          C(r) = 4 \pi r \frac{1000 - \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3}{\pi r^2} + 20 \pi r^2 = 4 \frac{1000 - \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3}{r} + 20\pi r^2
        </me>
        Simplifying further, we have found that
        <me permid="fdU">
          C(r) = \frac{4000}{r} - \frac{16}{3}\pi r^2 + 20 \pi r^2 = \frac{4000}{r} + \frac{44}{3}r^2
        </me>.
        Based on the physical constraints of the problem,
        we obviously will only consider values of <m>r \gt 0</m> and <m>h \gt 0</m>.
        Since <m>h = \frac{1000 - \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3}{\pi r^2}</m>,
        we must have
        <me permid="Lld">
          \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3 \lt 1000
        </me>
        so <m>r^3 \lt \frac{3}{4} \cdot 1000 = 750</m>,
        and thus <m>r \lt \sqrt[3]{750} \approx 9.086</m>.
        We now work to minimize <m>C(r)</m> on the interval <m>0 \lt r \lt \sqrt[3]{750}</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="TUV">
        Taking the derivative of <m>C</m>,
        we find that <m>C'(r) = -\frac{4000}{r^2} + \frac{88}{3}r</m>.
        Setting <m>C'(r) = 0</m>, it follows that
        <me permid="rsm">
          \frac{4000}{r^2} = \frac{88}{3}r
        </me>
        and thus
        <me permid="Xzv">
          4000 \cdot \frac{3}{88} = r^3
        </me>.
        Therefore, <m>r^3 = \frac{1500}{11}</m>,
        so <m>r = \sqrt[3]{\frac{1500}{11}} \approx 5.147</m> is the only critical number of <m>C</m>;
        observe that it lies within the interval <m>0 \lt r \lt \sqrt[3]{750}</m>.
      </p>

      <p permid="Ace">
        If we plot the derivative function, <m>y = C'(r)</m>,
        on the interval <m>0 \lt r \lt \sqrt[3]{750}</m>,
        we see that for <m>0 \lt r \lt 5.147</m>,
        <m>C'(r) \lt 0</m>,
        and for <m>5.147 \lt r \lt 9.086</m>, <m>C'(r) \gt 0</m>,
        which shows that <m>C</m> is decreasing before the critical number and increasing after the critical number,
        and hence <m>C</m> has a global minimum of <m>C(\sqrt[3]{\frac{1500}{11}}) \approx 1165.70</m>,
        so <dollar />1165.70 is the minimum cost to build the desired tank under the given constraints.
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

 </exercises>
</section>

