<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="explog"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction to Continuity</title>
<objectives permid="xFB">
    <ul permid="JTT">

      <li permid="ODM">
        <p permid="wAi">
          What does it mean to say that a function <m>f</m> is continuous at <m>x = a</m>?
        </p>
      </li>
      
          <li permid="ODM">
        <p permid="wAi">
          What does it mean to say that a function <m>f</m> is continuous everywhere?
        </p>
      </li>

    </ul>
  </objectives>


<introduction>
<p>In this section we introduce the idea of a continuous function.  
Many of the results in calculus require that the functions be continuous so having a strong understanding of continuous functions will be very important. 
</p>
</introduction>

<subsection permid="gHq">
    <title>Being continuous at a point</title>
    <idx><h>continuous</h></idx>
    <p permid="AeI">
      Intuitively,
      a function is continuous if we can draw its graph without ever lifting our pencil from the page.
      Alternatively,
      we might say that the graph of a continuous function has no jumps or holes in it.
    </p>
    
        <figure xml:id="F-1-7-Cont" permid="kVK">
      <caption>Functions <m>f</m>, <m>g</m>, and <m>h</m> that demonstrate subtly different behaviors at <m>a = 1</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_7_Cont" />
    </figure>
    
    
        <p permid="glR">
      First consider the function in the left-most graph.
      Note that <m>f(1)</m> is not defined,
      which leads to the resulting hole in the graph of <m>f</m> at <m>a = 1</m>.
      If you were to draw the graph of <m>f</m> yourself then you would need to lift your pencil when you reached <m>f(1)</m>.
      We will naturally say that <m>f</m> is
      <em>not continuous at <m>a = 1</m></em>.
      For the function <m>g</m>,
      we observe that while <m>g(1)</m> is defined,
      the value of <m>g(1) = 2</m> is not what you would "expect."  Specifically, you would expect <m>g(1)</m> to be 3, not 2.
      Thus, to draw the graph of <m>g</m> you would need to lift you pencil at <m>a=1</m>.
      Again, we will say that <m>g</m> is
      <em>not continuous</em> at <m>a=1</m>,
      even though the function is defined at <m>a = 1</m>.
      Finally, the function <m>h</m> appears to be the most "well-behaved" of all three,
      since at <m>a = 1</m> its limit and its function value agree.  In this case we would say that <m>h</m> is continuous at <m>a=1</m>.
    </p>

<p>The above examples demonstrate a discontinuity commonly know as a <em>removable discontinuity</em>. 
 This is, however, not the only way in which a function can be discontinuous.  Another type of discontinuity is the so called <em>jump</em> discontinuity.  
</p>    

        <figure>
      <caption>Places where functions make a "jump" also produce discontinuities.</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/piecewise.pdf" />
    </figure>
<p>A third type of discontunity is the so called <em>infinite</em> discontinuity.  Infinite discontinuities exist when the points values of a function diverge to infinity.  A classic example of an infinite discontinuity is the point <m>x=0</m> for the function <m>f(x)=1/x</m>.
</p>
        <figure>
      <caption>A plot of the function <m>y=f(x)</m> for the function <m>f(x)=1/x</m>.</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/1overx.png" />
    </figure>
<example>
<statement>
    <p>
Consider the function <me>f(x)=\frac{3x(x+4)}{x^2-16}</me>.  Are there <m>x</m>-values where the function is discontinuous?  If so, what are those <m>x</m>-values and why type of discontinuity occurs at that value?
    </p>

  </statement>
  <hint>
  <p>Consider the graph of <m>y=f(x)</m>.</p>
          <figure>
      <caption>A plot of the function <m>y=f(x)</m>.</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/0-4-rational.pdf" />
    </figure>
   
  </hint>
  <solution>
  <p>We can expand the numerator and denominator of the function.  Specifically,
  <me>
  f(x)=\frac{3x(x+4)}{x^2-16}=\frac{3x(x+4)}{(x+4)(x-4)}.
  </me>
  From here we see that there are two <m>x</m>-values at which the function is undefined, <m>x=-4,4</m>.  
  Since the term <m>x+4</m> occurs in the numerator and denominator <m>x=-4</m> is a removable discontinuity.  
  Since the term <m>x-4</m> occurs only in the denominator, <m>x=4</m> is an infinite discontinuity.</p>
  <note>
  <p>
  Rational functions can be a challenging topic. 
  For a more complete discussion of rational functions we refer the reader to <url href="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/Graphing-Rational-Functions.html">Short-Run Behavior of Rational Functions</url>
  </p>
  </note>
  </solution>
  
</example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Exercises</title>
    <exercise>
    <title>Period and Amplitude</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec5/Q17.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      
      

</subsection>  
  
  </section>


<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
