<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="introfunctions"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Functions</title>
<subsection><title>The Definition of Function</title>



<p>
    We often want to predict values of one variable from the values of a related variable. For a more extensive treatment of functions we refer the reader to <url href="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/introfunctions.html">PreCalculus at Nebraska: Introduction to Functions</url></p>

<assemblage>
    <title>Definition of Function</title>
    <p>A <term>function</term><idx>function</idx> is a relationship between two variables for which a unique value of the <term>output</term><idx>output</idx> variable can be determined from a value of the <term>input</term><idx>input</idx> variable.
    </p>
</assemblage>

<p>
    What distinguishes functions from other variable relationships? The definition of a function calls for a <em>unique value</em>— that is, <em>exactly one value</em> of the output variable corresponding to each value of the input variable. This property makes functions useful in applications because they can often be used to make predictions.
</p>



<p>A function can be described in several different ways. In the following examples, we consider functions defined by tables, by graphs, and by equations.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Functions Defined by Tables</title>
    <p>When we use a table to describe a function, the first variable in the table (the left column of a vertical table or the top row of a horizontal table) is the input variable, and the second variable is the output. We say that the output variable <em>is a function of</em> the input.</p>

    <example xml:id="example-table-functions"><statement><p>
        <ol label="a">
        <li><p><xref ref="table-auto-sales" text="type-global" /> shows data on sales compiled over several years by the accounting office for Eau Claire Auto Parts, a division of Major Motors. In this example, the year is the input variable, and total sales is the output. We say that total sales, <m>S</m>, <em>is a function of</em> <m>t</m>.</p>
        <table xml:id="table-auto-sales"><caption></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Year <m>(t)</m></cell>
            <cell>Total sales <m>(S)</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>2000</cell>
            <cell><dollar />612,000</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>2001</cell>
            <cell><dollar />663,000</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>2002</cell>
            <cell><dollar />692,000</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>2003</cell>
            <cell><dollar />749,000</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>2004</cell>
            <cell><dollar />904,000</cell>
        </row>
        </tabular></table>
        </li>
        <li><p><xref ref="table-postage" text="type-global" /> gives the cost of sending printed material by first-class mail in 2016. </p>
        <table xml:id="table-postage"><caption></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Weight in ounces <m>(w)</m></cell>
            <cell>Postage <m>(P)</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>0 \lt w \le 1 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />0.47</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>1 \lt w \le 2 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />0.68</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>2 \lt w \le 3 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />0.89</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>3 \lt w \le 4 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />1.10</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>4 \lt w \le 5 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />1.31</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>5 \lt w \le 6 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />1.52</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>6 \lt w \le 7 </m></cell>
            <cell><dollar />1.73</cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></table>

        <p>If we know the weight of the article being shipped, we can determine the required postage from <xref ref="table-postage" text="type-global" />. For instance, a catalog weighing 4.5 ounces would require <dollar />1.31 in postage. In this example, <m>w</m> is the input variable and <m>p</m> is the output variable. We say that <m>p</m> <em>is a function of</em> <m>w</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p><xref ref="table-cholesterol" text="type-global" /> records the age and cholesterol count for 20 patients tested in a hospital survey.</p>
        <table xml:id="table-cholesterol"><caption></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Age</cell>
            <cell>Cholesterol count</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>Age</cell>
            <cell>Cholesterol count</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>53</cell>
            <cell>217</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell><m>\alert{51}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\alert{209}</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>48</cell>
            <cell>232</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>53</cell>
            <cell>241</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>55</cell>
            <cell>198</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>186</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>56</cell>
            <cell>238</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell><m>\alert{51}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\alert{216}</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell><m>\alert{51}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\alert{227}</m></cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>57</cell>
            <cell>208</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>52</cell>
            <cell>264</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>52</cell>
            <cell>248</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>53</cell>
            <cell>195</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>50</cell>
            <cell>214</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>47</cell>
            <cell>203</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>56</cell>
            <cell>271</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>48</cell>
            <cell>212</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>53</cell>
            <cell>193</cell>
        </row>
        <row> 
            <cell>50</cell>
            <cell>234</cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell>48</cell>
            <cell>172</cell>
        </row>

    </tabular></table>

        <p>According to these data, cholesterol count is <em>not</em> a function of age, because several patients who are the same age have different cholesterol levels. For example, three different patients are 51 years old but have cholesterol counts of 227, 209, and 216, respectively. Thus, we cannot determine a <em>unique</em> value of the output variable (cholesterol count) from the value of the input variable (age). Other factors besides age must influence a person’s cholesterol count.</p></li>

    </ol></p></statement>
    </example>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Functions Defined by Graphs</title>
<p>
    A graph may also be used to define one variable as a function of another. The input variable is displayed on the horizontal axis, and the output variable on the vertical axis.
</p>    

<example xml:id="example-sun-hours"><statement>
    <p><xref ref="fig-sun-hours" text="type-global"/>  shows the number of hours, <m>H</m>, that the sun is above the horizon in Peoria, Illinois, on day <m>t</m>, where January 1 corresponds to <m>t = 0</m>.</p>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%">
        
        <paragraphs><p>
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Which variable is the input, and which is the output?</p></li>
            <li><p>Approximately how many hours of sunlight are there in Peoria on day 150?</p></li>
            <li><p>On which days are there 12 hours of sunlight?</p></li>
            <li><p>What are the maximum and minimum values of <m>H</m>, and when do these values occur?</p></li>
        </ol></p></paragraphs>
        <figure xml:id="fig-sun-hours"><caption></caption><image source="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/images/fig-sun-hours.pdf" width="90%"><description>Peoria sunlight hours</description></image></figure>
    </sidebyside></statement>
    <solution><p>
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>The input variable, <m>t</m>, appears on the horizontal axis. The number of daylight hours, <m>H</m>, is a function of the date. The output variable appears on the vertical axis.</p></li>
            <li><p>The point on the curve where <m>t = 150</m> has <m>H \approx 14.1</m>, so Peoria gets about 14.1 hours of daylight when <m>t = 150</m>, which is at the end of May.</p></li>
            <li><p><m>H = 12</m> at the two points where <m>t \approx 85</m> (in late March) and <m>t \approx 270</m> (late September).</p></li>
            <li><p>The maximum value of 14.4 hours occurs on the longest day of the year, when <m>t \approx 170</m>, about three weeks into June. The minimum of 9.6 hours occurs on the shortest day, when <m>t \approx 355</m>, about three weeks into December.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </solution>
</example>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Functions Defined by Equations</title>
<p><xref ref="example-falling-book" text="type-global"/> illustrates a function defined by an equation.</p>
<example xml:id="example-falling-book">
    <p>As of 2016,  One World Trade Center in New York City is the nation’s tallest building, at 1776 feet. If an algebra book is dropped from the top of One World Trade Center, its height above the ground after <m>t</m> seconds is given by the equation <me>h = 1776 - 16t^2</me> Thus, after <m>\alert{1}</m> second the book’s height is <me>h = 1776 - 16(\alert{1})^2 = 1760 \text{ feet}</me> After <m>\alert{2}</m> seconds its height is <me>h = 1776 - 16(\alert{2})^2 = 1712 \text{ feet}</me> For this function, <m>t</m> is the input variable and <m>h</m> is the output variable. For any value of <m>t</m>, a unique value of <m>h</m> can be determined from the equation for <m>h</m>. We say that <m>h</m> <em>is a function of</em> <m>t</m>.</p>
 </example>  


</subsection>



<subsection><title>Function Notation</title>
    <p>There is a convenient notation for discussing functions. First, we choose a letter, such as <m>f</m>, <m>g</m>, or <m>h</m> (or <m>F</m>, <m>G</m>, or <m>H</m>), to name a particular function. (We can use any letter, but these are
        the most common choices.) For instance, the height, <m>h</m>, of a falling textbook is a function of the elapsed time, <m>t</m>. We might call this function <m>f</m>. In other words, <m>f</m> is the name of the relationship between the variables <m>h</m> and <m>t</m>. We write
        <me>h = f (t)</me>
        which means "<m>h</m> is a function of <m>t</m>, and <m>f</m> is the name of the function."</p>
    
    
    <p>Remember that when we write <m>y = f(x)</m>, the symbol <m>f(x)</m> is just another name for the output variable.</p>
    

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Evaluating a Function</title>
    <p>
        Finding the value of the output variable that corresponds to a particular value of the input variable is called <term>evaluating the function</term><idx>evaluating the function</idx>.
    </p>
    

    <p>If a function is described by an equation, we simply substitute the given input value into the equation to find the corresponding output, or function value.</p>

    
    <p>
        To simplify the notation, we sometimes use the same letter for the output variable and
        for the name of the function. 
    </p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Linear Functions</title>   

<p>
Linear relationships are relationships in which the rate of change is constant.

    <assemblage><title>Linear Equation</title>
    <p>
        A <term>linear function</term> is a function which has a <term>constant rate of change.</term>
    </p>
</assemblage>


    Many phenomena can be modeled using linear functions <m>y = f (x)</m> where the equations have the form
    <me>f (x) = (\text{starting value}) + (\text{rate of change}) \cdot x.</me>
    The initial value, or the value of <m>f(0)</m>, is the vertical intercept of the graph, and the rate of change is the slope of the graph. 
    
    Thus, we can write an equation of a line as
    <me>f (x) = b + mx</me>
    where the constant term, <m>b</m>, is the vertical intercept of the line, and <m>m</m>, the coefficient of <m>x</m>, is the slope of the line. This form for an equation of a line is called the <term>slope-intercept form</term><idx>slope-intercept form</idx>.
</p>

<assemblage><title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>
    <p>
        If we write an equation of a linear function in the form,
        <me>f (x) = b + mx</me>
        then <m>m</m> is the <term>slope</term><idx>slope</idx> of the line, and <m>b</m> is the <term>vertical intercept</term>.
    </p>
</assemblage>

<p>
Is is also useful to introduce the term <m>x</m>-intercept at this point.
    <assemblage><title><m>x</m>-intercept</title>
    <p>
        An <term><m>x</m>-intercept</term> for a function <m>f(x)</m> is the value of <m>x</m> such that <m>f(x)=0</m>.
    </p>
</assemblage>
</p>



<note><p>
    In the equation <m>f (x) = b + mx</m>, we call <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> <term>parameters</term><idx>parameters</idx>. Their values are fixed for any particular linear equation; for example, in the equation <m>y = 2x + 3</m>, <m>m = 2</m> and <m>b = 3</m>, and the variables are <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>. By changing the values of <m>m</m> and <m>b</m>, we can write the equation for any line except a vertical line (see <xref ref="fig-slope-vs-intercept" text="type-global"/>). The collection of all linear functions <m>f (x) = b + mx</m> is called a <term>two-parameter</term><idx>two-parameter</idx> family of functions.
</p></note>
<figure xml:id="fig-slope-vs-intercept"><caption></caption><image source="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/images/fig-slope-vs-intercept.pdf"   width="80%"><description>lines with common intercept or common slope</description></image></figure>
</subsection>



<subsection><title>Describing Functions</title>
<p>There are several terms that will be useful in describing functions.  We first begin with the notion of an increasing function.</p>

<assemblage><title>Increasing Function</title><p>A function $f$ is increasing if the values of $f(x)$ increase as $x$ increases.

The graph of an increasing function climbs as we move from left to right.</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Decreasing Function</title>
<p>A function <m>f</m> is decreasing if the values of <m>f(x)</m> decrease as <m>x</m> increases.

The graph of a decreasing function falls as we move from left to right.</p>

</assemblage>
<p>
<em>A function <m>f(x)</m> is monotonic if it increases for all <m>x</m> or decreases for all <m>x</m>. 
</em>
</p>

<assemblage><title>Directly Proportional</title> <p>We say <m>y</m> is directly proportional to <m>x</m> if there is a nonzero constant <m>k</m> such that, <m>y = kx</m>. This <m>k</m> is called the constant of proportionality.
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Inversely Proportional</title> <p>We say that <m>y</m> is inversely proportional to <m>x</m> if <m>y</m> is proportional to the reciprocal of <m>x</m>, that is, <m>y = k/x</m> for a nonzero constant <m>k</m>.
</p>

</assemblage>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Function Transformations</title>
<p>It is also useful to talk about transformations of functions.  Several key facts will be useful.</p>

<assemblage><title>Function Transformations</title> <p>
<ol>
<li> Multiplying a function by a constant, <m>c</m>, stretches the graph vertically (if <m>c <greater> 1</m>) or shrinks the graph vertically (if <m>0 <less> c <less> 1</m>)</li>
<li> A negative sign (if <m>c <less> 0</m>) reflects the graph about the <m>x</m>-axis, in addition to shrinking or stretching.</li>
<li> Replacing <m>y</m> by <m>(y+k)</m> moves a graph up by <m>k</m> (down if <m>k</m> is negative).</li>
<li> Replacing <m>x</m> by <m>(x-h)</m> moves a graph to the right by <m>h</m> (to the left if <m>h</m> is negative).</li>
</ol>

</p>
</assemblage>

</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Inverse Functions</title>

    <p> It is also useful to consider inverse functions.
        </p>
    
        <assemblage><title>Inverse Functions</title><idx>inverse functions</idx>
         <p>       Suppose the inverse of <m>f</m> is a function, denoted by <m>f^{-1}</m>. Then
                <me>f^{-1}(y) = x \text{ if and only if }f(x) = y.</me>
         </p>
        </assemblage>
        
<assemblage>
    <title>Functions and Inverse Functions</title>
    <p>
        Suppose <m>f^{-1}</m> is the inverse function for <m>f</m>. Then
        <me>f^{-1}\left(f(x)\right) = x\text{ and }f\left(f^{-1}( y)\right) = y</me>
        as long as <m>x</m> is in the domain of <m>f</m>, and <m>y</m> is in the domain of <m>f^{-1}</m>.
    </p>
</assemblage>

<p>
We also have a method of quickly determining if a function is invertible once we have a graph of the function.
</p>

<assemblage><title>Horizontal Line Test</title><idx>horizontal line test</idx>
	<p>
		If no horizontal line intersects the graph of a function more than once, then its inverse is also a function.
	</p>
</assemblage>

<p>
    We have been talking about how to tell if the inverse of a function is also a function, but in practice this is not the language typicaly used. Usually we ask this same question in the form "Is the function invertible?" The following definition explains this relationship:
    
    <assemblage><title>Invertible Function</title><idx>Invertible Function</idx>
        <p>
            If <m> y=f(x) </m> is a function such that its inverse, <m> x=f^{-1}(y)</m>, is also a function then we say that <m> f(x) </m> is an <term> invertible function </term>.
        </p>
    </assemblage>
    
    </p>
    
    
    
    <p>
	The inverse function <m>f^{-1}</m> undoes the effect of the function <m>f</m>. The function <m>f(t) = 6 + 2t</m> multiplies the input by <m>2</m> and then adds <m>6</m> to the result. The inverse function <m>f^{-1}(H) = \dfrac{H -6}{2}</m> undoes those operations in reverse order: It subtracts <m>6</m> from the input and then divides the result by <m>2</m>.</p>

	<p> If we apply the function <m>f</m> to a given input value and then apply the function <m>f^{-1}</m> to the output from <m>f</m>, the end result will be the original input value. For example, if we choose <m>t = 5</m> as an input value, we find that
	\begin{align*}
	f(\alert{5})\amp= 6 + 2(\alert{5}) 
	= \blert{16}\amp\amp\text{ Multiply by 2, then add 6.}\\
	\text{and } f^{-1}(\blert{16}) \amp = \frac{\blert{16} - 6}{2}
	= \alert{5}.\amp\amp\text{Subtract 6, then divide by 2.}
	\end{align*}</p>
	<figure xml:id="fig-function-and-inverse-diagram"><caption></caption><image source="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/images/fig-function-and-inverse-diagram.pdf"  width="50%"><description>function and inverse diagram</description></image></figure>
	<p>We return to the original input value, <m>5</m>, as illustrated in <xref ref="fig-function-and-inverse-diagram" text="type-global"/>.
</p>
<p>
	<xref ref="example-inverse-of-inverse" text="type-global"/> illustrates the fact that if <m>f^{-1}</m> is the inverse function for <m>f</m>, then <m>f</m> is also the inverse function for <m>f^{-1}</m>.
</p>



</subsection>


<subsection><title>Exercises</title>
  <exercise>
    <title>Slope and Intercept</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec1/Q09.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
    <title>Graphs of Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec1/Q11.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Proportionality</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec1/Q24.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
  <exercise>
    <title>Finding Lines</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec1/Q04.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
  <exercise>
    <title>Transformations</title>
    <webwork source="local/Functions/Transformations/VertHoriz_Seperate.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
    <title>Matching Transformations</title>
    <webwork source="local/Library/LoyolaChicago/Precalc/Chap5Sec1/Q08.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
  
</subsection>  
  
  </section>


<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
