<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- UNL Department of Mathematics                                         -->
<!-- Based upon the work of                                                -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Coordinated Calculus.                            -->
<!-- This file is based on Active Calculus.                                -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-5-units" permid="IVE">
  <title>Interpreting, estimating, and using the derivative</title>
  <objectives permid="NFx">
    <ul permid="mih">
      <li permid="ywz">
        <p permid="PuK">
          In contexts other than the position of a moving object,
          what does the derivative of a function measure?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="eDI">
        <p permid="vBT">
          What are the units on the derivative function <m>f'</m>,
          and how are they related to the units of the original function <m>f</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="KKR">
        <p permid="bJc">
          What is a central difference,
          and how can one be used to estimate the value of the derivative at a point from given function data?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="qSa">
        <p permid="HQl">
          Given the value of the derivative of a function at a point,
          what can we infer about how the value of the function changes nearby?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="tMG">
    <p permid="lcO">
      A powerful feature of mathematics is that it can be studied both as an abstract discipline and as an applied one.
      For instance,
      calculus can be developed almost entirely as an abstract collection of ideas that focus on properties of functions.
      At the same time,
      if we consider functions that represent meaningful processes,
      calculus can describe our experience of physical reality.
      We have already seen that for the position function
      <m>y = s(t)</m> of a ball being tossed straight up in the air,
      the derivative of the position function,
      <m>v(t) = s'(t)</m>, gives the ball's velocity at time <m>t</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="RjX">
      In this section,
      we investigate several functions with specific physical meaning,
      and consider how the units on the independent variable,
      dependent variable,
      and the derivative function add to our understanding.
      To start, we consider the familiar problem of a position function of a moving object.
    </p>

<example xml:id="PA-1-5" permid="Qvm">
  <statement>
  <p permid="XZL">
    One of the longest stretches of straight
    (and flat)
    road in North America can be found on the Great Plains in the state of North Dakota on state highway 46,
    which lies just south of the interstate highway I-94 and runs through the town of Gackle.
    Suppose a car leaves town
    (at time <m>t = 0</m>)
    and heads east on highway 46;
    its position in miles from Gackle at time <m>t</m> in minutes is given by the graph of the function in <xref ref="F-1-5-PA1">Figure</xref> below.
    Three important points are labeled on the graph;
    where the curve looks linear, you may
    assume that it is indeed a straight line.
  </p>

  <figure xml:id="F-1-5-PA1" permid="kod">
    <caption>The graph of <m>y = s(t)</m>, the position of the car along highway 46, which gives distance (in miles) from Gackle, ND at time <m>t</m> (in minutes).</caption>
    <image width="47%" source="images/1_5_PA1" />
  </figure>

  <p permid="EgU">
    <ol label="a." permid="uNi">
      <li permid="aUr">
        <p permid="zxb">
          In everyday language,
          describe the behavior of the car over the provided time interval.
          In particular,
          discuss what is happening on the time intervals <m>[57,68]</m> and <m>[68,104]</m>.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="HbA">
        <p permid="fEk">
          Find the slope of the line between the points
          <m>(57,63.8)</m> and <m>(104,106.8)</m>.
          What are the units on this slope?
          What does the slope represent?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="niJ">
        <p permid="LLt">
          Find the average rate of change of the car's position on the interval <m>[68,104]</m>.
          Include units in your answer.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="TpS">
        <p permid="rSC">
          Estimate the instantaneous rate of change of the car's position at the moment <m>t = 80</m>.
          Write a sentence to explain your reasoning and the meaning of this value.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </p>
  </statement>
  <hint>
    <ol label="a.">
      <li>
      <p>
      When is the car moving? When is the car stopped? How do you know? (What features of the graph
      tell you this information?)
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      Units of slope should be <q>units of <m>s</m> per unit of <m>t</m></q>. 
      Think about what the slope of a secant line represents.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      Use the formula for average rate of change from <xref ref="aroc-def">Definition</xref>. <!-- <xref ref="sec-1-3-derivative-pt">Section</xref> -->
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      Close to the time <m>t=80</m> minutes, the function is linear. What does 
      this mean for the instantaneous rate of change of the car's position at this instant?
      </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </hint>
  <answer>
    <ol label="a.">
      <li>
      <p>
      The car drives away from Gackle at a constant speed for <m>57</m> minutes, stops for <m>11</m> minutes
      (on the interval <m>[57,68]</m>), and then resumes driving away from Gackle at a constant
      speed for another <m>36</m> minutes (on the interval <m>[68,104]</m>).
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      The slope between these points is <m>m=\frac{43}{57}\approx0.75</m> miles per minute.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      <m>AV_{[68,104]}=\frac{43}{36}\approx1.194</m> miles per minute.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      <m>s'(80)=\frac{43}{36}</m> miles per minute, the speed of the car after <m>80</m> minutes of driving.
      </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <ol label="a.">
      <li>
      <p>
      For the first <m>57</m> minutes, the car travels away from Gackle at a constant speed.
      Since it travels a total of <m>63.8</m> miles during this time, its velocity is 
      <m>\frac{63.8}{57}</m> miles per minute, or approximately <m>67.16</m> miles per hour. 
      The car is stopped between minutes <m>57</m> and <m>68</m>, and then resumes 
      driving away from Gackle, again at a constant speed.
      Between <m>68</m> and <m>104</m> minutes, the car travels <m>106.8-63.8=43</m> miles, 
      so its (average) velocity during this time is <m>\frac{43}{104-68}=\frac{43}{36}</m>
      miles per minute, or about <m>71.67</m> miles per hour.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      The slope of the line between the points <m>(57,63.8)</m> and <m>(104,106.8)</m>
      is <m>m=\frac{106.8-63.8}{104-57}=\frac{43}{57}\approx0.754</m> miles per minute.
      This value represents the average speed of the car between <m>57</m> and <m>104</m> minutes of 
      driving. Because the car is stopped for the first <m>11</m> minutes of this time interval, 
      the average speed on this interval is down to approximately <m>45</m> miles per hour.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      The average rate of change of the car's position on the interval <m>[68,104]</m>
      is <me>AV_{[68,104]}=\frac{106.8-63.8}{104-68}=\frac{43}{36}\approx1.194</me> miles per minute. 
      On this interval, the car travels at an average speed of <m>72</m> miles per hour.
      </p>
      </li>
      <li>
      <p>
      At <m>t=80</m> minutes, we are solidly in the middle of the time interval <m>[68,104]</m>, 
      over which the car appears to be traveling at a constant velocity of about <m>72</m> miles per hour. 
      A constant velocity (and in general, a linear position function) on an interval means the 
      instantaneous velocity of the car at a point on that interval is the same as the average 
      velocity of the car over that interval. 
      Therefore, the instantaneous rate of change of the car's position at the moment <m>t=80</m>
      minutes is about <m>72</m> miles per hour, or <m>1.2</m> miles per minute. 
      </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </solution>
</example>
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="pcN">
    <title>Units of the derivative function</title>
    <p permid="xrg">
      As we now know,
      the derivative of the function <m>f</m> at a fixed value <m>x</m> is given by
      <me permid="zgt">
        f'(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}
      </me>,
      and this value has several different interpretations.
      If we set <m>x = a</m>,
      one meaning of <m>f'(a)</m> is the slope of the tangent line at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="dyp">
      We also sometimes write <m>\frac{df}{dx}</m> or
      <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> instead of <m>f'(x)</m>,
      and these alternate notations help us see the units
      (and thus the meaning)
      of the derivative as
      <em>the instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m></em>.
          <idx><h>instantaneous rate of change</h></idx>
      The units on the slope of the secant line,
      <m>\frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}</m>,
      are <q>units of <m>y</m> per unit of <m>x</m>,</q> and
      when we take the limit as <m>h</m> goes to zero,
      the derivative <m>f'(x)</m> has the same units:
      units of <m>y</m> per unit of <m>x</m>.

      It is helpful to remember that the units on the derivative function are
      <q>units of output per unit of input,</q> for the variables
      of the original function.
    </p>

    <p permid="JFy">
      For example, suppose that the function <m>y = P(t)</m>
      measures the population of a city
      (in thousands)
      at the start of year <m>t</m>
      (where <m>t = 0</m> corresponds to 2010 AD).
      We are told that <m>P'(2) = 21.37</m>.
      What is the meaning of this value?
      Well, since <m>P</m> is measured in thousands and <m>t</m> is measured in years,
      we can say that the instantaneous rate of change of the city's population with respect to time at the start of 2012 is 21.37 thousand people per year.
      We therefore expect that in the coming year,
      about 21,370 people will be added to the city's population.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="VjW">
    <title>Toward more accurate derivative estimates</title>
    <p permid="pMH">
      Recall that to estimate the value of <m>f'(x)</m> at a given <m>x</m>,
      we calculate a <em>difference quotient</em>
          <idx><h>difference quotient</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}</m> with a relatively small value of <m>h</m>.
      We should use both positive and negative values of <m>h</m> in order to account for the behavior of the function on both sides of the point of interest.
      To that end, we introduce the notion of a
      <em>central difference</em>
      and its role in estimating derivatives.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-1-5-1" permid="hyo">
      <statement>
        <p permid="EVF">
          Suppose that <m>y = f(x)</m> is a function for which three values are known:
          <m>f(1) = 2.5</m>, <m>f(2) = 3.25</m>, and <m>f(3) = 3.625</m>.
          Estimate <m>f'(2)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <hint>
        <p>
          Try using a difference quotient with <m>h=\pm1</m>.
        </p>
      </hint>
      <answer>
        <p>
          <m>f'(2)\approx0.5625</m>
        </p>
      </answer>
      <solution permid="ZTP">
        <p permid="gsV">
          We know that <m>f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(2+h) - f(2)}{h}</m>.
          But since we don't have a graph or a formula for the function,
          we can neither sketch a tangent line nor evaluate the limit algebraically.
          We can't even use smaller and smaller values of <m>h</m> to estimate the limit.
          Instead, we have just two choices:
          using <m>h = -1</m> or <m>h = 1</m>,
          depending on which point we pair with <m>(2,3.25)</m>.
        </p>

        <p permid="MAe">
          So, one estimate is
          <me permid="fnC">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{f(1)-f(2)}{1-2} = \frac{2.5-3.25}{-1} = 0.75
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="sHn">
          The other is
          <me permid="LuL">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{f(3)-f(2)}{3-2} = \frac{3.625-3.25}{1} = 0.375
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="YOw">
          Because the first approximation looks backward from the point
          <m>(2,3.25)</m> and the second approximation looks forward,
          it makes sense to average these two estimates in order to account for behavior on both sides of <m>x=2</m>.
          Doing so, we find that
          <me permid="rBU">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{0.75 + 0.375}{2} = 0.5625
          </me>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p permid="VTQ">
      The intuitive approach to average the two estimates found in <xref ref="Ex-1-5-1">Example</xref>
      is in fact the best possible way to estimate a derivative when we have just two function values for <m>f</m> on opposite sides of the point of interest.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-5-Ex1" permid="GKS">
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>y = f(x)</m> along with the secant line through <m>(1,2.5)</m> and <m>(2,3.25)</m>, the secant line through <m>(2, 3.25)</m> and <m>(3,3.625)</m>, as well as the tangent line through <m>(2,3.25)</m>.  At right, the same graph of <m>y=f(x)</m> along with the secant line through <m>(1,2.5)</m> and <m>(3,3.625)</m>, plus the tangent line through <m>(2,3.25)</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_5_Ex1" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="CaZ">
      To see why,
      we think about the diagram in <xref ref="F-1-5-Ex1">Figure</xref> above.
      On the left,
      we see the two secant lines with slopes that come from computing the
      <em>backward difference</em>
          <idx><h>backward difference</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(1)-f(2)}{1-2} = 0.75</m> and from the
      <em>forward difference</em>
          <idx><h>forward difference</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(3)-f(2)}{3-2} = 0.375</m>.
      Note how the first slope overestimates the slope of the tangent line at <m>(2,f(2))</m>,
      while the second slope underestimates <m>f'(2)</m>.
      On the right, we see the secant line whose slope is given by the
      <em>central difference</em>
          <idx><h>central difference</h></idx>
      <me permid="XJd">
        \frac{f(3)-f(1)}{3-1} = \frac{3.625-2.5}{2} = \frac{1.125}{2} = 0.5625
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="iii">
      Note that this central difference has the same value as the average of the forward and backward differences
      (and it is straightforward to explain why this always holds).
      The central difference yields a very good approximation to the derivative's value,
      because it yields a line closer to being parallel to the tangent line.
    </p>

<assemblage>
    <p permid="Opr">
      The <term>central difference approximation</term>
      to the value of the first derivative is given by
      <me permid="DQm">
        f'(a) \approx \frac{f(a+h) - f(a-h)}{2h}
      </me>.
      This quantity measures the slope of the secant line to <m>y = f(x)</m> through the points
      <m>(a-h, f(a-h))</m> and <m>(a+h, f(a+h))</m>.
    </p>
</assemblage>

<example xml:id="act-1-5-1" permid="yxi">
  <statement>
    <p permid="NGg">
      A potato is placed in an oven,
      and the potato's temperature <m>F</m>
      (in degrees Fahrenheit)
      at various points in time is taken and recorded in the following table.
      Time <m>t</m> is measured in minutes.
    </p>

    <table permid="miQ">
      <caption>Temperature data in degrees Fahrenheit.</caption>
      <tabular bottom="minor" top="minor" permid="SpZ">
        <row bottom="medium">
          <cell><m>t</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0</m></cell>
          <cell><m>15</m></cell>
          <cell><m>30</m></cell>
          <cell><m>45</m></cell>
          <cell><m>60</m></cell>
          <cell><m>75</m></cell>
          <cell><m>90</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>F(t)</m></cell>
          <cell><m>70</m></cell>
          <cell><m>180.5</m></cell>
          <cell><m>251</m></cell>
          <cell><m>296</m></cell>
          <cell><m>324.5</m></cell>
          <cell><m>342.8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>354.5</m></cell>
        </row>
      </tabular>

    </table>

    <p permid="tNp">
      <ol label="a." permid="DCA">
        <li permid="jJJ">
          <p permid="Cxh">
            Use a central difference to estimate the instantaneous rate of change of the temperature of the potato at <m>t= 30</m>.
            Include units in your answer.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="PQS">
          <p permid="iEq">
            Use a central difference to estimate the instantaneous rate of change of the temperature of the potato at <m>t= 60</m>.
            Include units in your answer.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="vYb">
          <p permid="OLz">
            Without doing any calculation,
            which do you expect to be greater:
            <m>F'(75)</m> or <m>F'(90)</m>?
            Why?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="cfk">
          <p permid="uSI">
            Suppose it is given that
            <m>F(64) = 330.28</m> and <m>F'(64) = 1.341</m>.
            What are the units on these two quantities?
            What do you expect the temperature of the potato to be when <m>t = 65</m>? when <m>t = 66</m>?
            Why?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Imt">
          <p permid="aZR">
            Write a couple of careful sentences that describe the behavior of the temperature of the potato on the time interval <m>[0,90]</m>,
            as well as the behavior of the instantaneous rate of change of the temperature of the potato on the same time interval.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="eZQ">
    <p permid="hyX">
      <ol label="a." permid="Xvr">
        <li permid="otC">
          <p permid="Hha">
            Think about quantities such as <m>\frac{F(45)-F(30)}{45-30}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="UAL">
          <p permid="noj">
            See the note in (a).
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="AHU">
          <p permid="Tvs">
            Is <m>F</m> changing faster at <m>t = 75</m> or at <m>t = 90</m>?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="gPd">
          <p permid="zCB">
            Remember that the units on <m>F'</m> will be
            <q>degrees Fahrenheit per minute.</q>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="MWm">
          <p permid="fJK">
            Be careful to distinguish between the temperature,
            <m>F</m>,
            and the rate of change of temperature,
            <m>F'</m>, in your commentary.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="ySH">
    <p permid="BrO">
      <ol label="a." permid="roi">
        <li permid="tdv">
          <p permid="LQT">
            <m>F'(30) \approx 3.85</m> degrees per minute.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ZkE">
          <p permid="rYc">
            <m>F'(60) \approx 1.56</m> degrees per minute.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="FrN">
          <p permid="Yfl">
            <m>F'(75) \gt F'(90)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="lyW">
          <p permid="Emu">
            The value <m>F(64) = 330.28</m> is the temperature of the potato in degrees Fahrenheit at time <m>64</m>,
            while <m>F'(64) = 1.341</m> measures the instantaneous rate of change of the potato's temperature with respect to time at the instant <m>t = 64</m>,
            and its units are degrees per minute.
            Because at time <m>t = 64</m> the potato's temperature is increasing at a rate of <m>1.341</m> degrees per minute,
            we expect that at <m>t = 65</m>,
            the temperature will be about <m>1.341</m> degrees greater than at <m>t = 64</m>,
            or in other words <m>F(65) \approx 330.28 + 1.341 = 331.621</m> degrees.
            Similarly, at <m>t = 66</m>,
            two minutes have elapsed from <m>t = 64</m>,
            so we expect an increase of <m>2 \cdot 1.341</m> degrees:
            <m>F(66) \approx 330.28 + 2 \cdot 1.341 = 332.962</m> degrees.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="RGf">
          <p permid="ktD">
            Throughout the time interval <m>[0,90]</m>,
            the temperature <m>F</m> of the potato is increasing.
            But as time goes on,
            the rate at which the temperature is rising appears to be decreasing.
            That is,
            while the values of <m>F</m> continue to get larger as time progresses,
            the values of <m>F'</m> are getting smaller
            (while still remaining positive).
            We thus might say that <q>the temperature of the potato is increasing,
            but at a decreasing rate.</q>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="SLy">
    <p permid="VkF">
      <ol label="a." permid="LgZ">
        <li permid="xNo">
          <p permid="QAM">
            Using the central difference, we find that
            <me permid="ZUy">
              F'(30) \approx \frac{F(45)-F(15)}{45-15} = \frac{296-180.5}{30} = 3.85
            </me>
            degrees per minute.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="dUx">
          <p permid="wHV">
            Using the central difference, we find that
            <me permid="GbH">
              F'(60) \approx \frac{F(75)-F(45)}{45-15} = \frac{342.8-296}{30} = 1.56
            </me>
            degrees per minute.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="KbG">
          <p permid="cPe">
            Over each subsequent time interval,
            we see that the amount of increase in the potato's temperature gets less and less,
            thus we expect the value of <m>F'(t)</m> to get smaller and smaller as time goes on.
            We therefore expect <m>F'(75) \gt F'(90)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="qiP">
          <p permid="IWn">
            The value <m>F(64) = 330.28</m> is the temperature of the potato in degrees Fahrenheit at time <m>64</m>,
            while <m>F'(64) = 1.341</m> measures the instantaneous rate of change of the potato's temperature with respect to time at the instant <m>t = 64</m>,
            and its units are degrees per minute.
            Because at time <m>t = 64</m> the potato's temperature is increasing at a rate of <m>1.341</m> degrees per minute,
            we expect that at <m>t = 65</m>,
            the temperature will be about <m>1.341</m> degrees greater than at <m>t = 64</m>,
            or in other words <m>F(65) \approx 330.28 + 1.341 = 331.621</m> degrees.
            Similarly, at <m>t = 66</m>,
            two minutes have elapsed from <m>t = 64</m>,
            so we expect an increase of <m>2 \cdot 1.341</m> degrees:
            <m>F(66) \approx 330.28 + 2 \cdot 1.341 = 332.962</m> degrees.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="WpY">
          <p permid="pdw">
            Throughout the time interval <m>[0,90]</m>,
            the temperature <m>F</m> of the potato is increasing.
            But as time goes on,
            the rate at which the temperature is rising appears to be decreasing.
            That is,
            while the values of <m>F</m> continue to get larger as time progresses,
            the values of <m>F'</m> are getting smaller
            (while still remaining positive).
            We thus might say that <q>the temperature of the potato is increasing,
            but at a decreasing rate.</q>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

<example xml:id="act-1-5-2" permid="lNr">
  <statement>
    <p permid="ZyZ">
      A company manufactures rope,
      and the total cost of producing <m>r</m> feet of rope is <m>C(r)</m> dollars.

      <ol label="a." permid="Pvt">
        <li permid="vCC">
          <p permid="Oqa">
            What does it mean to say that <m>C(2000) = 800</m>?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="bJL">
          <p permid="uxj">
            What are the units of <m>C'(r)</m>?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="HQU">
          <p permid="aEs">
            Suppose that <m>C(2000) = 800</m> and <m>C'(2000) = 0.35</m>.
            Estimate <m>C(2100)</m>,
            and justify your estimate by writing at least one sentence that explains your thinking.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="nYd">
          <p permid="GLB">
            Do you think <m>C'(2000)</m> is less than, equal to,
            or greater than <m>C'(3000)</m>?
            Why?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Ufm">
          <p permid="mSK">
            Suppose someone claims that <m>C'(5000) = -0.1</m>.
            What would the practical meaning of this derivative value tell you about the approximate cost of the next foot of rope?
            Is this possible?
            Why or why not?
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="qSJ">
    <p permid="trQ">
      <ol label="a." permid="jok">
        <li permid="Amv">
          <p permid="SZT">
            The cost of producing 2000 feet of rope is <m>\ldots</m>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="gtE">
          <p permid="zhc">
            Remember that the units on any derivative are
            <q>units of output per unit of input.</q>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="MAN">
          <p permid="fol">
            How much do you expect <m>C</m> to increase for each additional foot away from 2000?
            By how many feet will the input increase to get to 2100?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="sHW">
          <p permid="Lvu">
            In manufacturing processes,
            there is often a decrease in cost per unit as the number of units increases.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="YPf">
          <p permid="rCD">
            Is it possible for the total cost function to be decreasing at some point?
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="KLA">
    <p permid="NkH">
      <ol label="a." permid="Dhb">
        <li permid="EWo">
          <p permid="XJM">
            It costs <dollar />800 to make 2000 feet of rope.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ldx">
          <p permid="DQV">
            <q>dollars per foot.</q>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="RkG">
          <p permid="jYe">
            <m>C(2100) \approx 835</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="xrP">
          <p permid="Qfn">
            Either <m>C'(2000) = C'(3000)</m> or <m>C'(2000) > C'(3000)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="dyY">
          <p permid="wmw">
            Impossible.
            The total cost function <m>C(r)</m> can never decrease.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="eEr">
    <p permid="hdy">
      <ol label="a." permid="WZS">
        <li permid="JGh">
          <p permid="ctF">
            <m>C(2000) = 800</m> means that it costs <dollar />800 to make 2000 feet of rope.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="pNq">
          <p permid="IAO">
            The units of <m>C'(r)</m> are
            <q>dollars per foot.</q>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="VUz">
          <p permid="oHX">
            If <m>C(2000) = 800</m> and <m>C'(2000) = 0.35</m>,
            then we know once 2000 feet of rope are produced,
            the total cost function is increasing at <dollar />0.35 per additional foot of rope.
            Then, if we manufacture an additional 100 feet of rope,
            the additional total cost will be approximately
            <me permid="FGi">
              100 \ \text{feet}  \cdot 0.35 \ \frac{\text{dollars} }{\text{foot} } = 35 \ \text{dollars}
            </me>.
            Therefore,
            we find that <m>C(2100) \approx C(2000) + 35 = 835</m>,
            or that the cost to make 2100 feet of rope is about <dollar />835.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="CbI">
          <p permid="UPg">
            Either <m>C'(2000) = C'(3000)</m> or <m>C'(2000) > C'(3000)</m>,
            since we expect the cost per foot of additional rope to either stay constant or to get smaller as the production volume increases.
            Said differently,
            the instantaneous rate of change of the total cost function should either be constant or decrease due to economy of scale.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="iiR">
          <p permid="AWp">
            It is impossible to have
            <m>C'(5000) = -0.1</m> and indeed to have any negative derivative value for the total cost function.
            The total cost function <m>C(r)</m> can never decrease,
            because it doesn't make sense for the total cost of producing 5001 feet of rope to be less than the total cost of producing 5000 feet of rope.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

<example xml:id="act-1-5-3" permid="eSM">
  <statement>
    <p permid="SEu">
      Researchers at a major car company have found a function that relates gasoline consumption to speed for a particular model of car.
      In particular,
      they have determined that the consumption <m>C</m>,
      in <em>liters per kilometer</em>,
      at a given speed <m>s</m>,
      is given by a function <m>C = f(s)</m>,
      where <m>s</m> is the car's speed in
      <em>kilometers per hour</em>.

      <ol label="a." permid="CLC">
        <li permid="iSL">
          <p permid="EAP">
            Data provided by the car company tells us that <m>f(80) = 0.015</m>,
            <m>f(90) = 0.02</m>, and <m>f(100) = 0.027</m>.
            Use this information to estimate the instantaneous rate of change of fuel consumption with respect to speed at <m>s = 90</m>.
            Be as accurate as possible,
            use proper notation, and include units in your answer.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="OZU">
          <p permid="kHY">
            By writing a complete sentence, interpret the meaning
            (in the context of fuel consumption)
            of <q><m>f(80) = 0.015</m>.</q>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="vhd">
          <p permid="QPh">
            Write at least one complete sentence that interprets the meaning of the value of <m>f'(90)</m> that you estimated in (a).
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="eiS">
    <p permid="mxl">
      <ol label="a." permid="WEt">
        <li permid="bom">
          <p permid="wWq">
            Try a central difference.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Hvv">
          <p permid="ddz">
            What is happening when the car is traveling at 80 km/hr?
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="nCE">
          <p permid="JkI">
            Remember that units on the derivative are
            <q>units of output per unit of input.</q>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="ybJ">
    <p permid="Gqc">
      <ol label="a." permid="qxk">
        <li permid="TJN">
          <p permid="prR">
            <m>f'(90) \approx 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="zQW">
          <p permid="Vza">
            At 80 kilometers per hour,
            the car is using fuel at a rate of 0.015 liters per kilometer.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="fYf">
          <p permid="BGj">
            When the car is traveling at 90 kilometers per hour,
            its rate of fuel consumption per kilometer is increasing at a rate of 0.0006 liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="RUA">
    <p permid="aiT">
      <ol label="a." permid="Kqb">
        <li permid="Mfo">
          <p permid="hNs">
            Using a central difference, we have
            <me permid="yLD">
              f'(90) \approx \frac{f(100) - f(80)}{100-80} = \frac{0.027 - 0.015}{20} = \frac{0.012}{20} = 0.0006
            </me>
            which tells us that
            <m>f'(90) \approx 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="smx">
          <p permid="NUB">
            When the car is traveling at 80 kilometers per hour,
            it is using fuel at a rate of 0.015 liters per kilometer.
            That is, at the given speed,
            for each additional kilometer the car travels,
            it uses an additional 0.015 liters of fuel.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="YtG">
          <p permid="ubK">
            To say that <m>f'(90) = 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour means that when the car is traveling at 90 kilometers per hour,
            its rate of fuel consumption per kilometer is increasing at a rate of 0.0006 liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.
            If we increase our speed from 90 to 91 km/hr,
            we would expect our rate of fuel consumption to rise by 0.0006 liters for each additional kilometer driven.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>

    <p permid="uwA">
      In <xref ref="sec-1-4-derivative-fxn">Section</xref>,
      we learned how use to the graph of a given function <m>f</m> to plot the graph of its derivative,
      <m>f'</m>.
      It is important to remember that when we do so,
      the scale and the units on the vertical axis often have to change to represent <m>f'</m>.
      For example, suppose that
      <m>P(t) = 400-330e^{-0.03t}</m> tells us the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit of a potato in an oven at time <m>t</m> in minutes.
      In <xref ref="F-1-5-PPprime">Figure</xref> below,
      we sketch the graph of <m>P</m> on the left and the graph of <m>P'</m> on the right.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-5-PPprime" permid="mSb">
      <caption>Plot of <m>P(t) = 400-330e^{-0.03t}</m> at left, and its derivative <m>P'(t)</m> at right.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_5_PPprimeplot" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="aDJ">
      Notice that both the size and the units of the vertical scales differ,
      as the units of <m>P</m> are
      <m>^{\circ}</m>F, while those of <m>P'</m> are <m>^{\circ}</m>F/min.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="Brf">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="SZk">
      <ul permid="Spq">
        <li permid="WZj">
          <p permid="nXu">
            The derivative of a given function <m>y=f(x)</m> measures the instantaneous rate of change of the output variable with respect to the input variable.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Dgs">
          <p permid="UeD">
            The units on the derivative function
            <m>y = f'(x)</m> are units of <m>f(x)</m> per unit of <m>x</m>.
            Again,
            this measures how fast the output of the function <m>f</m> changes when the input of the function changes.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="jnB">
          <p permid="AlM">
            The central difference approximation to the value of the first derivative is given by
            <me permid="jXv">
              f'(a) \approx \frac{f(a+h) - f(a-h)}{2h}
            </me>.
            This quantity measures the slope of the secant line to <m>y = f(x)</m> through the points
            <m>(a-h, f(a-h))</m> and <m>(a+h, f(a+h))</m>.
            The central difference generates a good approximation of the derivative's value.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-5.xml" />
</section>

