<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-2-10-MVT" permid="kOT">
  <title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
  <objectives permid="pyM">
    <ul permid="hUn">
      <li permid="uiF">
        <p permid="eZH">
          Can we use global information about a function (for instance, the average rate of change) to say anything about the local behavior of the function (such as the instantaneous rate of change)?
        </p>
      </li>

    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction><p>
  When you know how a function behaves at every point, you know quite a lot about that function. This is the whole idea behind plotting points on a coordinate plane in order to determine what the graph of a function looks like. Indeed, given enough local information about a function, we can describe it very well globally. However, the opposite is not generally true. Suppose, for instance, that you know the graph of <m>y=f(x)</m> is a parabola. Knowing that, can you determine the value of <m>f(3)</m>? The answer, of course, is that you do not have enough information. In general, global information is not enough to determine local information. In other words, knowing how a function behaves overall is not usually enough to say anything about how the function behaves at a specific point. However, there are some exceptions to this generalization. One such special case is the mean value theorem. 
  
</p>
  </introduction>
<subsection><title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
<example>
<p>
Suppose it took you exactly three quarters of an hour to drive the <m>59</m> miles 
from Lincoln, Nebraska to Omaha, Nebraska.  Is it possible that you drove less than 
<m>75</m> miles per hour the entire trip?  
</p>
<p>
Since <m>59</m> miles were driven in <m>\frac34</m> hours, the average speed (i.e. 
average rate of change) on the trip was 
<me>\frac{59\text{ miles}}{\frac34\text{ hours}}=\frac{59\cdot4}3\approx78.67\text{ mph}</me>. 
Because this is an average, our intuition tells us that at some point on the trip the 
car must have been going at least as fast as <m>78.67</m> miles per hour. This is 
precisely what the mean value theorem addresses.  
</p>
</example>
<assemblage><title>The Mean Value Theorem</title><p>
<idx><h>mean value theorem</h></idx>
Let <m>f</m> be a function that is continuous on the closed interval <m>[a,b]</m> 
and differentiable on the open interval <m>(a,b)</m>. Then there exists a number 
<m>c</m>, with <m>a\lt c \lt b</m>, such that <me>f'(c)=\dfrac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}.</me>  
In other words, <m>f(b)-f(a)=f'(c)(b-a)</m>.</p>
</assemblage>

<p>
While a proof of the mean value theorem is outside the scope of this textbook, it is 
worth rephrasing the theorem in a way that is perhaps more clear. The mean value 
theorem essentially states that given any two points on a continuous curve, there is a 
point somewhere in the middle at which the line tangent to the curve is parallel to 
the secant line that connects the two points. A geometric representation of this is illustrated 
below in <xref ref="mvt">Figure</xref>.
</p>
<figure xml:id="mvt">
    <caption>A geometric representation of the Mean Value Theorem. The blue curve is the graph of <m>y=f(t)</m>, where <m>f</m> is some function that is continuous on <m>[a,b]</m> and differentiable on <m>(a,b)</m>. The secant line connecting the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(b,f(b))</m> is shown in black and has slope <m>(f(b)-f(a))/(b-a)</m>. There appears to be at least one point, <m>c</m>, between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> at which the slope of the tangent line (shown in red) is precisely the same as the slope of the secant line.</caption>
    <image width="60%" source="images/2-10-MVT2.jpg" />
</figure>

<example>
<statement>
  <p>
  Consider the function <m>f(x)=2x^3-x</m> on the interval <m>[1,3]</m>. Find a value 
  of <m>c</m> on the interval <m>(1,3)</m> such that 
  <me>f'(c)=\frac{f(3)-f(1)}{3-1}.</me>
  </p>
</statement>
<hint>
<p>Use differentiation rules to find the derivative, then evaluate at <m>x=c</m> and 
solve for <m>c</m>.</p>
</hint>
<answer>
<p><m>c=\sqrt{\frac{13}{3}}</m>.</p>
</answer>
<solution>
<p>
We start by evaluating the function at the endpoints of the interval, finding that  
<me>f(3)=2(27)-3=51, \quad \text{and} \quad f(1)=2(1)-1=1</me>. So we are trying to find 
<m>c</m> in the interval <m>(1,3)</m> such that <m>f'(c)=\frac{51-1}{3-1}=25.</m> 
</p>
<p>Using the power rule and the sum rule, we have that <m>f'(x)=6x^2-1</m>, 
so <m>f'(c)=6c^2-1</m>. Solving the equation <m>6c^2-1=25</m>, we find that 
<m>c=\pm\sqrt{\frac{13}{3}}</m>. Since we are looking only on the interval <m>(1,3)</m>, 
<!--we find that the value of <m>c</m> on the interval <m>(1,3)</m> such that 
<m>f'(c)=\frac{f(3)-f(1)}{3-1}</m>--> 
the value we want 
is <m>c=+\sqrt{\frac{13}{3}}</m>.
</p>
</solution>
</example>


</subsection>
<subsection><title>Consequences of the Mean Value Theorem</title>
<p>
The Mean Value Theorem has several important consequences that confirm some intuitive ideas that you may already hold.  
First, the <em>Increasing Function Theorem</em> establishes that continuous functions with a positive derivative on an interval are increasing on that interval.  More formally,
</p>

<assemblage><title>The Increasing Function Theorem</title>
<idx><h>increasing function theorem</h></idx>
<p>
Suppose that <m>f</m> is continuous on <m>a \leq x \leq b</m> and differentiable on <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>.
<ul>
<li> If <m>f'(x)>0</m> on <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>, then <m>f</m> is increasing on <m>a \leq x \leq  b</m>.</li>
<li> If <m>f'(x) \geq 0</m> on <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>, then <m>f</m> is non-decreasing on <m>a \leq x \leq  b</m>.</li>
</ul></p>
</assemblage>
  <p>This theorem is demonstrated in <xref ref="ift">Figure</xref>. When the slope of the tangent line is positive for all <m>x</m> values on a given interval, we see that the function is increasing. </p>
  <figure xml:id="ift">
    <caption>A geometric representation of the Increasing Function Theorem. The blue curve is the graph of <m>y=f(t)</m>, where <m>f</m> is some function that is continuous on <m>[a,b]</m> and differentiable on <m>(a,b)</m>. The tangent lines are positive where the function is increasing.</caption>
    <image width="60%" source="images/2-10-increasingfunction.gif" />
</figure>
  
<p>
We can also state that a function with a derivative equal to zero on an interval is constant on that interval.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Constant Function Theorem</title><p>
Suppose that <m>f</m> is continuous on <m>a \leq x \leq b</m> and differentiable on <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>.  If <m>f '(x) = 0</m> on <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>, then <m>f</m> is constant on <m>a \leq x \leq b</m>.
</p>
</assemblage>
  <p>The following example will provide some intuition for the Constant Function Theorem.</p>
  <example><p>
   Suppose you're driving your car using cruise control set to 55 miles per hour. Let's say you drive this way for 30 minutes. The instantaneous rate of change (i.e., the instantaneous acceleration) at each minute of your drive is 0 miles per hour<m>^2</m>. If we plotted the car's velocity as a function <m>v=f(t)</m> of time in minutes, the car's acceleration is the derivative <m>a=f'(t)</m>.</p>
    
    <p> Let's say you approach a red light on the road and you turn the cruise control off for 30 seconds, but then the light turns green and you reset the cruise control to 55 miles per hour. When you turned the cruise control off, your car slowed down a little bit before returning to the cruising speed. Thus, the instantaneous acceleration is non-zero during the 30 seconds. In other words, when the car's velocity is not constant over an interval, the derivative is non-zero over that interval.  
   </p></example>


<p>
We have one final result that can be used to formalize another intuitive idea.  The <em>Racetrack Principle</em> argues that if two objects begin at the same place and the same time and one is traveling faster than the other, then the faster object will be ahead of the slower object.  Formally, we write the principle in terms of functions.
</p>

<assemblage><title>The Racetrack Principle</title>
<p>
Suppose that <m>g</m> and <m>h</m> are continuous on <m>a \leq x \leq b</m> and differentiable on <m>a\lt x\lt b</m>, and that <m>g'(x) \leq h'(x)</m> for <m>a\lt x \lt b</m>.
<ul>
<li>If <m>g(a)=h(a)</m>, then <m>g(x) \leq h(x)</m> for <m>a \leq x \leq b</m>.</li>
<li> If <m>g(b)=h(b)</m>, then <m>g(x) \geq h(x)</m> for <m>a \leq x \leq b</m>.</li>
</ul>
</p>
</assemblage>
  
  
  <example><p>
   Erica and Mason want to race each other down the street. They draw the start line and finish line. On your mark, get set, GO! Erica runs faster than Mason the entire time, so Erica wins the race. It makes sense that Erica was ahead of Mason during the whole race.</p>
    
    <p> Now suppose that Mason wanted a rematch, but he isn't willing to play fair this time. Mason and Erica line up at the starting line, but Mason takes an early start. Again, Erica runs faster than Mason the entire time. This time, they reach the finish line at the same time. It makes sense that Mason was ahead of Erica during the whole race.     
    </p>
  </example>
  

<example>
  <statement><p>
    Use the Racetrack Principle to show that <m>\ln(x)\leq x-1</m> for all <m>x\geq 1.</m> Is the statement also true for all <m> 0\lt x \leq 1</m>?
    </p></statement>
    <solution><p>Set <m>g(x)=\ln(x)</m> and <m>h(x)=x-1</m>. Both functions are continuous on <m>[1,\infty)</m> and differentiable on <m>(1,\infty)</m>. </p>
      <p>We take the derivative of each function:
        <me>g'(x)=\frac{1}{x},</me>
        <me> h'(x)=1.</me></p>
      <p>Since <q><m>x\ge1</m></q> and <q><m>\frac1x\le1</m></q> are equivalent statements,
      we thus have <m>g'(x)\leq h'(x)</m> for all <m>x\geq 1</m>.</p>
      <p>Comparing function values when <m>x=1</m>, we see that <m>g(1)=\ln(1)=0</m> and <m>h(1)=1-1=0</m>.
      Therefore the Racetrack Principle says <m>g(x)\leq h(x)</m> (i.e. <m>\ln(x)\leq x-1 </m>) for all <m> x\geq 1</m>.</p>
      
      <p>Similarly, if we consider values <m> 0\lt x \leq 1</m>, we have that <m>g'(x)\geq h'(x)</m>. Since <m>g(1)=h(1)</m>, we have that <m>h(x)\geq g(x)</m> or <m>x-1\geq \ln(x)</m> for all <m>0\lt x\leq 1</m>.
      Note that we have to be careful in applying the racetrack principle here, since <m>\ln(x)</m> is not continuous (because it's undefined) at <m>x=0</m>. But we can choose the lower bound of the interval to be any positive number less than <m>1</m>, and then take the limit as that number approaches <m>0</m> to obtain the result.</p>
    </solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"> 
  <exercise>
    <title>Understanding the Statement of the Mean Value Theorem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap3Sec10/Q07.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
    <title>Applying Theorems</title>
    <webwork source="local/Derivatives_Theorems/TrueFalseApplyingTheorems.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Conclusion of the Mean Value Theorem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Wiley/setAnton_Section_4.8/Question8.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
  
        <exercise>
    <title>Conclusion of the Mean Value Theorem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/WHFreeman/Rogawski_Calculus_Early_Transcendentals_Second_Edition/4_Applications_of_the_Derivative/4.3_The_Mean_Value_Theorem_and_Monotonicity/4.3.1.pg" />
  </exercise>
  

  
  
 </exercises>  




</section>

