<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="explog"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Exponential and Logarithmic Functions</title>
<introduction>
<p>In this chapter we define exponential and logarithmic functions.  For a more extensive treatment of exponential functions we refer the reader to <url href="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/Exponential-Functions.html">PreCalculus at Nebraska: Exponential Functions</url> and for a more extensive treatment of exponential functions we refer the reader to <url href="https://mathbooks.unl.edu/PreCalculus/section-33.html">PreCalculus at Nebraska: Logarithmic Functions</url></p>
</introduction>
<subsection><title>Exponential Functions</title>

  <p>
  Before we discuss exponential functions, it is first useful to define the notion of concavity.
  </p>
 <assemblage>
    <title>Concavity</title>
    <p>
    The graph of a function is concave up if it bends upward as we move left to right; it is concave down if it bends downward.  A line is neither concave up nor concave down. 
    </p>
</assemblage> 


<p>
     An exponential function will be either be increasing or decreasing, but will always be concave up! We define such a function as follows:
</p>
<assemblage><title>Exponential Function</title>
<p>
	<me>P(t) = a \cdot b^t \text{, where } b \gt 0 \text{ and } b \ne 1 \text{, } a \ne 0.</me>
</p>
<p>The constant <m> a </m> is the <m> y</m>-value of the <m> y</m>-intercept of the function.
</p>
</assemblage>


<p>
The equation
<me>
P(t)=P_0 a^t
</me>
gives an exponential function with base <m>a</m>. Then 
<me>
\frac{P(t+1)}{P(t)}=\frac{P_0 a^{t+1}}{P_0 a^t}=a =\text{constant rate of growth/decay}
</me>
<ul>
<li>Growth: <m>a\gt1</m>: Doubling time: the time it takes to double the initial amount</li>

<li>Decay <m>0\lt a\lt1</m>: Half-life: the time it takes to decay to half of the initial amount</li>
</ul>

</p>
 <assemblage>
    <title>Doubling Time and Half-life</title>
<p>
<li>The doubling time of an exponentially increasing quantity is the time required for the quantity to double.</li>


<li>The half-life of an exponentially decaying quantity is the time required for the quantity to be reduced by a factor of one half.</li>
</p>
</assemblage> 

<p>
We will (naturally) consider exponentials (and later, logarithms) in base 
<me>
e \approx 2.718281828459... \text{ (irrational number)}
</me>
For example, the general exponential function in the natural base
<me>
P(t)=P_0 a^t=P_0 (e^k)^t=P_0e^{kt}, \quad a=e^k. 
</me>
Thus, we will have 
<ul>
<li>exponential growth if <m>a\gt 1</m>, which gives <m>k\gt 0</m></li>
<li>exponential decay if <m>0\lt a\lt 1</m>, which gives <m>k\lt 0</m></li>
</ul>
The number <m>k</m> is called <em>the continuous rate of growth/decay.</em> To find <m>k</m> we will need the logarithmic function.
</p>

</subsection> 

<subsection><title>Logarithmic Functions</title>
<p> Recall inverse functions.  If for each <m>y</m> in the range of <m>f</m> there exists exactly one value of <m>x</m> such that <m>f(x)=y,</m> then <m>f</m> has an inverse at <m>y</m> denoted by <m>f^{-1}</m> such that
<me>
f(x)=y \quad \iff \quad f^{-1}(y)=x
</me>
Hence
<me>
f(f^{-1}(y))=y \quad \text{and} \quad f^{-1}(f(x))=x.
</me>
The <em>inverse</em> of the exponential function <m>f(x)=e^x</m> is the natural <em>logarithmic</em> function <m>f^{-1}(x)= \ln(x)</m> so we have
<me>
\ln(x) =c \iff e^c=x  
</me>
</p>
        <assemblage><title>The Logarithm</title><idx>The Logarithm</idx>
            <p>
                Let <m> b\neq 1 </m> be a positive number, then the function
                <me> f(t)=\log_b(t) </me>
                    is called a logarithm with base <m> b </m>.
                    </p>
                
                <p>
                    Upon inputting a value <m> t</m>, the function <m> \log_b(t)</m> will tell you the  power of <m> b </m> which will yield <m> t </m>.
            </p>
        </assemblage>
        
                <p>
            Due to the relationship between logarithms and exponentials, we often say that the equations
            
            <me> x=\log_b(y)\ \ \ \ \text{and}\ \ \ \ b^x=y</me>
            are equivalent.
            </p>
        <warning>
            <p>Two common bases of a logarithm are base <m> 10 </m> and <m> e</m>. Since they are used so often, we have developed a short hand notation for a logarithm of base <m> 10</m> and a logarithm of base <m> e</m>. This short hand is shown below:
            <me>
                \log_{10}(y)=\log(y).
                </me>
                
                            <me>
                \log_{e}(y)=\ln(y).
                </me>
            In other words, we simply drop the subscript when referring to base <m> 10 </m> and we change to <m>\ln</m> when referring to base <m>e</m></p>
            </warning>
<p>
There are some important properties of logarithms that you should be familiar with.
</p>
        <assemblage><title>Properties of Logarithms</title>
            <p> If <m> x,y,b>0</m>, and <m> b\neq 1</m>, then
                <ol label="1">
                    <li><p>
                        <m>
                            \log_b(xy)=\log_b(x)+\log_b(y),
                            </m>
                    </p></li>
                    <li><p>
                        <m>
                            \log_b(\frac{x}{y})=\log_b(x)-\log_b(y),
                            </m>
                    </p></li>
                    <li><p>
                        <m>
                            \log_b(x^k)=k\cdot \log_b(x),
                        </m>
                    </p></li>
                    <li><p>
                        <m>
                            \log_b(b^y)=y,
                        </m>
                    </p></li>
                    <li><p>
                        <m>
                            b^{\log_b(x)}=x.
                        </m>
                    </p></li>
                </ol></p>
            </assemblage>

</subsection>

<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"> 
    <exercise>
    <title>General Exponential Functions</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec2/Q23.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
      <exercise>
    <title>Finding Exponential Functions</title>
    <webwork source="local/Functions/Exponential_Functions/PointsOnFunction.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
        <exercise>
    <title>Finding the Parameters for an Exponential Function</title>
    <webwork source="local/Functions/Exponential_Functions/FindInitValueAndFactor.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
          <exercise>
    <title>Half-Life</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec4/Q36.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
            <exercise>
    <title>Applied Half-Life</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap1Sec4/Q46.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
              <exercise>
    <title>Solving Exponential Equations</title>
    <webwork source="local/Functions/Logarithms/Solving.pg" />
  </exercise>
  
                <exercise>
    <title>Using Inverse Functions With Exponentials and Logarithms</title>
    <webwork source="local/Functions/Logarithms/Inverses.pg" />
  </exercise>
  

 </exercises>  
  
  </section>


<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
