<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-7-other-opt" permid="GxK">
  <title>Other Options for Finding Algebraic Antiderivatives</title>
  <objectives permid="XvV">
    <ul permid="MWQ">
      <li permid="Zli">
        <p permid="Kck">
          How does the method of partial fractions enable many rational functions to be antidifferentiated?
        </p>
      </li>
      <li> 
        <p> 
          How does the method of trigonometric substitutions help us find antiderivatives of functions that may include expressions like <m> \sqrt{a^2-x^2}</m>, <m> a^2 + x^2 </m>, and <m> \sqrt{a^2 + x^2} </m> where <m> a </m> is any real number?   
        </p>  
      </li>  
      <li permid="Fsr">
        <p permid="qjt">
          What role have integral tables historically played in the study of calculus and how can a table be used to evaluate integrals such as <m>\int \sqrt{a^2 + u^2} \, du</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="lzA">
        <p permid="WqC">
          What role can a computer algebra system play in the process of finding antiderivatives?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="DDe">
    <p permid="IWR">
      We have learned two antidifferentiation techniques:
      <m>u</m>-substitution and integration by parts.
      The former is used to reverse the chain rule,
      while the latter is used to reverse the product rule.
      But we have seen that each works only in specialized circumstances.
      For example,
      while <m>\int xe^{x^2} \, dx</m> may be evaluated by <m>u</m>-substitution and
      <m>\int x e^x \, dx</m> by integration by parts,
      neither method provides a route to evaluate <m>\int e^{x^2} \, dx</m>.
      In fact, an elementary algebraic antiderivative for <m>e^{x^2}</m> does not exist.
      No antidifferentiation method will provide us with a simple algebraic formula for a function <m>F(x)</m> that satisfies <m>F'(x) = e^{x^2}</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="pea">
      In this section,
      our main goals are to identify some classes of functions that can be antidifferentiated,
      and to learn some methods to do so.
      We should also recognize that there are many functions for which an algebraic formula for an antiderivative does not exist,
      and appreciate the role that computing technology can play in finding antiderivatives of other complicated functions.
    </p>

<example xml:id="PA-5-5" permid="XEz">
<statement>
  <p permid="rxq">
    For each of the indefinite integrals below,
    decide whether the integral can be evaluated using <m>u</m>-substitution,
    integration by parts, a combination of the two, or neither.


    For integrals for which your answer is affirmative,
    state the substitution(s) you would use.
    It is not necessary to actually evaluate any of the integrals completely,
    unless the integral can be evaluated immediately using a familiar basic antiderivative.

    <ol label="a." permid="OkN">
      <li permid="urW">
        <p permid="SUG">
          <m>\int x^2 \sin(x^3) \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /><m>\int x^2 \sin(x) \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \sin(x^3) \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int x^5 \sin(x^3) \, dx</m>
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="azf">
        <p permid="zbP">
          <m>\int \frac{1}{1+x^2} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \frac{x}{1+x^2} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \frac{2x+3}{1+x^2} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /><m>\int \frac{e^x}{1+(e^x)^2} \, dx</m>,
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="GGo">
        <p permid="fiY">
          <m>\int x \ln(x) \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \frac{\ln(x)}{x} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \ln(1+x^2) \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /><m>\int x\ln(1+x^2) \, dx</m>,
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="mNx">
        <p permid="Lqh">
          <m>\int x \sqrt{1-x^2} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /> <m>\int \frac{x}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}\, dx</m>,
          <nbsp /><m>\int \frac{1}{x\sqrt{1-x^2}} \, dx</m>,
        </p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </p>
  </statement>
   <solution>
    <p>
      <ol label="a.">
        <li>
          <p>
            The first integral may be solved by substitution using 
            <m> u = x^3 \ , du = 3x^2 \, dx </m>. 
            The second may be solved using IBP with <m> u = x^2 \ , dv = \sin(x) \, dx </m>
            The third can not be solved using substitution or IBP. 
            The last one can be solve using a combination. First do a substitution with <m> w = x^3 \ , dw = 3x^2 \, dx </m>
            to convert the integral to <m> \frac{1}{3} \int w \sin(w) \, dw </m>. This may be solved using IBP with <m> u = w </m> and <m> dv = \sin(w) \, dw. </m>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li> 
          <p> 
            The first integral can be evaluated by following <xref ref="T-4-4-Act2_2"> Table </xref> which has antiderivatives of some basic functions. The second integral can be solved using the  <m> u </m>-substitution <m> u=1+x^2 \ , du=2x \, dx </m>. This transforms the integral to <m> \frac{1}{2} \int \frac{1}{u} \, du </m>. The third integral requires algebraic manipulation before you can successfully use a substitution. We can evaluate <m> \int \frac{2x+3}{1+x^2} \, dx </m> by recognizing that <m> \frac{2x+3}{1+x^2} =\frac{2x}{1+x^2} + \frac{3}{1+x^2}</m> so we can split the original integral into two integrals. Then, evaluate <m> \int \frac{2x}{1+x^2} \, dx </m> with the substitution <m> u=1+x^2 \ , du=2x \, dx </m> and evaluate <m> \int \frac{3}{1+x^2} \, dx </m> by following <xref ref="T-4-4-Act2_2"> Table </xref>. The fourth integral can be found by using the substitution <m> u=e^x \ , du=e^x \, dx </m> which transforms the integral to <m> \int \frac{1}{1+u^2} \, du </m>. The antiderivative of <m> \frac{1}{1+u^2} \, du </m> is in <xref ref="T-4-4-Act2_2"> Table </xref>.
          </p>  
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>
            The first integral can be evaluated by using integration by parts with <m> u= \ln(x) </m> and <m> dv=x \, dx </m>. The second integral is evaluated by using the substitution <m> u=\ln(x) \ , du= \frac{1}{x} \, dx </m>. The third integral cannot be solved by only using the methods of integration by parts or substitution. In fact, one solution to evaluate it involves first using integration by parts then using a method called <xref ref= "PT"> partial fractions</xref>. The fourth integral can be evaluated by using both a substitution and integration by parts. First, perform the substitution <m> w=1+x^2 \ , dw= 2x \, dx </m> which transforms the integral to <m> \frac{1}{2} \int \ln(w) \, dw </m>. Integration by parts can be used to evaluate this with <m> u=\ln(w) </m> and <m> dv=dx </m>.
          </p>  
        </li> 
        <li>
          <p>
            The first integral can be found by using the substitution <m> u=1-x^2 \ , du=-2x \, dx </m>. The second integral can be evaluated by following <xref ref="T-4-4-Act2_2"> Table </xref>. The third integral can be evaluated by using the substitution <m> u=1-x^2 \ , du=-2x\, dx </m>. The fourth integral cannot be solved with standard substitution, integration by parts, or a combination of both. We will need a new style of substitution called <xref ref="Trig-Sub"> trigonometric substitution </xref> which will be discussed in this section. 
          </p>  
        </li>  
        </ol>

   </p>
        </solution>
        
        
  </example>
  </introduction>

  <subsection xmlid="PT" permid="mET">
    <title>The Method of Partial Fractions</title>
    <idx><h>partial fractions</h></idx>

    <p permid="Vlj">
      The method of partial fractions is used to integrate some rational functions. A rational function is a function that can be written as a quotient of polynomials. The goal of partial fractions is to reverse the process of finding a common denominator, so this method works better when the denominator can be factored into smaller degree polynomials. It is an algebraic manipulation tool that can make integrals more manageable. The method of partial fractions will be demonstrated in the solutions of the next examples. A summary of the method of partial fractions and why it helps with evaluating integrals will follow these examples. 
    </p>

    <example permid="LhD">
      <statement>
        <p permid="wIz">
          Evaluate
          <me permid="JGL">
            \int \frac{5x}{x^2-x-2} \, dx
          </me>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="jKn">
        <p permid="uTm">
          If we factor the denominator of the integrand,
          we can see how <m>\frac{5x}{x^2-x-2}=\frac{5x}{(x-2)(x+1)}</m> might be the sum of two fractions of the form <m>\frac{A}{x-2} + \frac{B}{x+1}</m>, so we
          suppose that
          <men xml:id="E-PF-1" permid="pNU">
            \frac{5x}{(x-2)(x+1)} = \frac{A}{x-2} + \frac{B}{x+1}
          </men>
          and look for the constants <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>.
        </p>

        <p permid="bav">
          Multiplying both sides of this equation by the denominator of the left hand side, <m>(x-2)(x+1)</m>,
          we find that
          <me permid="VVd">
            5x = A(x+1) + B(x-2)
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="HhE">
          To find <m> A </m> and <m> B</m>, we will rearrange the right hand side of the equation so that similar terms are grouped. 
          <me> 5x=Ax+ A + Bx -2B </me>
          <me> 5x+0=(A+B)x + (A-2B) </me>
          Notice that if this equation is going to hold, then the coefficients for <m> x </m> on each side of the equation need to match, and we need the constant terms on each side of the equation to match. This gives us the following system of equations:
          <me> 5=A+B \, \text{ and } \, 0=A-2B</me>
          We find that <m> A=\frac{10}{3} </m> and <m> B=\frac{5}{3} </m>.
          Thus, using <xref ref="E-PF-1"> Equation </xref>, we can rewrite the original integral as
          <me permid="OqE">
            \int \frac{5x}{x^2-x-2} \, dx = \int \frac{10/3}{x-2} + \frac{5/3}{x+1} \, dx
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="noN">
          This integral can be evaluated by using the fact that <m> \int \frac{1}{u} \, du =\ln|u| + C </m> and by using substitutions,
          and hence we find that
          <me permid="uxN">
            \int \frac{5x}{x^2-x-2} \, dx = \frac{10}{3} \ln|x-2| + \frac{5}{3}\ln|x+1| + C
          </me>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p> 
          Evaluate 
          <me> \int \frac{2x^2+5}{x^3-2x^2+x} \, dx </me>.
        </p>  
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          If we factor the denominator of the integrand, we can see that <m> \frac{2x^2+5}{x^3-2x^2+x} = \frac{2x^2+5}{x(x-1)^2} </m>. Notice that the factor <m> (x-1)</m> shows up twice in the denominator. We call <m> (x-1)^2 </m> a repeated linear root. The repeated linear root slightly changes our partial fraction decomposition. <m> \frac{2x^2+5}{x(x-1)^2} </m> can be decomposed into the sum of fractions <m> \frac{A}{x}+ \frac{B}{x-1}+\frac{C}{(x-1)^2}</m>. We need both <m> \frac{B}{x-1} </m> and <m> \frac{C}{(x-1)^2} </m> since both <m> x-1 </m> and <m> (x-1)^2 </m> divide <m> x(x-1)^2 </m>. Suppose 
          <men xml:id="E-PF-2"> \frac{2x^2+5}{x(x-1)^2}= \frac{A}{x}+ \frac{B}{x-1} + \frac{C}{(x-1)^2} </men>
          and look for constants <m> A </m>, <m> B</m>, and <m> C</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Multiplying both sides of this equation by the denominator of the left hand side, <m> x(x-1)^2 </m>, we find that 

          <me> 2x^2+5=A(x-1)^2 + B x (x-1) + Cx </me>

          To find <m> A </m>, <m> B </m>, and <m> C </m>, we will rearrange the right hand side of the equation so that similar terms are grouped. 

          <me>2x^2+5= A(x^2-2x+1) + B(x^2-x) + Cx </me>

          <me>2x^2+0x + 5= (A+B)x^2 + (-2A-B+C)x + A </me>

          Like the previous example, we need the coefficients for <m> x^2 </m> to be the same on each side of the equation, the coeffiecients for <m> x </m> to be the same on each side of the equation, and the constant terms to be the same on each side of the equation. Thus, we obtain the system of equations
          <me> A+B=2 \ , -2A-B+C=0 \ , \text{ and } A=5.</me>
          We find that <m> A=5 </m>, <m> B=-3 </m>, and <m> C=7 </m>. Thus, using <xref ref="E-PF-2"> Equation </xref>, we can rewrite the original integral as 
          <me>\int \frac{2x^2+5}{x(x-1)^2} \, dx=\int  \frac{5}{x}- \frac{3}{x-1} + \frac{7}{(x-1)^2} \, dx</me>

          This integral can be evaluated by using the fact that <m> \int \frac{1}{u} \, du =\ln|u|+C</m> and by using appropriate substitutions, and hence we find that 
          <me>\int \frac{2x^2+5}{x(x-1)^2} \, dx=\int  \frac{5}{x} \, dx - 3 \int \frac{1}{x-1} \, dx + 7 \int (x-2)^{-2} \, dx </me>
          <me> =5 \ln|x| -3 \ln|x-1| - 7 (x-1)^{-1} + C </me>
        </p>  
      </solution>  
    </example>
        
    <example>
      <statement>  
        <p>
          Evaluate
          <me> \int \frac{3x^2-1}{(x^2+2x+3)(x-2)} \, dx </me>.
        </p> 
      </statement> 
      <solution>
        <p>
          The denominator of the integrand is already factored, and the quadratic polynomial <m> x^2 + 2x + 3 </m> cannot be factored anymore. We call this factor an irreducible quadratic factor. The irreducible quadratic factor slightly changes our partial fraction decomposition. <m> \frac{3x^2-1}{(x^2+2x+3)(x-2)} </m> can be decomposed into the sum of fractions <m> \frac{Ax+B}{x^2+2x+3}+ \frac{C}{x-2}</m>. We need the term <m> \frac{Ax+B}{x^2+2x+3} </m> to include all possibilities where the degree of the numerator is less than the degree of the denominator. Suppose 
          <men xml:id="E-PF-3"> \frac{3x^2-1}{(x^2+2x+3)(x-2)}=\frac{Ax+B}{x^2+2x+3}+ \frac{C}{x-2} </men>
          and look for constants <m> A </m>, <m> B</m>, and <m> C</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Multiplying both sides of this equation by the denominator of the left hand side, <m>(x^2+2x+3)(x-2) </m>, we find that 

          <me> 3x^2-1= (Ax+B)(x-2)+ C(x^2+2x+3) </me>

          To find <m> A </m>, <m> B </m>, and <m> C </m>, we will rearrange the right hand side of the equation so that similar terms are grouped. 

          <me>3x^2-1= Ax^2-2Ax + Bx -2B + Cx^2 + 2Cx + 3C </me>

          <me>3x^2+0x-1= (A+C)x^2 + (-2A+B-2C)x + (-2B+3C) </me>

          Like the first example, we need the coefficients for <m> x^2 </m> to be the same on each side of the equation, the coeffiecients for <m> x </m> to be the same on each side of the equation, and the constant terms to be the same on each side of the equation. Thus, we obtain the system of equations
          <me> A+C=3 \ , -2A+B-2C=0 \ , \text{ and } -2B+3C=-1.</me>
          We find that <m> A=2 </m>, <m> B=2 </m>, and <m> C=1 </m>. Thus, using <xref ref="E-PF-3"> Equation </xref>, we can rewrite the original integral as 
          <me>\int \frac{3x^2-1}{(x^2+2x+3)(x-2)} \, dx=\int  \frac{2x+2}{x^2+2x+3}  + \frac{1}{x-2} \, dx</me>

          This integral can be evaluated by using the fact that <m> \int \frac{1}{u} \, du =\ln|u|+C</m> and by using appropriate substitutions, and hence we find that 
          <me>\int \frac{3x^2-1}{(x^2+2x+3)(x-2)} \, dx = \int \frac{2x+2}{x^2+2x+3} \, dx + \int \frac{1}{x-2} \, dx </me>
          <me> =\ln|x^2+2x+3| + \ln|x-2|+C </me>
        </p> 

      </solution>  
    </example> 

    <example>
      <statement> 
      <p> Evaluate  
        <me> \int \frac{-3x^3+9x^2-9x+7}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx.</me>
       </p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
      <p> 
        Before decomposing the integrand into partial fractions, we need to perform polynomial long division because the degree of the numerator, <m> 3</m>, is greater than the degree of the denominator, <m> 2</m>. We need to do this because partial fraction decompsition leads to a sum of rational functions where the degree of the numerator is less than the degree of the denominator. 

      </p>
      
      <p> After completing polynomial long division, we find that   
        <me> 
            \frac{-3x^3+9x^2-9x+7}{-x^2+3x-2}
            = 3x + \frac{7-3x}{-x^2+3x-2} \, ,
        </me>
        hence, we can change the original integral
        <men xml:id="E-PF-4"> 
            \int \frac{-3x^3+9x^2-9x+7}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx
            = \int 3x \, dx + \int \frac{7-3x}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx
        </men>  
      We'll proceed by using the method of partial fraction decomposition on the integrand <m> \frac{7-3x}{-x^2+3x-2} </m>.
      </p>
      <p>
      Notice that the denominator factors as <m> -x^2+3x-2= (x-1)(2-x) </m>, so we'll suppose the integrand decomposes as
      <me> \frac{7-3x}{(x-1)(2-x)}= \frac{A}{x-1}+ \frac{B}{2-x}</me>

      and we'll look for constants <m> A </m> and <m> B </m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Multiplying both sides of the equation by the denominator of the left hand side, <m> (x-1)(2-x)</m>, we find that 
        <me> 7-3x = A(2-x) + B(x-1) </me>

        To find <m> A</m> and <m> B</m>, we will rearrange the right hand side of the equation so that similar terms are grouped.
        <me> 7-3x=2A-Ax+Bx-B </me>
        <me> 7-3x=(B-A)x+(2A-B)</me>

        To make sure the coefficients of <m> x</m> match on each side of the equation and that the constant terms are the same on each side of the equation, we obtain the following system of equations: 
        <me> -3=B-A \text{ and } 7=2A-B</me>

        We find that <m> A=4 </m> and <m> B=1 </m>. Thus, using <xref ref="E-PF-4"> Equation </xref>, we can rewrite the original integral as 
        <me> \int \frac{-3x^3+9x^2-9x+7}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx
            = \int 3x \, dx + \int \frac{7-3x}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx 
        </me>
        <me> 
          = \int 3x \, dx + \int \frac{4}{x-1} + \frac{1}{2-x} \, dx 
        </me> 
        These integrals can be evaluated by using the antidifferentiation rules from <xref ref="T-4-4-Act2_2"> Table </xref> and using appropriate substitutions, and hence we find that 
        <me> \int \frac{-3x^3+9x^2-9x+7}{-x^2+3x-2} \, dx = \int 3x \, dx + \int \frac{4}{x-1}\, dx + \int \frac{1}{2-x} \, dx</me>
        <me>=\frac{3}{2}x^2 + 4\ln|x-1| - \ln|2-x|+C </me> 
      </p>  
    </solution>  
    </example> 
    <p>
      These examples have demonstrated how to use the method of partial fraction decomposition in different situations including when the demoninator of a rational function is a product of distinct linear factors, when there is a repeated linear factor in the denominator, when there is an irreducible quadratic factor in the denominator, and when the degree of the numerator is greater than the degree of the denominator. 
     
    <assemblage>
      <title> Method of Partial Fraction Decomposition for a Rational Function <m> R(x)=\frac{P(x)}{Q(x)} </m> </title>
      <p> 
        Note: This method works best on rational functions when <m> Q(x)</m> can be factored into linear and irreducible quadratic terms. 
        <ul> 
          <li>
            <p> If the degree of <m> P(x) </m> is greater than or equal to the degree <m> Q(x) </m>, then perform polynomial long division to calculate <m> \frac{P(x)}{Q(x)}</m>, else move on to the next step. The result gives a new way to write <m>R(x)</m>. We know that <m> R(x)= S(x)+ \frac{P_2(x)}{Q(x)} </m> where <m> S(x) </m> is the quotient of the polynomial long division and <m> P_2 (x) </m> is the remainder of the polynomial long division. Now the degree of <m> P_2(x) </m> is less than the degree of <m> Q(x) </m>, so follow the remaining steps to decompose <m> \frac{P_2(x)}{Q(x)}</m> . </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p> If the degree of <m> P(x) </m> is less than the degree of <m> Q(x)</m>, then factor <m> Q(x) </m> and add a partial fraction for the decomposition based on the following rules: 
              <ul>
                <li>
                  <p> For each distinct linear factor <m> (x-c)</m> of <m> Q(x) </m>, add 
                    <me> \frac{A}{x-c}.</me>
                   </p>
                 </li>
                 <li>
                  <p> For each repeated linear factor <m> (x-c)^n</m> of <m> Q(x)</m> where <m> n </m> is a positive whole number, add 
                    <me> \frac{A_1}{x-c} + \frac{A_2}{(x-c)^2} + \cdots + \frac{A_n}{(x-c)^n}.</me>
                  </p>  
                 </li> 
                 <li>
                  <p> For each irreducible quadratic factor <m> t(x) </m> of <m> Q(x) </m>, add 
                  <me> \frac{Ax+B}{t(x)}. </me>
                  </p>  
                 </li> 
                 <li>
                  <p> For each repeated irreducible quadratic factor <m> t(x)^n </m> of <m> Q(x) </m> where <m> n </m> is a positive whole number, add 
                  <me> \frac{A_1x+B_1}{t(x)} + \frac{A_2x+B_2}{t(x)^2} + \cdots + \frac{A_nx+B_n}{t(x)^n}.</me>
                  </p>  
                 </li> 
              </ul>  
          </p>
          </li>  
        </ul>  
      </p>
    </assemblage>  
    </p> 
    <p>
     The smaller blocks, or partial fraction terms, that <m> R(x) </m> is broken into often leads to more manageable antidifferentiation. For example if <m> A </m> and <m> k </m> are real numbers, then <m> \int \frac{A}{x-k} \, dx = A \ln |x-k| + C</m> by using the substitution <m> u=x-k </m>. We also know the antiderivative of other common partial fractions like <m> \int \frac{A}{x^2+1} \, dx= \arctan(x) + C </m>. 
     </p>
     
     <p> In many cases, partial fraction decomposition helps the process of finding algebraic antiderivatives. However, there are still some cases where we must find the antiderivative of rational functions like 
      <me> \int \frac{1}{x^2+4x+13} \, dx </me>
      for which we still need to develop different tools to find an algebraic antiderivative. The topic of <xref ref="Trig-Sub"> Trigonometric Substitutions </xref> will allow us to tackle antiderivatives of some ill-behaved functions.
    </p>  
    
<example xml:id="act-5-5-1" permid="TTE">
  
    <p permid="byd">
      For each of the following problems,
      evaluate the integral by finding the partial fraction decomposition of each integrand.

      <ol label="a." permid="LFl">
        <li permid="rMu">
          <statement>
          <p permid="Nuy">
            <m>\int \frac{1}{x^2 - 2x - 3} \, dx</m>
          </p>
          </statement>
          <hint>
            <p> The partial fraction decomposition of the integrand has the form 
              <me> \frac{1}{x^2-2x-3}=\frac{A}{x-3}+\frac{B}{x+1}</me>.
            </p>  
          </hint>
          <answer> 
            <p> 
              <me>\int \frac{1}{x^2 - 2x - 3} \, dx = \frac{1}{4}\ln|x-3| - \frac{1}{4}\ln|x+1| + C</me>.
            </p>  
          </answer> 
          <solution>
            <p permid="qHb">
              To use partial fraction decomposition on the integrand, we'll assume that 
              <me> \frac{1}{x^2-2x-2}=\frac{1}{(x-3)(x+1)}=\frac{A}{x-3}+ \frac{B}{x+1} </me>
              To solve for <m> A </m> and <m> B</m>, we'll multiply both sides of the equation by the denominator of the left side of the equation and rearrange like the earlier exmaples. We'll have the following sequence of steps: 
              <me> 1=A(x+1) + B(x-3) </me>
              <me> 1=(A+B)x + (A-3B)</me>
              We know that 
              <me> A+B=0 \, \text{ and } A-3B=1, </me>
              so <m> A=1/4 </m> and <m> B=-1/4 </m>. This implies that 
            <me>\int \frac{1}{x^2 - 2x - 3} \, dx = \int \frac{1/4}{x-3} - \frac{1/4}{x+1} \, dx </me>
            <me> = \frac{1}{4}\ln|x-3| - \frac{1}{4}\ln|x+1| + C</me>.
          </p>
          </solution> 
        </li>

        <li permid="XTD">
          <statement>
          <p permid="tBH">
            <m>\int \frac{x^2+1}{x^3 - x^2} \, dx</m>
          </p>
          </statement>
          <hint> 
            <p> 
              The partial fraction decomposition of the integrand has the form
              <me>\frac{x^2+1}{x^3-x^2}=\frac{A}{x} + \frac{B}{x^2} + \frac{C}{x-1} </me>
            </p>  
          </hint>
          <answer>
            <p permid="esJ">
            <me>\int \frac{x^2+1}{x^3 - x^2} \, dx = -\ln|x| + x^{-1} + 2\ln|x-1| + C</me>.
          </p>
          </answer>
          <solution>
            <p permid="WOk">
              To use partial fraction decomposition on the integrand, we'll assume that 
              <me> \frac{x^2+1}{x^3-x^2}=\frac{x^2+1}{x^2(x-1)}=\frac{A}{x}+ \frac{B}{x^2}+ \frac{C}{x-1} </me>
              To solve for <m> A </m>, <m> B</m>, and <m> C </m>, we'll multiply both sides of the equation by the denominator of the left side of the equation and rearrange like the earlier exmaples. We'll have the following sequence of steps: 
              <me> x^2+1=Ax(x-1) + B(x-1) + Cx^2 </me>
              <me> x^2+0x+1=(A+C)x^2 +(B-A)x+ (-B)</me>
              We know that 
              <me> A+C=1 \ , B-A=0 \ , \text{ and } -B=1, </me>
              so <m> A=-1 </m>, <m>B=-1</m>, and <m>C=2</m>. This implies that
            <me>\int \frac{x^2+1}{x^3 - x^2} \, dx = \int\left(-\frac{1}{x} - \frac{1}{x^2} + \frac{2}{x-1} \right) \, dx </me>
            <me>= -\ln|x| + x^{-1} + 2\ln|x-1| + C</me>.
          </p>
          </solution>  
        </li>

        <li permid="EaM">
          <statement>
          <p permid="ZIQ">
            <m>\int \frac{x-2}{x^4 + x^2}\, dx</m>
          </p>
          </statement>
          <hint>
            <p> 
              The partial fraction decomposition of the integrand has the form 
              <me>\frac{x-2}{x^4+x^2}=\frac{A}{x} + \frac{B}{x^2} + \frac{Cx+D}{x^2+1} </me>
            </p>  
          </hint>
          <answer>
            <p permid="KzS">
            <me>\int \frac{x-2}{x^4 + x^2}\, dx = \ln|x| + 2x^{-1} - \frac{1}{2} \ln|1+x^2| + 2\arctan(x) + C</me>.
          </p>
          </answer>  
          <solution>
           <p permid="CVt">
            To use partial fraction decomposition on the integrand, we'll assume that 
              <me> \frac{x-2}{x^4+x^2}=\frac{x-2}{x^2(x^2+1)}=\frac{A}{x}+ \frac{B}{x^2} + \frac{Cx+D}{x^2+1} </me>
              To solve for <m> A </m>, <m> B</m>, <m>C</m>, and <m>D</m>, we'll multiply both sides of the equation by the denominator of the left side of the equation and rearrange like the earlier exmaples. We'll have the following sequence of steps: 
              <me> x-2=Ax(x^2+1) + B(x^2+1) + (Cx+D)x^2 </me>
              <me> x-2=(A+C)x^3 + (B+D)x^2 + Ax+ B</me>
              We know that 
              <me> A+C=0 \ , B+D=0 \ , A=1 \text{ and } B=-2, </me>
              so <m> A=1 </m>, <m> B=-2 </m>, <m>C=-1</m>, and <m>D=2</m>. 
              Observing that <m>\frac{-x+2}{1+x^2} = \frac{-x}{1+x^2}+\frac{2}{1+x^2}</m>,
            it now follows that
            <me permid="HFm">
              \int \frac{x-2}{x^4 + x^2}\, dx = \int \frac{1}{x} - \frac{2}{x^2} - \frac{x}{1+x^2} + \frac{2}{1+x^2} \, dx
            </me>.
            Noting that <m>\int \frac{x}{1+x^2} \, dx</m> can be evaluated by the <m>u</m>-substitution <m>u=1+x^2</m>,
            we see that <m>\int \frac{x}{1+x^2} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \ln(1+x^2) + C</m>.
            Thus
            <me permid="nMv">
              \int \frac{x-2}{x^4 + x^2}\, dx = \int \frac{1}{x} - \frac{2}{x^2} - \frac{x}{1+x^2} + \frac{2}{1+x^2} \, dx </me>
            <me> = \ln|x| + 2x^{-1} - \frac{1}{2} \ln(1+x^2) + 2\arctan(x) + C
            </me>.
          </p> 
          </solution>  
        </li>
        <li>
          <statement>
            <p>
              <m> \int \frac{4x^2+x}{2x^2+x-1} \, dx</m>              
            </p>
          </statement>
          <hint>
            <p>First, use polynomial long division then the partial fraction decomposition of the remainder will have the form <m>\frac{A}{2x-1}+\frac{B}{x+1}</m>. </p>
          </hint>
          <answer>
            <p>
              <m>\int \frac{4x^2+x}{2x^2+x-1} \, dx=2x + \frac{1}{2} \ln|2x-1|-\ln|x+1|+C</m>
            </p>
          </answer>
          <solution>
            <p>
              First, use polynomial long division since the degree of the numerator is the same as the degree of the denominator. We'll find that 
              <me>\frac{4x^2+x}{2x^2+x-1} = 2 + \frac{2-x}{2x^2+x-1}.</me>
              To use partial fraction decomposition on the remainder, we'll assume that 
              <me> \frac{2-x}{2x^2+x-1}=\frac{2-x}{(2x-1)(x+1)}=\frac{A}{2x-1}+ \frac{B}{x+1}</me>
              To solve for <m> A </m> and <m> B</m>, we'll multiply both sides of the equation by the denominator of the left side of the equation and rearrange like the earlier exmaples. We'll have the following sequence of steps: 
              <me> 2-x=A(x+1) + B(2x-1) </me>
              <me> 2-x=(A+2B)x + (A-B)</me>
              We know that 
              <me> A+2B=-1 \, \text{ and } A-B=2, </me>
              so <m> A=1 </m> and <m>B=-1</m>. This implies that
            <me>\int \frac{4x^2+x}{2x^2+x-1} \, dx = \int\left(2 + \frac{1}{2x-1} - \frac{1}{x+1} \right) \, dx </me>
            <me>= 2x + \frac{1}{2}\ln|2x-1|-\ln|x+1| + C</me>.
            </p>
          </solution>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </example>
</subsection>
  
  
<subsection xmlid="Trig-Sub">
  <title>Trigonometric Substitutions</title>
  <idx><h>trig subs</h></idx>
  <p>
    Intro: how can we handle integrands like <m> \frac{1}{x^2+4x+13} </m>? We can complete the square to put it in the form <m> \frac{1}{(x+2)^2 + 9} </m>. Now, it is in a form that looks similar to the derivative of <m> \arctan(x+2) </m>. How can we show <m> \int \frac{1}{1+x^2} \, =\arctan(x) +C </m> and <m>\int\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \, dx =\arcsin(x) + C</m> without using the corresponding differentiation rules? These differentiation rules are covered in section 2.6. We'll introduce a new substitution style that introduces trigonometric functions so that we can leverage Pythagoren's Identity and a modified version of Pythagorean's Identity. The new tools we are adding to find algebraic antiderivatives are the substitutions <m> x=a\sin(\theta) </m> and <m>x=a\tan(\theta) </m> where <m> a </m> is a real number. 
  </p>
  
  <assemblage><title> Key Trigonometric Identities </title>
    <p> 
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Pythagorean's Identity:
           <me> \sin^2(\theta) + \cos^2(\theta)=1  </me>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p> Modified Pythagorean's Identity: (It can be found by starting with Pythagorean's Identity then dividing by <m> \cos^2(\theta) </m> on both sides of the equation)
            <me> \tan^2(\theta) + 1=\sec^2(\theta) </me>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </assemblage>
  <p>
    First, let's look at the substitution <m> x=a\sin(\theta) </m> where <m>-\frac{\pi}{2}\leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2}</m> <fn> <xref ref="E-TS-1"> Example </xref> will show why we need these bounds on <m> \theta </m> </fn> and <m> a </m> is a real number and see how it can be used to find the antiderivative of <m> \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} </m>. 
    <example xml:id="E-TS-1">
      <p> 
        Use the substitution <m>x=\sin(\theta) </m> where <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m> to find the general antiderivative 
        <me>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}\, dx.</me>
      </p>
      <p>
        When using the substitution <m> x=\sin(\theta) </m> where <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m>, we are regarding <m> x </m> as a function of <m> \theta </m>. The goal is to change the integrand to contain trigonometric functions so that Pythagorean's Identity can be used. To do this, the integral will be changed to be in terms of the variable <m> \theta</m>. With this in mind, both <m> x </m> and <m> dx </m> will need to be changed. Starting from <m> x=\sin(\theta) </m>, take the derivative with respect to <m> \theta </m> to find that 
        <me> \frac{dx}{d\theta}=\cos(\theta) .</me>
        In other words, <m> dx=\cos(\theta) \, d\theta </m>. Now, change the original integral to be in terms of the variable <m> \theta </m>: 
        <me> \int\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}\, dx=\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{1-\sin^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta  </me>
        Use Pythagorean's Identity, <m>1-\sin^2(\theta)=\cos^2(\theta)</m> to simplify the denominator of the integrand:
        <me> \int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{1-\sin^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta = \int\frac{\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{\cos^2(\theta)}} \, d \theta.</me>
        Now we need to use the assumption that <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2}</m>. In general, <m>\sqrt{\cos^2(\theta)}=|\cos(\theta)|</m>, but <m>\cos(\theta)\geq 0</m> on the interval <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2}</m>. Thus, <m> |\cos(\theta)|=\cos(\theta)</m> if <m> -\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m>. The denominator can now be further simplified, and the remaining steps lead to a familar antiderivative: 
        <md>
          <mrow>\int\frac{\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{\cos^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta \amp = \int\frac{\cos(\theta)}{|\cos(\theta)|} \, d\theta </mrow>
          <mrow> \amp =\int\frac{\cos(\theta)}{\cos(\theta)} \, d\theta </mrow>
          <mrow> \amp =\int 1 \, d\theta </mrow>
          <mrow> \amp =\theta + C</mrow>
        </md>   
        While we have computed an antiderivative successfully, we aren't quite done yet because the answer is not written in terms of the original variable <m> x </m>. Rearrange the substitution equation <m>x=\sin(\theta) </m> to find that <m> \theta=\arcsin(x) </m> and use this to turn <m> \theta</m> back into <m> x </m>. Therefore, 
        <me> \int\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \, dx= \arcsin(x) + C </me>
      </p>
    </example> 
    From now on, we'll usually omit the explanation that <m> \sqrt{\cos^2(\theta)}=|\cos(\theta)|=\cos(\theta)</m> since we additionally assume that <m> -\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m> in order to force <m> \cos(\theta) \geq 0 </m>. It is still incredibly important so that the calculation of the antiderivative is seamless, but since we always assume that <m> -\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \frac{\pi}{2} </m> the same reasoning always applies. 
  </p>
  <p>
    The style of substitution that was demonstrated in the previous example can be extended to help find more algebraic antiderivatives especially when the integrand contains <m> a^2-u^2 </m> where <m> a </m> is a real number and <m> u </m> is a variable. The changes that will be made to the substitution are necessary so that Pythagorean's Identity can still be applied. The following examples will explore exactly what alterations should be made to the substitution <m> x=\sin(\theta) </m>.
    <example> 
      <p> 
        <ol label="a.">
          <li>
            <statement>
            <p>
              Use a trigonometric substitution to find the antiderivative of 
              <me>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx</me>
            </p>
            </statement>
            <hint> 
              <p> Use the substitution <m> x=4\sin(\theta) </m> with <m> -\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m>. How does including the factor of <m> 4 </m> affect our ability to use Pythagorean's Identity? </p>
            </hint>
            <answer>
              <p> <me>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx= \arcsin\left(\frac{x}{4}\right) + C </me></p>
            </answer>
            <solution>
              <p> 
                Use the substitution <m> x=4\sin(\theta) </m> with <m> -\frac{\pi}{2} \leq \theta \leq \frac{\pi}{2} </m>. Then <m> x^2=16\sin^2(\theta) </m> and <m> dx=4\cos(\theta) d\theta </m>. This implies that 
                <md> 
                  <mrow>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx \amp = \int \frac{4\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{16-16\sin^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta </mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \int \frac{4\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{16(1-\sin^2(\theta))}} \, d\theta</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \int \frac{4\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{16\cos^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \int \frac{4\cos(\theta)}{4\cos(\theta)} \, d\theta</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \int 1 \, d\theta</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \theta + C</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \arcsin\left(\frac{x}{4}\right) + C</mrow>
                </md>
              </p>
            </solution>
          </li>
          <li> 
            <statement>
              <p> 
                It's possible to find the answer to part (a) by using some algebra, a u-sub, and the antidifferentiation rule <m> \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-u^2}} \, du =\arcsin(u) + C</m>. 
                Without using a trigonometric substitution, find the antiderivative of 
                <me>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx</me>
              </p>
            </statement>
            <hint>
              <p> Factor out 16 from the expression inside the square root, so 
                <me> \sqrt{16-x^2}=\sqrt{16(1-\frac{x^2}{16})}=\sqrt{16(1-\frac{x^2}{4^2})}. </me>
              </p>
            </hint>
            <answer>
              <p> <me>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx= \arcsin\left(\frac{x}{4}\right) + C </me></p>
            </answer>
            <solution>
              <p> 
                We'll factor out 16 from the expression inside the square root and continue to rearrange the denominator in preparation of using a substitution: 
                <md> 
                  <mrow>\int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16-x^2}} \, dx \amp = \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16(1-\frac{x^2}{16})}} \, dx </mrow>
                  <mrow> \amp = \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16(1-\frac{x^2}{4^2})}} \, dx</mrow>
                  <mrow> \amp = \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{16(1-\frac{x^2}{4^2})}} \, dx</mrow>
                  <mrow> \amp =\int \frac{1}{4\sqrt{1-(x/4)^2}} \, dx</mrow>
                </md> 
                Use the substitution <m> u=\frac{x}{4} </m>, <m> du= \frac{1}{4} \, dx</m>:
                <md>
                  <mrow> \int \frac{1}{4\sqrt{1-(x/4)^2}} \, dx \amp= \int\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-u^2}} \, du</mrow>
                  <mrow> \amp= \arcsin(u) + C</mrow>
                  <mrow> \amp= \arcsin\left(\frac{x}{4} \right) + C</mrow>
                </md>
              </p>
            </solution>
          </li>  
        </ol>
      </p>
    </example> 
    <p>
      
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
      <p>
        Use a trigonometric substitution to find the antiderivative 
        <me> \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-4x^2}} \, dx.</me>
      </p>
      </statement>
      <hint>
        <p> Notice that <m> \sqrt{9-4x^2}=\sqrt{9-(2x)^2}</m>, so we'll want to replace <m> 2x </m> by an appropriate trigonometric function.</p>
      </hint>
      <answer>
        <p> \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-4x^2}} \, dx=\frac{1}{2} \arcsin \left(\frac{2x}{3}\right) + C </p>
      </answer>
      <solution>
        <p> 
          Compared to the first example, where the substitution <m> x=\sin(\theta) </m> worked, we'll need to make two adjustments so that we can still use Pythagoren's Identity. Since <m> \sqrt{9-4x^2}=\sqrt{9-(2x)^2}</m>, we'll want to substitute <m> 2x=3\sin(\theta) </m> so that we can factor out the 9 and obtain the expression <m> 1-\sin^2(\theta) </m>. Assuming <m> 2x=3\sin(\theta) </m> then <m>(2x)^2=9 \sin^2(\theta)</m> and <m>2 dx=3 \cos(\theta)d\theta</m>.
          <md>
            <mrow> \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-4x^2}} \, dx \amp = \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-(2x)^2}} \, dx</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-(2x)^2}} \, dx</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \int \frac{(3/2)\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{9-9\sin^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{3}{2}\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{\sqrt{9(1-\sin^2(\theta))}} \, d\theta</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{3}{2}\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{3\sqrt{\cos^2(\theta)}} \, d\theta</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{3}{2}\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{3\cos(\theta)} \, d\theta</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{3}{6}\int 1 \, d\theta</mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{1}{2}\theta+ C \</mrow>
          </md>
          We can solve for <m> \theta </m> in our substitution equation to find that the antiderivative is: 
          <me> \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{9-4x^2}} \, dx=\frac{1}{2} \arcsin\left(\frac{2x}{3} \right) + C</me>
        </p>
      </solution>      
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the antiderivative 
          <me> \int \frac{9}{(9-x^2)^{3/2}} \, dx </me>
        </p>
      </statement>
      <hint>
        <p> Use the substitution <m> x=3\sin(\theta) </m> and treat <m> (9-x^2)^{3/2}</m> as <m>((9-x^2)^{1/2})^3 </m>. </p>
      </hint>
      <answer>
        <p> <m> \int \frac{9}{(9-x^2)^{3/2}} \, dx=\dfrac{x}{9-x^2} + C </m></p>
      </answer>
      <solution>
        <p> 
          Use the substitution <m> x=3\sin(\theta) </m>. Then <m>x^2=9\sin^2(\theta)</m> and <m>dx=3\cos(\theta) d\theta</m>. As stated in the hint, we'll use that <m>(9-x^2)^{3/2}=((9-x^2)^{1/2})^3</m> and simplify the inner most set of parentheses before cubing.
          <md>
            <mrow> \int \frac{9}{(9-x^2)^{3/2}} \, dx \amp = \int \frac{9\cdot 3\cos(\theta)}{(9-9\sin^2(\theta))^{3/2}} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = 27\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{(9(1-\sin^2(\theta)))^{3/2}} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = 27\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{9^{3/2}((1-\sin^2(\theta))^{1/2})^3} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \frac{27}{27}\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{((\cos^2(\theta))^{1/2})^3} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp =\int \frac{\cos(\theta)}{(\cos(\theta))^3} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp =\int \frac{1}{\cos^2(\theta)} \, d\theta </mrow>
            <mrow> \amp = \tan(\theta) + C</mrow>
          </md>
        </p>
      </solution>      
    </example>  

  </p>
  
  <assemblage>  
    <p>Blue box item: summarize when and how to use this substitution </p>
  </assemblage>

  <p>
    For <m> x=a\tan(\theta) </m>, 
    -derive <m> \arctan(x) </m> rule
    -example with <m> \frac{1}{a^2+x^2} </m>
    -example with <m> \frac{1}{a^2+u^2} </m> and <m> u=bx </m> and another with <m> u=x-c </m>
    -example that requires substituting for <m> \theta </m> back to <m> x </m> in the answer
  </p> 
  <assemblage>
   <p> Blue box item: summarize when and how to use this substitution </p>
  </assemblage>
  <p>
  Final example with no direction for which trig sub to use. (Throw in "THE" Gateway problem) 
  </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection permid="SMc">
    <title>Using an Integral Table</title>
    <p permid="ZVc">
      Calculus has a long history,
      going back to Greek mathematicians in 400-300 BC. Its main foundations were first investigated and understood independently by Isaac Newton and Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz in the late 1600s,
      making the modern ideas of calculus well over 300 years old.
      It is instructive to realize that until the late 1980s,
      the personal computer did not exist, so calculus
      (and other mathematics)
      had to be done by hand for roughly 300 years.
      In the 21st century, however,
      computers have revolutionized many aspects of the world we live in,
      including mathematics.
      In this section we take a short historical tour to precede discussing the role computer algebra systems can play in evaluating indefinite integrals.
      In particular,
      we consider a class of integrals involving certain radical expressions.
    </p>

    <p permid="Gcl">
      As seen in the short table of integrals found in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>,
      there are many forms of integrals that involve
      <m>\sqrt{a^2 \pm w^2}</m> and <m>\sqrt{w^2 - a^2}</m>.
      These integral rules can be developed using a technique known as
      <em>trigonometric substitution</em> that we choose to omit;
      instead, we will simply accept the results presented in the table.
      To see how these rules are used,
      consider the differences among
      <me permid="mTo">
        \int \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \,dx, \ \ \  \int \frac{x}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \,dx, \ \ \  \text{and}  \ \ \ \int \sqrt{1-x^2} \,dx
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="mju">
      The first integral is a familiar basic one,
      and results in <m>\arcsin(x) + C</m>.
      The second integral can be evaluated using a standard <m>u</m>-substitution with <m>u = 1-x^2</m>.
      The third, however,
      is not familiar and does not lend itself to <m>u</m>-substitution.
    </p>

    <p permid="SqD">
      In <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>, we find the rule
      <me permid="Tax">
        (h) ~  \int \sqrt{a^2 - u^2} \, du = \frac{u}{2}\sqrt{a^2 - u^2} + \frac{a^2}{2} \arcsin \frac{u}{a} + C
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="yxM">
      Using the substitutions <m>a = 1</m> and <m>u = x</m>
      (so that <m>du = dx</m>),
      it follows that
      <me permid="zhG">
        \int \sqrt{1-x^2} \, dx = \frac{x}{2} \sqrt{1-x^2} - \frac{1}{2} \arcsin x + C
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="eEV">
      Whenever we are applying a rule in the table,
      we are doing a <m>u</m>-substitution,
      especially when the substitution is more complicated than setting <m>u = x</m> as in the last example.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="ex-5-5-table-c" permid="roM">
      <statement>
        <p permid="cPI">
          Evaluate the integral
          <me permid="foP">
            \int \sqrt{9 + 64x^2} \, dx
          </me>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="PRw">
        <p permid="TvW">
          Here, we want to use Rule (c) from the table,
          but we now set <m>a = 3</m> and <m>u = 8x</m>.
          We also choose the <q><m>+</m></q> option in the rule.
          With this substitution,
          it follows that <m>du = 8dx</m>,
          so <m>dx = \frac{1}{8} du</m>.
          Applying the substitution,
          <me permid="LvY">
            \int \sqrt{9 + 64x^2} \, dx = \int \sqrt{9 + u^2} \cdot \frac{1}{8} \, du = \frac{1}{8} \int \sqrt{9+u^2} \, du
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="zDf">
          By Rule (c), we now find that
          <md permid="rDh">
            <mrow>\int \sqrt{9 + 64x^2} \, dx =\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{8} \left( \frac{u}{2}\sqrt{u^2 + 9} + \frac{9}{2}\ln|u + \sqrt{u^2 + 9}| + C \right)</mrow>
            <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{8} \left( \frac{8x}{2}\sqrt{64x^2 + 9} + \frac{9}{2}\ln|8x + \sqrt{64x^2 + 9}| + C \right)</mrow>
          </md>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p permid="KMe">
      Whenever we use a <m>u</m>-subsitution in conjunction with <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>, it's
      important that we not forget to address any constants that arise and include them in our computations,
      such as the <m>\frac{1}{8}</m> that appeared in <xref ref="ex-5-5-table-c">Example</xref>.
    </p>

<example xml:id="act-5-5-2" permid="OOm">
  <statement>
    <p permid="xQb">
      For each of the following integrals,
      evaluate the integral using <m>u</m>-substitution and/or an entry from the table found in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>.

      <ol label="a." cols="2" permid="kRP">
        <li permid="QYY">
          <p permid="LjM">
            <m>\int \sqrt{x^2 + 4} \, dx</m>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="xgh">
          <p permid="rqV">
            <m>\int \frac{x}{\sqrt{x^2 +4}} \, dx</m>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="dnq">
          <p permid="Xye">
            <m>\int \frac{2}{\sqrt{16+25x^2}}\, dx</m>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Juz">
          <p permid="DFn">
            <m>\int \frac{1}{x^2 \sqrt{49-36x^2}} \, dx</m>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint permid="Mpf">
    <p permid="RIS">
      <ol label="a." permid="EKG">
        <li permid="pBI">
          <p permid="jMw">
            Compare <m>\int \sqrt{u^2 + a^2} \, du</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="VIR">
          <p permid="PTF">
            Try a straightforward <m>u</m>-substitution;
            the table is unneeded.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="BQa">
          <p permid="waO">
            Let <m>a = 4</m> and <m>u = 5x</m> and look for a similar integral in the table.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="hXj">
          <p permid="chX">
            Let <m>a = 7</m> and <m>u = 6x</m>;
            find a related integral in the table.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer permid="ghW">
    <p permid="lBJ">
      <ol label="a." permid="YDx">
        <li permid="Oes">
          <p permid="Ipg">
            <m>\int \sqrt{x^2 + 4} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \arctan(\frac{x}{2})+C</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ulB">
          <p permid="owp">
            <m>\int \frac{x}{\sqrt{x^2 +4}} \, dx = \sqrt{x^2 + 4} + C</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="asK">
          <p permid="UDy">
            <m>\int \frac{2}{\sqrt{16+25x^2}}\, dx = \frac{2}{5} \ln| 5x + \sqrt{16+25x^2} | + C</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="GzT">
          <p permid="AKH">
            <m>\int \frac{1}{x^2 \sqrt{49-36x^2}} \, dx = - \frac{\sqrt{49-36x^2}}{49x} + C</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution permid="AaN">
    <p permid="FuA">
      <ol label="a." permid="swo">
        <li permid="mHc">
          <p permid="gRQ">
            By (1) in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>
            with <m>a=2</m> and <m>u = x</m>,
            <me permid="dXk">
              \int \sqrt{x^2 + 4} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \arctan(\frac{x}{2})+C
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="SOl">
          <p permid="MYZ">
            Let <m>u=x^2 + 4</m>, so <m>du = 2x dx</m>.
            Thus
            <me permid="Ket">
              \int \frac{x}{\sqrt{x^2 +4}} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \int \frac{du}{\sqrt{u}} = \frac{1}{2} \cdot 2u^{1/2} + C = \sqrt{x^2 + 4} + C
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="yVu">
          <p permid="tgi">
            Letting <m>a = 4</m> and <m>u = 5x</m>, we see <m>du=5dx</m>.
            Thus,
            <me permid="qlC">
              \int \frac{2}{\sqrt{16+25x^2}}\, dx = \frac{2}{5} \int \frac{du}{\sqrt{a^2 + u^2}}
            </me>.
            Now by (2) in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>,
            it follows
            <me permid="WsL">
              \int \frac{2}{\sqrt{16+25x^2}}\, dx = \frac{2}{5} \ln| 5x + \sqrt{16+25x^2} | + C
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="fcD">
          <p permid="Znr">
            Letting <m>a = 7</m> and <m>u = 6x</m>,
            it follows <m>x=\frac{1}{6}u</m> and <m>du=6dx</m>,
            and therefore
            <me permid="CzU">
              \int \frac{1}{x^2 \sqrt{49-36x^2}} \, dx = \frac{1}{6} \int \frac{1}{\frac{1}{36}u^2 \sqrt{a^2-u^2}} \, du
            </me>.
            Using (11) in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>
            and the fact that <m>\frac{1}{6} \cdot 36 = 6</m>, we see
            <me permid="iHd">
              \int \frac{1}{x^2 \sqrt{49-36x^2}} \, dx = -6\cdot \frac{\sqrt{49-36x^2}}{49 \cdot 6x} + C
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="yTl">
    <title>Using Computer Algebra Systems</title>
    <p permid="qTn">
      A computer algebra system (CAS) is a computer program that is capable of executing symbolic mathematics.
      For example, if we ask a CAS to solve the equation
      <m>ax^2 + bx + c = 0</m> for the variable <m>x</m>,
      where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are arbitrary constants,
      the program will return <m>x = \frac{-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac}}{2a}</m>.
      Research to develop the first CAS dates to the 1960s, and
      these programs became publicly available in the early 1990s.
      Two prominent examples are the programs
      <em>Maple</em> and <em>Mathematica</em>,
      which were among the first computer algebra systems to offer a graphical user interface.
      Today, <em>Maple</em> and <em>Mathematica</em>
      are exceptionally powerful professional software packages that can execute an amazing array of sophisticated mathematical computations.
      They are also very expensive,
      as each is a proprietary program.
      The CAS <em>SAGE</em> is an open-source,
      free alternative to <em>Maple</em>
      and <em>Mathematica</em>.
    </p>
    
    
    <assemblage> <title> Possibly get rid of this paragraph or embed the command in text below</title>
    <p permid="hzB">
      A computer algebra system such as
      <em>Maple</em>, <em>Mathematica</em>,
      or <em>WolframAlpha</em>
      can be used to find the partial fraction decomposition of any rational function.
      In <em>WolframAlpha</em>, entering
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="vYF">
      <p permid="fKo">
        <c>partial fraction 5x/(x^2-x-2)</c>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="NGK">
      results in the output
      <me permid="GMf">
        \frac{5x}{x^2-x-2} = \frac{10}{3(x-2)} + \frac{5}{3(x+1)}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="tNT">
      We will use technology to generate partial fraction decompositions of rational functions,
      and then evaluate the integrals using established methods.
    </p>
  </assemblage>

    

    <p permid="Xaw">
      For the purposes of this text,
      when we need to use a CAS, we are going to turn instead to a similar,
      but somewhat different computational tool,
      the web-based <q>computational knowledge engine</q>
      called <em>WolframAlpha</em>.
      There are two features of <em>WolframAlpha</em>
      that make it stand out from the CAS options mentioned above: (1) unlike
      <em>Maple</em> and <em>Mathematica</em>,
      <em>WolframAlpha</em> is free (provided we are willing to navigate some pop-up advertising);
      and (2) unlike any of the three,
      the syntax in <em>WolframAlpha</em> is flexible.
      Think of <em>WolframAlpha</em>
      as being a little bit like doing a Google search:
      the program will interpret what is input,
      and then provide a summary of options.
    </p>

    <p permid="DhF">
      If we want to have <em>WolframAlpha</em>
      evaluate an integral for us,
      we can provide it syntax such as
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="cfO">
      <p permid="LRx">
        <c>integrate x^2 dx</c>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="joO">
      to which the program responds with
      <me permid="XKq">
        \int x^2 \, dx = \frac{x^3}{3} + \text{constant}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="PvX">
      While there is much to be enthusiastic about regarding CAS programs such as <em>WolframAlpha</em>,
      there are several things we should be cautious about: (1) a CAS only responds to exactly what is input; (2) a CAS can answer using powerful functions from very advanced mathematics;
      and (3) there are problems that even a CAS cannot do without additional human insight.
    </p>

    <p permid="vDg">
      Although (1) likely goes without saying,
      we have to be careful with our input:
      if we enter syntax that defines the wrong function,
      the CAS will work with precisely the function we define.
      For example, if we are interested in evaluating the integral
      <me permid="DRz">
        \int \frac{1}{16-5x^2} \, dx
      </me>,
      and we mistakenly enter
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="ImX">
      <p permid="rYG">
        <c>integrate 1/16 - 5x^2 dx</c>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="bKp">
      a CAS will (correctly) reply with
      <me permid="jYI">
        \frac{1}{16}x - \frac{5}{3} x^3
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="HRy">
      But if we are sufficiently well-versed in antidifferentiation,
      we will recognize that this function cannot be the one that we seek:
      integrating a rational function such as <m>\frac{1}{16-5x^2}</m>,
      we expect the logarithm function to be present in the result.
    </p>

    <p permid="nYH">
      Regarding (2), even for a relatively simple integral such as <m>\int \frac{1}{16-5x^2} \, dx</m>,
      some CASs will invoke advanced functions rather than simple ones.
      For instance, if we use <em>Maple</em> to execute the command
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="oug">
      <p permid="YfP">
        <c>int(1/(16-5*x^2), x);</c>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="UfQ">
      the program responds with
      <me permid="QfR">
        \int \frac{1}{16-5x^2} \, dx = \frac{\sqrt{5}}{20} \arctanh  (\frac{\sqrt{5}}{4}x)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="AmZ">
      While this is correct
      (save for the missing arbitrary constant,
      which <em>Maple</em> never reports),
      the inverse hyperbolic tangent function is not a common nor familiar one;
      a simpler way to express this function can be found by using the partial fractions method,
      and happens to be the result reported by <em>WolframAlpha</em>:
      <me permid="wna">
        \int \frac{1}{16-5x^2} \, dx = \frac{1}{8\sqrt{5}} \left(\log(4\sqrt{5}+5x) - \log(4\sqrt{5}-5x)\right) + \text{constant}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="gui">
      Using sophisticated functions from more advanced mathematics is sometimes the way a CAS says to the user
      <q>I don't know how to do this problem.</q>
      For example, if we want to evaluate
      <me permid="cuj">
        \int e^{-x^2} \, dx
      </me>,
      and we ask <em>WolframAlpha</em> to do so, the input
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="UBp">
      <p permid="EmY">
        <c>integrate exp(-x^2) dx</c>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="MBr">
      results in the output
      <me permid="IBs">
        \int e^{-x^2} \, dx = \frac{\sqrt{\pi}}{2}\erf  (x) + \text{constant}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="sIA">
      The function <q>erf<m>(x)</m></q>
      is the <em>error function</em>,
          <idx><h>error function</h></idx>
      which is actually defined by an integral:
      <me permid="oIB">
        \erf  (x) = \frac{2}{\sqrt{\pi}} \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \, dt
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="YPJ">
      So, in producing output involving an integral,
      the CAS has basically reported back to us the very question we asked.
    </p>

    <p permid="EWS">
      Finally, as remarked at (3) above,
      there are times that a CAS will actually fail without some additional human insight.
      If we consider the integral
      <me permid="UPK">
        \int (1+x)e^x \sqrt{1+x^2e^{2x}} \, dx
      </me>
      and ask <em>WolframAlpha</em> to evaluate
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="AIy">
      <p permid="kuh">
        <c>int (1+x) * exp(x) * sqrt(1+x^2 * exp(2x)) dx</c>,
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="leb">
      the program thinks for a moment and then reports
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="gPH">
      <p permid="QBq">
        (<em>no result found in terms of standard mathematical functions</em>)
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p permid="Rlk">
      But in fact this integral is not that difficult to evaluate.
      If we let <m>u = xe^{x}</m>,
      then <m>du = (1+x)e^x \, dx</m>,
      which means that the preceding integral has form
      <me permid="AWT">
        \int (1+x)e^x \sqrt{1+x^2e^{2x}} \, dx = \int \sqrt{1+u^2} \, du
      </me>,
      which is a straightforward one for any CAS to evaluate.
    </p>

    <p permid="xst">
      So, we should proceed with some caution:
      while any CAS is capable of evaluating a wide range of integrals
      (both definite and indefinite),
      there are times when the result can mislead us.
      We must think carefully about the meaning of the output,
      whether it is consistent with what we expect,
      and whether or not it makes sense to proceed.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="fau">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="dzC">
      <ul permid="tdZ">
        <li permid="RGJ">
          <p permid="CxL">
            We can antidifferentiate any rational function with the method of partial fractions.
            Any polynomial function can be factored into a product of linear and irreducible quadratic terms,
            so any rational function may be written as the sum of a polynomial plus rational terms of the form <m>\frac{A}{(x-c)^n}</m>
            (where <m>n</m> is a natural number)
            and <m>\frac{Bx+C}{x^2 + k}</m>
            (where <m>k</m> is a positive real number).
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="xNS">
          <p permid="iEU">
            Until the development of compute algebra systems,
            integral tables enabled students of calculus to evaluate integrals such as <m>\int \sqrt{a^2 + u^2} \, du</m>,
            where <m>a</m> is a positive real number.
            A short table of integrals may be found in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="dVb">
          <p permid="OMd">
            Computer algebra systems can play an important role in finding antiderivatives,
            though we must be cautious to use correct input,
            to watch for unusual or unfamiliar advanced functions that the CAS may cite in its result,
            and to consider the possibility that a CAS may need further assistance or insight from us in order to answer a particular question.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"> 

  <exercise xml:id="ez-5-5-WW1" permid="fHx">
    <title>Partial fractions: linear over difference of squares</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap7Sec4/Q57.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-5-5-WW2" permid="LOG">
    <title>Partial fractions: constant over product</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap7Sec4/Q33.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-5-5-WW3" permid="rVP">
    <title>Partial fractions: linear over quadratic</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap7Sec4/Q39.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-5-5-WW5" permid="YcY">
    <title>Partial fractions: cubic over 4th degree</title>
    <webwork source="Library/ma123DB/set3/s7_4_39.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-5-5-WW7" permid="Ekh">
    <title>Partial fractions: quadratic over factored cubic</title>
    <webwork source="Library/ma123DB/set3/s7_4_31.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="krq">
    <statement>
      <p permid="fVS">
        For each of the following integrals involving rational functions, (1) use a CAS to find the partial fraction decomposition of the integrand; (2) evaluate the integral of the resulting function without the assistance of technology; (3) use a CAS to evaluate the original integral to test and compare your result in (2).

        <ol label="a." permid="SnM">
          <li permid="KJn">
            <p permid="mQx">
              <m>\int \frac{x^3 + x + 1}{x^4 - 1} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="qQw">
            <p permid="SXG">
              <m>\int \frac{x^5 + x^2 + 3}{x^3 - 6x^2 + 11x - 6} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="WXF">
            <p permid="zeP">
              <m>\int \frac{x^2 - x - 1}{(x-3)^3} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="IUa">
      <p permid="nAr">
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="cMR">
      <p permid="veQ">
        <ol label="a." permid="NDT">
          <li permid="DeO">
            <p permid="flY">
              Wolfram|Alpha shows that
              <me permid="Yrt">
                \frac{x^3 + x + 1}{x^4 - 1} = -\frac{1}{2(x^2+1)} + \frac{1}{4(x+1)} + \frac{3}{4(x-1)}
              </me>.
              Then, using standard antiderivatives,
              <md permid="kFL">
                <mrow>\int \frac{x^3 + x + 1}{x^4 - 1} \, dx &amp;= \int -\frac{1}{2(x^2+1)} + \frac{1}{4(x+1)} + \frac{3}{4(x-1)} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \int -\frac{1}{2(x^2+1)} \ dx + \int \frac{1}{4(x+1)} \ dx + int \frac{3}{4(x-1)} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= -\frac{1}{2} \arctan(x) + \frac{1}{4} \ln|x+1| + \frac{3}{4} \ln|x-1| + C</mrow>
              </md>
              Directly asking Wolfram|Alpha to integrate <m>\frac{x^3 + x + 1}{x^4 - 1}</m> yields
              <me permid="EyC">
                \int \frac{x^3 + x + 1}{x^4 - 1} \, dx = \frac{1}{4} \left( 3\log(1-x) + \log(x+1) - 2\arctan{x} \right) + C
              </me>.
              By rearranging, distributing the <m>\frac{1}{4}</m>,
              and noticing that Wolfram|Alpha does not use absolute value with integrals involving the logarithm
              (as well as that <m>|x-1| = |1-x|</m>),
              we see that these two results are the same.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="jlX">
            <p permid="Lth">
              Wolfram|Alpha shows that
              <me permid="QMU">
                \frac{x^5 + x^2 + 3}{x^3 - 6x^2 + 11x - 6} = x^2 + 6x + 25 + \frac{255}{2(x-3)} - \frac{39}{x-2} + \frac{5}{2(x-1)}
              </me>.
              Then, using standard antiderivatives,
              <md permid="wUd">
                <mrow>\int \frac{x^5 + x^2 + 3}{x^3 - 6x^2 + 11x - 6} \, dx &amp;= \int x^2 + 6x + 25 + \frac{255}{2(x-3)} - \frac{39}{x-2} + \frac{5}{2(x-1)} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \int x^2 \ dx + \int 6x \ dx + \int 25 \ dx + \int \frac{255}{2(x-3)} \ dx - \int \frac{39}{x-2} \ dx + \int \frac{5}{2(x-1)} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \frac{x^3}{3} + 3x^2 + 25x + \frac{255}{2} \ln|x-3| - 39 \ln|x-2| + \frac{5}{2} \ln|x-1| + C</mrow>
              </md>.
              Directly asking Wolfram|Alpha to integrate
              <m>\frac{x^5 + x^2 + 3}{x^3 - 6x^2 + 11x - 6}</m> yields the same result with the caveats mentioned in part (a).
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="Ptg">
            <p permid="rAq">
              Wolfram|Alpha shows that
              <me permid="dbm">
                \frac{x^2 - x - 1}{(x-3)^3} = \frac{1}{x-3} + \frac{5}{(x-3)^2} + \frac{5}{(x-3)^3}
              </me>.
              Then, using standard antiderivatives,
              <md permid="VwN">
                <mrow>\int \frac{x^2 - x - 1}{(x-3)^3} \, dx &amp;= \int \frac{1}{x-3} + \frac{5}{(x-3)^2} + \frac{5}{(x-3)^3} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \int \frac{1}{x-3} \ dx + \int \frac{5}{(x-3)^2} \ dx + \int \frac{5}{(x-3)^3} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \ln|x-3| + \int 5(x-3)^{-2} \ dx + \int 5(x-3)^{-3} \ dx</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp;= \ln|x-3| - \frac{5}{x-3} - \frac{5}{2(x-3)^2} + C</mrow>
              </md>.
              Directly asking Wolfram|Alpha to integrate <m>\frac{x^2 - x - 1}{(x-3)^3}</m> yields
              <me permid="Jiv">
                \int \frac{x^2 - x - 1}{(x-3)^3} \, dx = \log(x-3) - \frac{5(2x-5)}{2(x-3)^2} + C
              </me>.
              The logarithm part is the same, and since
              <me permid="ppE">
                -\frac{5}{x-3} - \frac{5}{2(x-3)^2}  = -\frac{5[2(x-3) + 1]}{2(x-3)^2} = -\frac{5(2x-5)}{2(x-3)^2}
              </me>,
              we see that the rest of the result matches as well.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="Qyz">
    <statement>
      <p permid="Mdb">
        For each of the following integrals involving radical functions, (1) use an appropriate <m>u</m>-substitution along with <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>
        to evaluate the integral without the assistance of technology,
        and (2) use a CAS to evaluate the original integral to test and compare your result in (1).

        <ol label="a." permid="yuV">
          <li permid="vAp">
            <p permid="XHz">
              <m>\int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="bHy">
            <p permid="DOI">
              <m>\int x \sqrt{1 + x^4} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="HOH">
            <p permid="jVR">
              <m>\int e^x \sqrt{4 + e^{2x}} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="nVQ">
            <p permid="Qda">
              <m>\int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx</m>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="Vis">
      <p permid="THA">
        <ol label="a." permid="FZu">
          <li permid="UcZ">
            <p permid="wkj">
              <m>
              \int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx = -\frac{1}{5} \ln \left| \frac{5+\sqrt{9x^2 + 5^2}}{3x} \right| + C</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="Aki">
            <p permid="crs">
              <m>
              \int x \sqrt{1 + x^4} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \left( \frac{x^2}{2}\sqrt{x^4 + 1} + \frac{1}{2}\ln|x^2 + \sqrt{x^4 + 1}| \right) + C
              </m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="grr">
            <p permid="IyB">
              <m>
              \int e^x \sqrt{4 + e^{2x}} \, dx = \frac{e^x}{2}\sqrt{e^{2x} + 4} + 2\ln|e^x + \sqrt{e^{2x} + 4}| + C
              </m>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="MyA">
            <p permid="oFK">
              <m>
              \int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx = \frac{1}{3} \ln \left| \frac{3 + \sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}}{\cos(x)} \right| + C</m>.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="pbj">
      <p permid="blZ">
        <ol label="a." permid="tLc">
          <li permid="sFJ">
            <p permid="UMT">
              For <m>\int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx</m>,
              we let <m>u = 3x</m> so <m>du = 3 \, dx</m> and <m>x = \frac{1}{3} u</m>.
              Applying this substitution,
              <me permid="BDW">
                \int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx = \int \frac{3}{u \sqrt{u^2 + 25}} \cdot \frac{1}{3} \, du = \int \frac{1}{u \sqrt{u^2 + 25}} \, du
              </me>.
              Now, using Rule (e) from the appendix with <m>a = 5</m>,
              <me permid="hLf">
                \int \frac{1}{u \sqrt{u^2 + 25}} \, du = -\frac{1}{5} \ln \left| \frac{5+\sqrt{u^2 + 5^2}}{u} \right| + C
              </me>
              Substituting back to <m>x</m>, we've shown that
              <me permid="NSo">
                \int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx = -\frac{1}{5} \ln \left| \frac{5+\sqrt{9x^2 + 5^2}}{3x} \right| + C
              </me>.
              Asking Wolfram|Alpha to evaluate the same original integral,
              the program reports that
              <me permid="tZx">
                \int \frac{1}{x \sqrt{9x^2 + 25}} \, dx = \frac{1}{5} \left( \log(x) - \log\left( \sqrt{9x^2 + 25} + 5\right) \right) + C
              </me>.
              These two results are in fact the same
              (the program uses ``<m>\log</m>'' where we use ``<m>\ln</m>''),
              though it takes some work with logarithm properties to show this.
              Using the rule <m>\ln(\frac{u}{v}) = \ln (u) - \ln (v)</m> and
              <m>\ln(3x) = \ln(3) + \ln(x)</m> and including the value <m>\ln(3)</m> in the arbitrary constant of integration,
              it follows that the two results match.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="YMS">
            <p permid="AUc">
              For <m>\int x \sqrt{1 + x^4} \, dx</m>,
              we first recognize that <m>x^4 = (x^2)^2</m>,
              and that with <m>u = x^2</m> we have a function-derivative pair present with <m>du = 2x \, dx</m>.
              Applying this substitution,
              <me permid="agG">
                \int x \sqrt{1 + x^4} \, dx = \int \frac{1}{2} \sqrt{1+u^2} \, du
              </me>.
              Next, we use Rule (c) with ``<m>+</m>'' and <m>a = 1</m> to find that
              <me permid="GnP">
                \int \frac{1}{2} \sqrt{1+u^2} \, du = \frac{1}{2} \left( \frac{u}{2}\sqrt{u^2 + 1} + \frac{1}{2}\ln|u + \sqrt{u^2 + 1}| \right) + C
              </me>
              Returning to the original variable, <m>x</m>, we have
              <me permid="muY">
                \int x \sqrt{1 + x^4} \, dx = \frac{1}{2} \left( \frac{x^2}{2}\sqrt{x^4 + 1} + \frac{1}{2}\ln|x^2 + \sqrt{x^4 + 1}| \right) + C
              </me>
              Wolfram|Alpha's first response when asked to evaluate this integral is to give a result that involves the hyperbolic sine function (<m>\sinh^{-1}(x^2)</m>);
              if we scroll down to ``alternate results'', we find one that matches what we've found above.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="EUb">
            <p permid="hbl">
              For <m>\int e^x \sqrt{4 + e^{2x}} \, dx</m>,
              we first observe that <m>e^{2x} = (e^x)^2</m>.
              If we use the substitution <m>u = e^x</m>, the resulting integral is
              <me permid="SCh">
                \int e^x \sqrt{4 + e^{2x}} \, dx = \int \sqrt{4 + u^2} \, du
              </me>,
              which can be evaluated by the same approach as in part (b) with Rule (c) from the Appendix,
              this time with <m>a = 2</m>.
              Thus,
              <me permid="yJq">
                \int \sqrt{4 + u^2} \, du = \frac{u}{2}\sqrt{u^2 + 4} + \frac{2^2}{2}\ln|u + \sqrt{u^2 + 4}|
              </me>
              Substituting back,
              <me permid="eQz">
                \int e^x \sqrt{4 + e^{2x}} \, dx = \frac{e^x}{2}\sqrt{e^{2x} + 4} + 2\ln|e^x + \sqrt{e^{2x} + 4}|  + C
              </me>
              As in part (b),
              we need to scroll down in Wolfram|Alpha's results to find one close to what we have here.
              The alternate result almost matches, but the program writes
              <me permid="KXI">
                \log(\left( \sqrt{\frac{e^{2x}}{4} + 1 } + \frac{e^{x}}{2} \right)
              </me>
              where we have
              <me permid="reR">
                \ln|e^x + \sqrt{e^{2x} + 4}.|
              </me>
              This discrepancy can be explained using properties of the logarithm function and the presence of the arbitrary constant.
              If we write
              <me permid="Xma">
                \log(\left( \sqrt{\frac{e^{2x}}{4} + 1 } + \frac{e^{x}}{2} \right) = \log(\left( \sqrt{\frac{e^{2x} + 4}{4}} + \frac{e^{x}}{2} \right) = \log(\left( \frac{ \sqrt{e^{2x} + 4} + e^{x}}{2} \right)
              </me>
              and then recall that <m>\log \left( \frac{z}{2} \right) = \log(z) - \log(2)</m>,
              we see that the <m>\log(2)</m> can be included in the arbitray constant,
              and the two different results actually match.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="lbk">
            <p permid="Niu">
              To evaluate the integral <m>\int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx</m>,
              we first write <m>\tan(x) = \frac{\sin(x)}{\cos(x)}</m> to have the integral in the form
              <me permid="Dtj">
                \int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx = \int \frac{\sin(x)}{\cos(x) \sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx
              </me>.
              Next, letting <m>u = \cos(x)</m>,
              it follows <m>du = -\sin(x) \, dx</m>, and therefore
              <me permid="jAs">
                \int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx = \int \frac{-1}{u \sqrt{9 - u^2}} \, du
              </me>.
              By Rule (j) in the appendix, we know that
              <me permid="PHB">
                \int \frac{1}{u \sqrt{9 - u^2}} \, du = -\frac{1}{3} \ln \left| \frac{3 + \sqrt{9 - u^2}}{u} \right| + C
              </me>.
              Connecting the above chain of equalities and substituting back to <m>x</m>,
              we have shown that
              <me permid="vOK">
                \int \frac{\tan(x)}{\sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}} \, dx = \frac{1}{3} \ln \left| \frac{3 + \sqrt{9 - \cos^2(x)}}{\cos(x)} \right| + C
              </me>.
              When Wolfram|Alpha is asked to evaluate the original integral,
              its first result involves the inverse hyperbolic tangent function,
              and the alternate forms are equally complicated.
              It seems that the technology is unable to evaluate this integral in the most straightforward way.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise permid="wFI">
    <statement>
      <p permid="skk">
        Consider the indefinite integral given by
        <me permid="bVT">
          \int \frac{\sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}}{x} \, dx
        </me>.
        <ol label="a." permid="eCe">
          <li permid="Rit">
            <p permid="tpD">
              Explain why <m>u</m>-substitution does not offer a way to simplify this integral by discussing at least two different options you might try for <m>u</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="xpC">
            <p permid="ZwM">
              Explain why integration by parts does not seem to be a reasonable way to proceed, either,
              by considering one option for <m>u</m> and <m>dv</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="dwL">
            <p permid="FDV">
              Is there any line in the integral table in <xref ref="integral-table">Appendix</xref>
              that is helpful for this integral?
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="JDU">
            <p permid="lLe">
              Evaluate the given integral using <em>WolframAlpha</em>.
              What do you observe?
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer permid="hwK">
      <p permid="zOJ">
        <ol label="a." permid="mgD">
          <li permid="pLd">
            <p permid="RSn">
              Try <m>u = 1+x^2</m> or <m>u = x + \sqrt{1+x^2}</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="VSm">
            <p permid="xZw">
              Try <m>u = \sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}</m> and <m>dv = \frac{1}{x} \, dx</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="BZv">
            <p permid="egF">
              No.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="igE">
            <p permid="KnO">
              It appears that the function
              <m>\frac{\sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}}{x}</m> does not have an elementary antiderivative.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution permid="BpB">
      <p permid="Hti">
        <ol label="a." permid="ZSl">
          <li permid="OnN">
            <p permid="quX">
              Looking at the composite functions that are present,
              there are two possible <m>u</m>-substitutions to try.
              One is <m>u = 1+x^2</m>,
              for which <m>du = 2x \, dx</m> and <m>x = \sqrt{u-1}</m>.
              Because there is no <m>x \, dx</m> term present in the integral,
              this substitution will not work.
            </p>

            <p permid="WCg">
              A second subsitution to attempt is letting <m>u = x + \sqrt{1+x^2}</m>,
              for which <m>du = \left(1 + x(1+x^2)^{-1/2} \right) \, dx</m>.
              Here, too, the needed product is not present in the integral in order for the subsitution to work.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="uuW">
            <p permid="CJp">
              For integration by parts to work,
              we normally need a choice of <m>u</m> that is straightforward to differentiate,
              and <m>dv</m> that is straightforward to antidifferentiate.
              Noting that the integrand can really only be written as the product of
              <m>\frac{1}{x}</m> and <m>\sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}</m>,
              it appears that the most natural possible option is to let
              <m>u = \sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}</m> and <m>dv = \frac{1}{x} \, dx</m>,
              since we can antidifferentiate <m>\frac{1}{x}</m>.
              Here, however, the approach stalls,
              because integration by parts requires us to evaluate
              <m>\int v \, du</m>, and that integral is
              <me permid="Idc">
                \int \ln|x| \cdot \frac{1}{2} \left( x + \sqrt{1+x^2} \right)^{-1/2} \cdot \left( 1 + x(1+x^2)^{-1/2} \right) \, dx
              </me>
              which is far more complicated than the already-complicated integral we started with.
              From this it appears that integration by parts will not be productive.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="aCf">
            <p permid="iQy">
              Since we can't seem to find a <m>u</m>-substitution that simplifies the given integral,
              and there are no formulas in the Appendix that use nested square roots,
              it appears that the table doesn't offer any help in evaluating this particular integral.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="GJo">
            <p permid="OXH">
              Wolfram|Alpha returns results that either involve inverse hyperbolic trigonometric functions or complex numbers.
              As such, it appears that the function
              <m>\frac{\sqrt{x+\sqrt{1+x^2}}}{x}</m> does not have an elementary antiderivative that we can find.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

 </exercises>
</section>

