<?xml version="1.0"?>


<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!--   Modeling, Functions, and Graphs   -->
<!--           4th                                     -->
<!-- Copyright (C) Katherine Yoshiwara      -->

<exercises xml:id="section-A-3-exercises"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Exercises A.3</title>

<exercisegroup>
    <introduction><p>Write algebraic expressions to describe each situation and then evaluate for the given values.
    </p></introduction>

    <exercise number="1"><statement>
        <p>Jim was 27 years old when Ana was born.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for Jim's age in terms of Ana's age.</p></li>
            <li><p>Use your expression to find Jim's age when ana is 22 years old.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>j=a+27</m></p></li>
            <li><p>49</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="2"><statement>
        <p>Rani wansts to replace the wheels of her in-line skates. New wheels cost <dollar/>6.59 each.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the total cost of new wheels in terms of the number of wheels Rani must replace.</p></li>
            <li><p>Use your expression to find the total cost if Rani must replace 8 wheels.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="3"><statement>
        <p>Helen decides to drive to visit her father. The trip is a distance of 1260 miles.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the total number of hours Helen must drive in terms of her average driving speed.</p></li>
            <li><p>Use your expression to find how long Helen must drive if she averages 45 miles per hour.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>h=\dfrac{1260}{r} </m></p></li>
            <li><p>28 hours</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="4"><statement>
        <p>Ben will inherit one million dollars on his twenty-first birthday.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the number of years before Ben gets his inheritance in terms of his present age.</p></li>
            <li><p>Use your expression to find how many more years Ben must wait after he turns 13 years old.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
   </exercise>

    <exercise number="5"><statement>
        <p>The area of a circle is equal to <m>\pi</m> times the square of its radius.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the area of a circle in terms of its radius.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the area of a circle whose radius is 5 centimeters.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>A=\pi r^2 </m></p></li>
            <li><p>78.54 sq cm</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="6"><statement>
        <p>The volume of a sphere is equal to <m>\frac{4}{3} \pi</m> times the cube of the radius.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the volume of a sphere in terms of its radius.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the volume of a sphere whose radius is 5 centimeters.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="7"><statement>
        <p>The sales tax in the city of Preston is 7.9<percent/>.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the total bill for an item (price plus tax) in terms of the price of the item.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the total bill for an item whose price is <dollar/>490.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>b=1.079p </m></p></li>
            <li><p><dollar/>528.71</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
     </exercise>

    <exercise number="8"><statement>
        <p>A savings account pays 6.4<percent/> annual interest on the amount deposited.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the balance (initial deposit plus interest) in the account after one year in terms of the amount deposited. </p></li>
            <li><p>Find the total amount in the account after one year if <dollar/>350 was deposited.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="9"><statement>
        <p>Your best friend moves to another state. To call her, a long-distance phone call costs <dollar/>1.97 plus <dollar/>0.39 for each minute.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the cost of a long-distance phone call in terms of the number of minutes of the call.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the cost of a 27-minute phone call.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>C=1.97+0.39m </m></p></li>
            <li><p><dollar/>12.50</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="10"><statement>
        <p>Arenac Airplines charges 47 cents per pound on its flight from Omer to Pinconning, both for passengers and for luggage. Mr. Owsley wants to take the flight with 15 pounds of luggage.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the cost of the flight in terms of Mr. Owlsley's weight.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the cost if Mr. Owsley weights 162 pounds.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="11"><statement>
        <p>Juan buys a 50-pound bag of rice and consumes about 0.4 pound per week.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the amount of rice Juan has consumed in terms of the number of weeks since he bought the bag.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression for the amount of rice Juan has left in terms of the number of weeks since he bought the bag.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find the amount of rice Juan has left after 6 weeks.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>c=0.4w </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>r=50-0.4w</m></p></li>
            <li><p>47.6 lbs</p></li>
        </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="12"><statement>
        <p>Trinh is bicycling down a mountain road that loses 500 feet in elevation for each 1 mile of road. She started at an elevation of 6300 feet.
            <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Write an expression for the elevation that Trinh has lost in terms of the distance she has cycled.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression for Trinh's elevation in terms of the number of miles she has cycled.</p></li>
            <li><p>Find Trinh's elevation after she has cycled 9 miles.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

</exercisegroup>



<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Write and solve an equation to answer the question.</p>
</introduction>

    <exercise number="13"><statement><p>Celine's boutique carries a line of jewelry made by a local artists' co-op. If Celine charges <m>p</m> dollars for a pair of earrings, she finds that she can sell <m>200 - 5p</m> pairs per month. On the other hand, the co-op will provide her with <m>56 + 3p</m> pairs of earrings when she charges <m>p</m> dollars per pair. What price should Celine charge so that the demand for earrings will equal her supply?</p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p><dollar/>18</p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="14"><statement><p>Curio Electronics sells garage door openers. If it charges <m>p</m> dollars per unit, it sells <m>120 - p</m> openers per month. The manufacturer will supply <m>20 + 2p</m> openers at a price of <m>p</m> dollars each. What price should Curio Electronics charge so that its monthly supply will meet its demand?</p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="15"><statement><p>Roger sets out on a bicycle trip at an average speed of 16 miles per hour. Six hours later, his wife finds his patch kit on the dining room table. If she heads after him in the car at 45 miles per hour, how long will it be before she catches him?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the distance Roger's wife drives.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the distance Roger has cycled.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p>
        <ol label="a" cols="2">
                <li><p><m>t=\text{time wife drives} </m></p></li>
                <li><p><m>45t</m></p></li>
                <li><p><m>16(t+6) </m></p></li>
                <li><p>3.3 hours</p></li>
            </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="16"><statement><p>Kate and Julie set out in their sailboat on a straight course at 9 miles per hour. Two hours later, their mother becomes worried and sends their father after them in the speedboat. If their father travels at 24 miles per hour, how long will it be before he catches them?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the distance Kate and Julie sailed.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the distance their father traveled.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="17"><statement><p>The reprographics department has a choice of 2 new copying machines. One sells for <dollar/>20,000 and costs <dollar/>0.02 per copy to operate. The other sells for <dollar/>17,500, but its operating costs are <dollar/>0.025 per copy. The repro department decides to buy the more expensive machine. How many copies must the repro department make before the higher price is justified?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the total cost incurred by each machine.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p>
        <ol label="a" cols="2">
                <li><p><m>n=\text{number of copies} </m></p></li>
                <li><p><m>20,000+0.02n </m>, <m>17,500+0.025m</m></p></li>
                <li><p>500,000 copies</p></li>
            </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="18"><statement><p>Annie needs a new refrigerator and can choose between two models of the same size. One model sells for <dollar/>525 and costs <dollar/>0.08 per hour to run. A more energy-efficient model sells for <dollar/>700 but runs for <dollar/>0.05 per hour. If Annie buys the more expensive model, how long will it be before she starts saving money?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an expression in terms of your variable for the total cost incurred by each refrigerator.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="19"><statement><p>The population of Midland has been growing at an annual rate of 8<percent/> over the past 5 years. Its present population is 135,000.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Assuming the same rate of growth, what do you predict for the population of Midland next year?</p></li>
            <li><p>What was the population of Midland last year?</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p>
        <ol label="a" cols="2">
                <li><p>145,800</p></li>
                <li><p>125,000</p></li>
            </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="20"><statement><p>For the past 3 years, the annual inflation rate has been 6<percent/>. This year, a steak dinner at Benny's costs <dollar/>12.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Assuming the same rate of inflation, what do you predict for the price of a steak dinner next year?</p></li>
            <li><p>What did a steak dinner cost last year?</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="21"><statement><p>Virginia took a 7<percent/> pay cut when she changed jobs last year. What percent pay increase must she receive this year in order to match her old salary of <dollar/>24,000?</p>
    </statement>
    <hint><p>What was Virginia's salary after the pay cut?</p></hint>
    <answer><p>7.53<percent/></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="22"><statement><p>Clarence W. Networth took a 16<percent/> loss in the stock market last year. What percent gain must he realize this year in order to restore his original holdings of <dollar/>85,000?</p>
    </statement>
    <hint><p>What was the value of Clarence's stock holdings after the loss?</p></hint>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="23"><statement><p>Delbert's test average in algebra is 77. If the final exam counts for 30<percent/> of the grade and the test average counts for 70<percent/>, what must Delbert score on the final exam to have a term average of 80?</p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p>87</p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="24"><statement><p>Harold’s batting average for the first 8 weeks of the baseball season is 0.385. What batting average must he maintain over the last 18 weeks so that his season average will be 0.350 (assuming he continues the same number of at-bats per week)?</p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="25"><statement><p>A horticulturist needs a fertilizer that is 8<percent/> potash, but she can find only fertilizers that contain 6<percent/> and 15<percent/> potash. How much of each should she mix to obtain 10 pounds of 8<percent/> potash fertilizer?</p>
    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
        <row>
            <cell>Pounds of fertilizer</cell>
            <cell><percent/> potash</cell>
            <cell>Pounds of potash</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>
    <p><ol label="a">
        <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write algebraic expressions in terms of your variable for the amounts of each fertilizer the horticulturist uses. Use the table.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write expressions for the amount of potash in each batch of fertilizer.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write two different expressions for the amount of potash in the mixture. Now write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
    </ol></p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p><ol label="a">
        <li><p><m>x= </m> amount of 6<percent/> fertilizer</p></li>
        <li><p><m>x</m>; <m>~~10-x</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>0.06x</m>; <m>~~0.15(10-x)</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>0.06x+0.15(10-x)=0.08(10) </m>; <m>7.\overline{7} </m> lbs of 6<percent/>, <m>2.\overline{2} </m> lbs of 15<percent/></p></li>
    </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="26"><statement><p>A sculptor wants to cast a bronze statue from an alloy that is 60<percent/> copper. He has 30 pounds of a 45<percent/> alloy. How much 80<percent/> copper alloy should he mix with it to obtain the 60<percent/> copper alloy?</p>
    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" bottom="minor" left="minor" right="minor">
        <row>
            <cell>Pounds of alloy</cell>
            <cell><percent/> copper</cell>
            <cell>Pounds of copper</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m></m></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>
    <p><ol label="a">
        <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write algebraic expressions in terms of your variable for the amounts of each alloy the sculptor uses. Use the table.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write expressions for the amount of copper in each batch of alloy.</p></li>
        <li><p>Write two different expressions for the amount of copper in the mixture. Now write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
    </ol></p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="27"><statement><p>Lacy's Department Stores wants to keep the average salary of its employees under <dollar/>19,000 per year. If the downtown store pays its 4 managers <dollar/>28,000 per year and its 12 department heads <dollar/>22,000 per year, how much can it pay its 30 clerks?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write algebraic expressions for the total amounts Lacy’s pays its managers, its department heads, and its clerks.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write two different expressions for the total amount Lacy's pays in salaries each year.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    <answer><p>
        <ol label="a" cols="2">
                <li><p><m>x=\text{clerk's salary} </m></p></li>
                <li><p><m>4\times 28,000</m>; <m>~12\times 22,000</m>; <m>~19,000(4+12+x) </m></p></li>
                <li><p><m>4\times 28,000 +12\times 22,000 =19,000(4+12+x) </m>;  <dollar/>16,600</p></li>
                <li><p>3.3 hours</p></li>
            </ol></p></answer>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="28"><statement><p>Federal regulations require that 60<percent/> of all vehicles manufactured next year comply with new emission standards. Major Motors can bring 85<percent/> of its small trucks in line with the standards, but only 40<percent/> of its automobiles. If Major Motors plans to manufacture 20,000 automobiles next year, how many trucks will it have to produce in order to comply with the federal regulations?
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>What are we asked to find in this problem? Assign a variable to represent it.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write algebraic expressions for the number of trucks and the number of cars that will meet emission standards.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write two different expressions for the total number of vehicles that will meet the standards.</p></li>
            <li><p>Write an equation and solve it.</p></li>
        </ol></p>
    </statement>
    </exercise>

</exercisegroup>

</exercises>
