<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-graph-researchers">

<title>Researchers in Graph Theory</title>

<subsection><title>Jacqueline Akinpelu</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/akinpelu-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Akinpelu was in graduate school at Johns Hopkins University when she first encountered “applied mathematics." She completed a dissertation in inventory systems management and in 1980 joined AT/&T Bell Laboratories in Holmdel, NJ, where she worked for 25 years. The projects she worked on included developing new models for planning and managing telephone network call capacity under specific traffic conditions, and developing strategies for maintaining network stability. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/jacqueline-akinpelu/">Mathematically Gifted and Black</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/mX_TNxflzdA">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Christina Eubanks-Turner</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/eubanks-turner-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Christina Eubanks-Turner is an Associate Professor of Mathematics at Loyola Marymount University (LMU), Seaver College of Science and Engineering. She was one of the two first African-American women to earn a Ph.D. in mathematics from the University of Nebraska in 2008. Her academic areas of interest include graph theory, commutative algebra, mathematics education, and mathematical sciences diversification. She is also the Director of the Master’s Program in Teaching Mathematics at LMU. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/christina_eubanks_turner/">Mathematically Gifted and Black</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://vimeo.com/325971646 ">Girsl, Math /& STEM</url></p>

  <p><url href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/ebooks/pdf/LivingProof_WEB.pdf">Living Proof, pg 131</url></p>

  <p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Eubanks-Turner">Wikipedia</url></p>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Christine Kelley</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/kelley-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Christine Kelley is a Professor of Mathematics at UNL and works in coding theory. After receiving her Ph.D. from the University of Notre Dame in 2006, she held postdoctoral research positions at the Fields Institute and The Ohio State University. Her areas of research includes graph-based codes and algorithms, and coding applications such as flash memory storage, data streaming, and communication networks. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://math.unl.edu/christine-kelley">UNL Webpage</url></p>



</subsection>


</section>
