<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-14-1-researchers-modeling">

<title>Researchers in Modeling and Applied Mathematics</title>



<subsection><title>Selenne Bañuelos</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/banuelos-s-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Selenne Bañuelos is an Associate Professor of Mathematics at California State University Channel Islands. Bañuelos was born to Mexican immigrants and raised in East Los Angeles. She earned her Ph.D. in Applied Mathematics from the University of Southern California (USC) in 2013 where she received many awards during her studies. Her research interests are in mathematical modeling of biological systems including epidemiology, the dynamics of sleep, and phage treatment for bacterial infections.</p>

</sidebyside>
	<p><url href="https://www.lathisms.org/calendar-2018/selenne-banuelos">Lathisms Profile</url> (Both a brief biography and Podcast link are available at this site.)</p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Ron Buckmire</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/buckmire-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Ron Buckmire is currently an Associate Dean for Curricular Affairs and Professor of Mathematics at Occidental College in Los Angeles California. He spent four years as a program director at the National Science Foundation where he helped decide what types of programs should be funded to improve mathematics nationwide. He earned his Ph.D. at the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute where he studied computational aerodynamics. He continues to research applications of finite difference and partial differential equations.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/y2X8YMR5Az4">Meet a Mathematician Interview</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/ron-buckmire/">Mathematically Gifted and Black</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Ricardo Cortez</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/cortez-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Ricardo Cortez is a professor of mathematics at Tulane University. He studied both mathematics and mechanical engineering at Arizona State University before earning his Ph.D. in applied mathematics at the UC Berkeley. His research areas include computational fluid dynamics, numerical methods and scientific computing, and biological fluid flow applications.  He is a member of the Society for Advancement of Chicanos and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS).</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://sse.tulane.edu/math/faculty/cortez">Faculty Website</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/c3oaYL7VlMs">Meet a Mathematician Interview</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Sara Del Valle</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/del-valle-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Sara Del Valle earned her Ph.D. from the University of Iowa and works at the Los Alamos National Laboratory. Born in Mexico, she moved to the U.S. when she was 16. Though she had always loved mathematics, she participated in a summer research program her senior year of college which led her to study mathematical epidemiology. She develops mathematical and computational models to study infectious diseases. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/5f3e96827894c2ff19996e36/5f3f993c31330932d671085c_Sara%20del%20Valle.pdf">Lathisms Profile</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Raegan Higgins</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/higgins-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Raegan Higgins was born in Baton Rouge, LA and is now a professor at Texas Tech University. She was one of the first two African-American women to earn her Ph.D. from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln in 2008. Her research includes applying time scales to systems in biology, epidemiology, economics and statistics.  </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/raegan-higgins/">Mathematically Gifted and Black Profile</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/cmvAzNWjJAI">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>

</subsection>





<subsection><title>Jennifer Mueller</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/mueller-j-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Jennifer L. Mueller is at Colorado State University, where she is a professor in both the School of Biomedical Engineering and the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering. Mueller is from Grand Island, NE and earned her Ph.D. in applied mathematics from UNL.  Her research focuses on medical imaging and electrical impedance tomography.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer_Mueller">Wikipedia</url></p>
	<p><url href="https://www.math.colostate.edu/~mueller/">Faculty Website</url></p>
	<p><url href="https://www.math.colostate.edu/~mueller/eit_lab.html">Faculty News Feature</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Omayra Ortega</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/ortega-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Omayra Ortega is an assistant professor of mathematics and statistics at Sonoma State University and currently serves as the President of the National Association of Mathematicians. She participated in an undergraduate research experience that set her on a path toward mathematical epidemiology. She creates models to study the spread of an illness within different groups of people or in different geographical regions. One area of research involved the study of the spread of malaria between neighboring countries in Africa. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/gNrW2CE0SQ0">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>
	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/omayra-ortega/">Mathematically Gifted and Black Profile</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Freda Porter</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/porter-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Freda Porter, a member of the Lumbee tribe, is one of few American Indian women who have earned a Ph.D. in mathematics. While married and raising a family, she earned her Ph.D. from Duke University in applied mathematics and computational sciences. Porter is now President and CEO of Porter Scientific, Inc., a firm that addresses environmental for industry and various government organizations.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://www.agnesscott.edu/lriddle/women/porter.htm">Biographies of Women Mathematicians</url></p>
	<p><url href="https://www.diversitywoman.com/spotlight-freda-porter/">Diversity Women Media Spotlight</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Candice Price</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/price-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Candice Renee Price is a mathematician at Smith College in Northampton, MA. Born and raised in California, she earned her doctoral degree (2012) in mathematics from the University of Iowa.  Her research focuses on application of mathematics to biology primarily working in DNA topology and knot theory applied to the structure of DNA. More recently her research has included the study of how disease risks can impact social behavior. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/pCnQ1n8Bz-s">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>
	<p><url href="http://www.candicerprice.com/">Website</url></p>

</subsection>





<subsection><title>Vanessa Rivera Quiñones</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/quinones-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Vanessa Rivera Quiñones was born and raised in Puerto Rico and is an artificial intelligence coach at BeCode and a data science consultant. Her graduate research focused on the interactions between a host, a parasite, and the environment. In particular, how this can impact the spread of disease. She is interested in how to tackle problems in sustainability, climate change with a social justice lens.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/A-AMqRdvcHY">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>
	<p><url href="https://www.lathisms.org/calendar-2018/vanessa-rivera-quinones">Lathisms Profile</url></p>

</subsection>





<subsection><title>Luis Sordo Vieira</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/sordo-vieira-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Luis Sordo Vieira is a Venezuelan-American who earned his Ph.D. in 2017 in applied mathematics. He is a professor in the Department of Medicine at the University of Florida. He works computational biology and, among other topics, has studied the role of iron and tumor microenvironment on cancer progression.  </p>
</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://www.lathisms.org/calendar-2018/dr-luis-sordo-vieira">Lathisms Profile</url></p>


</subsection>





<subsection><title>Richard G. White</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/white-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Richard White is a professor of infectious disease modelling in the Center for the Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. He is co-head of LSHTM’s Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology and  is co-author  of  the textbook  An Introduction to Infectious Disease Modelling published by Oxford University Press. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/aboutus/people/white.richard">Faculty Profile</url></p>

</subsection>





<subsection><title>Kamuela Yong</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/yong-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Dr. Kamuela Yong is an Associate Professor of Mathematics at the University of Hawaii, West Oahu. His research explains biological, ecological, and epidemiological processes using mathematical models. Dr. Yong earned bachelor's degrees in Civil Engineering and Applied Math from Loyola Marymount University, and a master’s in Mathematics and a Ph.D. in Applied Mathematics from the University of Iowa. Dr. Yong is the first Native Hawaiian to earn a Ph.D. in Applied Mathematics, and is a co-founder of the Indigenous Mathematicians community. </p>

</sidebyside>

<p><url href="https://youtu.be/xB0yqZGh03k">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>
<p><url href="https://medium.com/stem-and-culture-chronicle/in-over-your-head-b9c37f8b7543">STEM and Culture Feature</url></p>

</subsection>





</section>
