<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-graph-researchers">

<title>Researchers in Graph Theory</title>

<subsection><title>Jacqueline Akinpelu</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/akinpelu-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Akinpelu was in graduate school at Johns Hopkins University when she first encountered applied mathematics. She completed a dissertation in inventory systems management and in 1980 joined AT &amp; T Bell Laboratories in Holmdel, NJ, where she worked for 25 years. The projects she worked on included developing new models for planning and managing telephone network call capacity under specific traffic conditions, and developing strategies for maintaining network stability. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/jacqueline-akinpelu/">Mathematically Gifted and Black</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/mX_TNxflzdA">Meet a Mathematician</url></p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Christina Eubanks-Turner</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/eubanks-turner-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Christina Eubanks-Turner is an Associate Professor of Mathematics at Loyola Marymount University (LMU), Seaver College of Science and Engineering. She was one of the two first African-American women to earn a Ph.D. in mathematics from the University of Nebraska in 2008. Her academic areas of interest include graph theory, commutative algebra, mathematics education, and mathematical sciences diversification. She is also the Director of the Master’s Program in Teaching Mathematics at LMU. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/christina_eubanks_turner/">Mathematically Gifted and Black</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://vimeo.com/325971646 ">Girls, Math &amp; STEM</url></p>

  <p><url href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/ebooks/pdf/LivingProof_WEB.pdf">Living Proof, pg 131</url></p>

  <p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Eubanks-Turner">Wikipedia</url></p>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Christine Kelley</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/kelley-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Christine Kelley is a Professor of Mathematics at UNL and works in coding theory. After receiving her Ph.D. from the University of Notre Dame in 2006, she held postdoctoral research positions at the Fields Institute and The Ohio State University. Her areas of research includes graph-based codes and algorithms, and coding applications such as flash memory storage, data streaming, and communication networks. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://math.unl.edu/christine-kelley">UNL Webpage</url></p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Steven Klee</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/klee-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Steven Klee received his BS in mathematics from Valparaiso University in 2005 and his PhD in mathematics from the University of Washington in 2010. After a two-year postdoc at UC Davis, he started at Seattle University in 2012, where he is currently an associate professor of mathematics. His primary research interest is in combinatorics, but research articles that include phrases such as "spanning tree enumeration" and "minimal length lattice paths" are indicative of the connections to graph theory. In his free time, Klee enjoys cooking and spending time with his family. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://www.seattleu.edu/">Seattle University Webpage (search for "Klee")</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/ebooks/pdf/LivingProof_WEB.pdf">Living Proof, page 12</url></p>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Hiram H. López Valdez</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/lopez-valdez-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Hiram López grew up in Aguascalientes, Mexico and earned his Ph.D. in Mathematics at the CINVESTAV-IPN in Mexico City in 2016. He spent part of his Ph.D. program at the University of Neuchatel, Switzerland, having won a Swiss Excellence Scholarship Award. After completing a postdoc at Clemson University, he joined the faculty at Cleveland State University in 2019. His main area of research is coding theory and network coding, using tools from graph theory, combinatorics and other areas of mathematics. He actively supports Mexican Ph.D. students by linking them to postdoctoral positions at U.S. universities. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/5f3e96827894c2ff19996e36/5f4c8443dc4a796fe32e61e8_Hiram%20H.%20Lopez%20Valdez.pdf">Latinxs and Hispanics in the Mathematical Sciences</url></p>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Oum Sang-il</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/sang-il-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p> Oum Sang-il is a mathematician from South Korea in the Department of Mathematical Sciences at the Korean Advanced Institute of Science and Technology. He works in graph theory and discrete mathematics as a chief investigator for the Pioneer Research Center for Mathematical and Computational Sciences at the Institute for Basic Science. He is best known for his work in structural graph theory. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oum_Sang-il">Wikipedia</url></p>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>John Urschel</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/urschel-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p> John Urschel began a PhD program in mathematics at MIT in 2016. (As of 2021, he is still in the program). After playing football at Penn State, he was a 5th round draft pick into the NFL in 2014.  He played for three years until he retired in 2017 to dedicate his time to studying. Urschel’s research interests are in data science/machine learning, graph theory and numerical linear algebra.  </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/ebooks/pdf/LivingProof_WEB.pdf">Living Proof, page 37</url></p>

  <p><url href="hhttp://math.mit.edu/~urschel/">MIT Website</url></p>

  <p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Urschel">Wikipedia</url></p>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Mariel Vasquez</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/vasquez-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p> Mariel Vasquez obtained a BS degree in mathematics from the National University of Mexico and went on to earn her Ph.D. from Florida State University. After joining the faculty at San Francisco State University in 2005, she became a CAMPOS Scholar at UC Davis in 2014, where she remains a professor of microbiology and molecular genetics. Her research combines mathematics and biology and uses tools such as knot theory and graph theory to study the packing of DNA. </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/5f3e96827894c2ff19996e36/5f3f95620dd5155d06207bdb_Mariel%20Vazquez.pdf">Latinxs and Hispanics in the Mathematical Sciences</url></p>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Michael Young</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/young-m-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p> Michael Young is an Associate Professor of Mathematics and Scott D. Hannah Faculty Fellow at Iowa State University. Young's research focuses on graph theory and cominatorics. Young also promotes equity and inclusion in mathematics, especially the impacts that (1) race, (2) mathematics culture and (3) learning have on one another.   (Which can be thought of as a TRI-partite graph!) </p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://orion.math.iastate.edu/myoung/">Iowa State University Website</url></p>

</subsection>




</section>
