<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-8-2-gerry">

<title>Gerrymandering</title>

<subsection>

	<title>Government Representation and Gerrymandering</title>

	<p>An important principle in a democracy is the notion of equal representation, in other words every citizen's vote counts equally. This is the idea behind the way in which people from each state are represented in Congress in the U.S. House of Representatives.</p>
	<p>In most states, there are a fixed number of representatives to the state legislature. Rather than apportioning each county a number of representatives, legislative districts are drawn so that each legislator represents a district. To help ensure that citizens are equally represented, each district must include approximately the same number of constituents. Because of this goal, a geographically small city may have several representatives, while a large rural region may be represented by one legislator. Nebraska's congressional districts, shown in 
<xref ref="NE-districts"/>
 are a good example of this.</p>

	<figure xml:id="NE-districts">
		<caption>
			Nebraska's congressional districts since 2013.
			<fn>
				Source: <url href="https://images.app.goo.gl/5GTjYaAhhcwD5SGQ7">Wikipedia</url>
			</fn>
		</caption>
		<image source="images/NE-congressional-districts.png"/>
	</figure>

	<p>Every ten years, the U.S. government conducts a census to measure the U.S. population to determine the number of seats each state has in the U.S. House of Representatives. The census identifies shifts in population and states use this data to redraw district maps.  This process is called redistricting and is required by law. </p>
	<p>The methods that states use for redistricting vary from state to state.  In 37 states, the state legislature draws the districts (usually with some guidance). As a result, the political party that controls the state house also controls the redistricting process. Although the districts are supposed to be roughly equal in population, the configuration of these districts is not clearly prescribed
	<fn>Many state constitutions require compactness and contiguity, but no definitions are provided.  Nebraska's state constitution includes these requirements.</fn>
, making the process of redistricting in some states highly politicized.
	<fn>Eight states use a commission to draw the districts; seven states (Alaska, Delaware, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, Vermont, and Wyoming) have only one Congressional district each, so boundaries are not needed.</fn>
  When efforts to redraw the districts are designed to favor one party over another, or one racial group over another, this process is called <term>gerrymandering</term>.</p>
	<assemblage>
		<title>Gerrymandering</title>
		<p><term>Gerrymandering</term> is the process of manipulating the boundaries of an electoral district using the political affiliation of the constituents to the advantage of those drawing the boundary. </p>
	</assemblage>

	<example xml:id="college-vs-rural">
		<p>Consider three districts which equal population simplified to the three boxes below. On the left there is a college area that typically votes Democratic. On the right is a rural area that typically votes Republican. The rest of the people are more evenly split. The middle district has been voting 50% Democratic and 50% Republican. </p>
		<image source="images/college-vs-rural-1.png"/>
		<p>As part of redistricting, a Democratic led committee could redraw the boundaries so that the middle district includes less of the typically Republican voters, thereby making it more likely that their party will win in that district, while increasing the Republican majority in the third district. </p>
		<image source="images/college-vs-rural-2.png"/>
		<p>On the other hand, a Republican led committee might redraw the boundaries to increase rural representation in the middle district while still maintaining a majority in the third district. </p>
		<image source="images/college-vs-rural-2.png"/>
	</example>
	<p>There are many methods that politicians use to try to gain an advantage, but the most common are: 
		<ul>
			<li><term>packing</term>&#8212;grouping as many members as possible of the opposing party into the smallest number of districts so they win fewer representatives.</li>
			<li><term>cracking</term>&#8212;dividing members of the opposing party into many districts so they will not comprise a majority in very many of them.</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>Let&apos;s see how this works.  Below are three ways to draw five districts (with equal population) to represent 50 people. </p>
	<figure xml:id="packing-cracking">
		<caption>
		Three different redistricting methods for a given population.
			<fn>
				Source: <url href="https://img.washingtonpost.com/wp-apps/imrs.php?src=https://img.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/files/2015/03/gerry.png&amp;w=1484">Washington Post</url>
			</fn>
		</caption>
		<sidebyside>
			<figure xml:id="population">
				<caption>Population</caption>
				<image source="images/packing-cracking-pop.png"/>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="method-1">
				<caption>Method 1</caption>
				<image source="images/packing-cracking-1.png"/>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="method-2">
				<caption>Method 2</caption>
				<image source="images/packing-cracking-2.png"/>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="method-3">
				<caption>Method 3</caption>
				<image source="images/packing-cracking-3.png"/>
			</figure>
		</sidebyside>
	</figure>

	<sidebyside>
		<p>You might notice the unusual shapes used to determine the districts in Method 3.  As it turns out, this can often be evidence of gerrymandering. In fact, it is built-in to the origin of the term. In 1812 Elbridge Gerry, the governor of Massachusetts, signed into law a district resembling a salamander (as shown here) designed to favor his party in 1812 elections: Gerry + salamander = gerrymander.</p>
		<image source="images/gerry-salamander.png"/>
	</sidebyside>

</subsection>

<subsection>

	<title>Using Mathematics to Combat Gerrymandering</title>

	<!-- WRITE THIS SECTION  First explain compactness. Which of the district plans in Figure XXX show districts that you think are compact? Why might this be an advantage?
Then explain the Polsby-Popper Score -->
	<subsubsection>
		<title>Compactness</title>
		<p>The Polsby-Popper Score (PPS) is a metric used to quantify compactness. Recall that popular opinion is that compactness is something to be desired; the more compact a district is, the better. To calculate the PPS, we use the following definition: 
			<me>\text{PPS} = \frac{4 \pi (\text{Area of District})}{(\text{Perimeter of District})^2}</me>
		</p>
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
		<title>Efficiency Gaps</title>

		<p>Since shape is not a consistent method of detecting gerrymandering, other methods for quantifying the strategic manipulation of voting districts.  Another, more reliable way to measure the degree to which a districting plan is gerrymandered is to compare the efficiency gaps of the two parties.</p>

	</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection>
	<title>The Impact of Gerrymandering</title>

	<p>Both the Republican and Democratic parties have used questionable boundaries to maintain their power.  Examples can be used to help illustrate the impact of gerrymandering on the political system.</p>
	<example xml:id="district-12">
		<title>North Carolina, Congressional District 12</title>
		<p>Even though the population of North Carolina is nearly evenly divided between Republicans and Democrats, at times as many as ten of the thirteen seats in the U.S. House of Representatives for North Carolina have been held by Republicans. This is in large part because of how district lines were drawn when Republicans controlled the redistricting process. In 2016, the Supreme court ruled that the boundary of district 12 (shown below), designed to concentrate the Black vote into one district and limit their influence elsewhere, was deemed unconstitutional. Struggles to ensure that Black and other minority voters have a voice in state elections are ongoing in North Carolina, making District 12 known as &quot;the most gerrymandered district in America&quot;.
			<fn>
				Source: <url href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/oct/19/gerrymandering-supreme-court-us-election-north-carolina">The Guardian</url>
			</fn>
		</p>
		<image source="images/district-12.png"/>
	</example>
	<example xml:id="massachusetts">
		<title>Representation in Massachusetts</title>

		<p>Although nearly one third of the voters in Massachusetts are known to be Republican, since 1994, all nine of their House representatives have been Democrats.
			<fn>
				Source: <url href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2021/05/27/redistricting-gerrymandering-2021-moon-duchin-interview-491199?utm_source=pocket-newtab">Politico</url>
			</fn>
		 Part of the issue in this case, is that the Republican voters are somewhat evenly distributed throughout the state, making it extremely difficult to draw a compact, connected district containing enough Republican voters in any one of them to have a majority.  Since Democrats have controlled the redistricting process for nearly three decades, it appears there has been little motivation to make any changes in order to remedy this.</p>
	</example>

</subsection>

<subsection>
	<title>Changing the Game</title>

	<p>The Voting Rights Act of 1965 created laws which apply to redistricting to prevent states and localities from drawing districts that deny minorities a chance to elect a candidate of their choice. Thus, certain districts are created to contain a majority of minority voters.  This requires a balancing act between maintaining a majority of votes and packing too many minorities into a single district.  In fact, there are many criteria that states list as important for redistricting and meeting all the criteria is quite difficult.  In most cases there is no &quot;best&quot; solution, so the goal is to find a &quot;good&quot; solution.  Two examples of this are below.</p>

	<example xml:id="district-38">
		<title>California, Congressional District 38</title>

		<sidebyside>
			<p>The map to the right shows the 38th congressional district in California in 2014.
				<fn>
					Source: <url href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:California_District_38_2004.png">Wikipedia</url>
				</fn>
 This district was created through a bi-partisan committee of incumbent legislators. This gerrymandering leads to districts that are not competitive; the prevailing party almost always wins with a large margin.</p>
			<image source="images/district-38.png"/>
		</sidebyside>
	</example>

	<example xml:id="district-4">
		<title>Illinois, Congressional District 4</title>

		<sidebyside>
			<p>The map to the right shows the 4th congressional district in Illinois in 2004.
				<fn>
					Source: <url href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Illinois_District_4_2004.png">Wikipedia</url>
				</fn>
 This district was drawn to contain the two predominantly Hispanic areas of Chicago. The largely Puerto Rican area to the north and the southern Mexican areas are only connected in this districting by a piece of the highway to the west. The result is that voters in this district have typically elected a representative from a minority group, reflecting the diversity of the state; the downside is the large number of wasted votes limits influence outside of these boundaries.</p>
			<image source="images/district-4.png"/>
		</sidebyside>
	</example>

</subsection>

</section>
