<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-6-1-researchers-stats">

<title>Researchers in Statistics and Data Science</title>


<subsection><title>Federico Ardila</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/Cotwright-williams-XXX.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Federico Ardila is a professor at San Francisco State University and an adjunct at Universidad de Los Andes in Colombia. His primary area of research is combinatorics.  Since combinatorics involves methods of counting, it is heavily used for discrete probability distributions. In addition to his own math research, Ardila has worked to encourage underrepresented groups within mathematics, with the goal of ensuring that everyone has access to joyful and meaningful mathematical experiences.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://youtu.be/vut--TS7FoQ">Video Biography</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federico_Ardila">Wikipedia</url></p>
  	<p><url href="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/5f3e96827894c2ff19996e36/5f3f95e7e34a758cb1e278f1_Federico%20Ardila.pdf">Latinx Mathematicians Post</url></p>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Carla Cotwright-Williams</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/Cotwright-williams-pic.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Carla Cotwright-Williams is a Senior Data Scientist for the United States Department of Defense. While her Ph.D. dissertation involved mathematical objects called matroids, her more recent work has included using statistics to prevent social security fraud, estimate savings from implementing government programs, and improve drone control systems for NASA.  She completed her Ph.D. at the University of Mississippi in 2006, the second African-American woman to earn a doctorate in mathematics there.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carla_Cotwright-Williams">Wikipedia</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://mathematicallygiftedandblack.com/honorees/carla-cotwright/">Mathematically Gifted and Black Post</url></p>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Moon Dunchin</title>

<sidebyside widths="25% 2% 73%">

	<image source="images/dunchin-pic-2.png"/>

	<p></p>

	<p>Moon Dunchin is a professor of mathematics at Tufts University in Massachusetts. She has become known as a leading expert in gerrymandering and has made it her goal to use education to combat its use and protect voting rights.  She directs the Metric Geometry and Gerrymandering Group (MGGG), whose goal is to research and share with the general public tools for better understanding the impact of districting, and provide consulting services.</p>

</sidebyside>

	<p><url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moon_Duchin">Wikipedia</url></p>

	<p><url href="https://now.tufts.edu/articles/fixing-gerrymandering-geometry">Tufts Now Article</url></p>

</subsection>



</section>
