<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-8-2-gerry">

<title>Gerrymandering</title>

<subsection>

	<title>Government Representation and Gerrymandering</title>

	<p>An important principle in a democracy is the notion of equal representation, in other words every citizen's vote counts equally. This is the idea behind the way in which people from each state are represented in Congress in the U.S. House of Representatives.</p>
	<p>In most states, there are a fixed number of representatives to the state legislature. Rather than apportioning each county a number of representatives, legislative districts are drawn so that each legislator represents a district. To help ensure that citizens are equally represented, each district must include approximately the same number of constituents. Because of this goal, a geographically small city may have several representatives, while a large rural region may be represented by one legislator. Nebraska's congressional districts, shown in 
<xref ref="NE-districts"/>
 are a good example of this.</p>

<figure xml:id="NE-districts">
	<caption>
		Nebraska's congressional districts since 2013.
		<fn>
			Source: <url href="https://images.app.goo.gl/5GTjYaAhhcwD5SGQ7">Wikipedia</url>
		</fn>
	</caption>
	<image width="50%" source="images/NE-congressional-districts.png"/>
</figure>

<p>Every ten years, the U.S. government conducts a census to measure the U.S. population to determine the number of seats each state has in the U.S. House of Representatives. The census identifies shifts in population and states use this data to redraw district maps.  This process is called redistricting and is required by law. </p>
<p>The methods that states use for redistricting vary from state to state.  In 37 states, the state legislature draws the districts (usually with some guidance). As a result, the political party that controls the state house also controls the redistricting process. Although the districts are supposed to be roughly equal in population, the configuration of these districts is not clearly prescribed
<fn>Many state constitutions require compactness and contiguity, but no definitions are provided.  Nebraska's state constitution includes these requirements.</fn>
, making the process of redistricting in some states highly politicized.
<fn>Eight states use a commission to draw the districts; seven states (Alaska, Delaware, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, Vermont, and Wyoming) have only one Congressional district each, so boundaries are not needed.</fn>
  When efforts to redraw the districts are designed to favor one party over another, or one racial group over another, this process is called <term>gerrymandering</term>.</p>
<assemblage>
	<title>Gerrymandering</title>
	<p><term>Gerrymandering</term> is the process of manipulating the boundaries of an electoral district using the political affiliation of the constituents to the advantage of those drawing the boundary. </p>
</assemblage>

<example xml:id="college-vs-rural">
	<p>Consider three districts which equal population simplified to the three boxes below. On the left there is a college area that typically votes Democratic. On the right is a rural area that typically votes Republican. The rest of the people are more evenly split. The middle district has been voting 50% Democratic and 50% Republican. </p>
	<image source="images/college-vs-rural-1.png"/>
	<p>As part of redistricting, a Democratic led committee could redraw the boundaries so that the middle district includes less of the typically Republican voters, thereby making it more likely that their party will win in that district, while increasing the Republican majority in the third district. </p>
	<image source="images/college-vs-rural-2.png"/>
	<p>On the other hand, a Republican led committee might redraw the boundaries to increase rural representation in the middle district while still maintaining a majority in the third district. </p>
	<image source="images/college-vs-rural-2.png"/>
</example>
<p>There are many methods that politicians to try to gain an advantage, but the most common are: 
	<ul>
		<li><term>packing</term>&#8212;grouping as many members as possible of the opposing party into the smallest number of districts so they win fewer representatives.</li>
		<li><term>cracking</term>&#8212;dividing members of the opposing party into many districts so they will not comprise a majority in very many of them.</li>
	</ul>
</p>
<p>Let&apos;s see how this works.  Below are three ways to draw five districts (with equal population) to represent 50 people. </p>
<figure xml:id="packing-cracking">
	<caption>Caption</caption>
</figure>
	

</subsection>

</section>
