<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->




<chapter xml:id="chap1"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction to Intermediate Algebra</title>
<section  xml:id="Numbers-and-Operations"><title>Numbers and Operations</title>
<introduction>
<p>Algebra is often described as the generalization of arithmetic. The systematic use of <term>variables</term>, letters used to represent numbers, allows us to communicate and solve a wide variety of real-world problems. For this reason, we begin by reviewing real numbers and their operations.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>review definitions surrounding <term>integers</term>.</p></li>
        <li><p>add, subtract, multiply, divide, and reduce fractions</p></li>
        <li><p>use the <term>order of operations</term> to put expressions into simplest form</p></li>
        <li><p>do computations with <term>percents</term></p></li>
        <li><p>review <term>radicals</term></p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>
</introduction>


<subsection><title>Numbers</title>
    
    <p>We call the set of numbers <m>\{\dots,-3,-2,-1,0,1,2,3,\dots\}</m> the <term>integers</term>.</p>

<p>A <term>prime number</term> is an integer greater than <m>1</m> that is divisible only by <m>1</m> and itself. The smallest prime number is <m>2</m> and the rest are necessarily odd:</p>

<me>2,3,5,7,11,13,17,19,23,29,\dots\text{.}</me>

<p>Any integer greater than <m>1</m> that is not prime can be uniquely written as a product of primes; we call such a number <term>composite</term>. Note that the number 1 is neither prime nor composite.</p>


<p>When a composite number, like <m>42</m>, is written as a product, <m>42=2\cdot 21</m>, we say that <m>2\cdot 21</m> is a <term>factorization</term> of <m>42</m> and that <m>2</m> and <m>21</m> are <term>factors</term>. Note that factors divide the number evenly.</p>

<p>When a factorization of a number consists only of prime numbers, we call it the <term>prime factorization</term> of that number. Since <m>21</m> is not prime, <m>42=2\cdot21</m> is not the prime factorization of <m>42</m>. However, we can continue to write factors as products until only a product of primes remains.</p>

 <image source="images/Chapter1/Numbers01.png" width="150%"><description>Factor Tree</description></image>

<p>Therefore the prime factorization of <m>42</m> is <m>2\cdot 3\cdot 7</m>.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Determine the prime factorization of <m>210</m>.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We begin by writing <m>210</m> as a product with <m>10</m> as a factor:
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                210\amp=10\cdot21
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
        We then continue by factoring the factors, breaking apart both <m>10</m> and <m>21</m> until only a product of primes remains.
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                210 \amp= 10\cdot 21 \\
                    \amp= 2\cdot 5\cdot 3\cdot 7
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
        Since the prime factorization is unique, it does not matter how we choose to initially factor the number - the end result will be the same (although you may write your answer in a different order).
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>A <term>fraction</term> is a number written as a quotient, or ratio <m>\frac{a}{b}</m>, of two integers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> where <m>b\neq 0</m>. The integer above the fraction bar is called the <term>numerator</term> and the integer below is called the <term>denominator</term>. Two equal ratios expressed using different numerators and denominators are called <term>equivalent fractions</term>. For example,</p>

<me>
    \frac{50}{100}=\frac{1}{2}\text{.}
    </me>

<p>One way that we can find equivalent fractions is to identify a <term>common factor</term> of the numerator and denominator, which is simply a factor that two or more numbers share. For example, consider the following factorizations of <m>50</m> and <m>100</m>:</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    50\amp = 2\cdot 25 \text{ and }\\
    100\amp =4\cdot 25\text{.}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

<p>Here we see that 25 is a common factor of 50 and 100. Making use of the fact that <m>\frac{25}{25}=1</m>, we see that</p>

<me>\frac{50}{100}=\frac{2\cdot 25}{4\cdot 25}=\frac{2}{4}\cdot 1=\frac{2}{4}\text{.}</me>

<p>Dividing <m>\frac{25}{25}</m> and replacing this factor with a <m>1</m> is called <term>cancelling</term>. Together, these basic steps for finding equivalent fractions define the process of <term>reducing</term> a fraction. Since factors divide their product evenly, we achieve the same result by dividing both the numerator and denominator by <m>25</m> as follows:</p>

<me>\frac{50\alert{\div 25}}{100\alert{\div 25}}=\frac{2}{4}\text{.}</me>

<p>Finding equivalent fractions where the numerator and denominator are relatively prime, or have no common factor other than <m>1</m>, is called <term>reducing to lowest terms</term>. This can be done by dividing the numerator and denominator by the <term>greatest common factor (GCF)</term>. The GCF is the largest number that divides a set of numbers evenly. One way to find the GCF of 50 and 100 is to list all the factors of each and identify the largest number that appears in both lists. Remember, each number is also a factor of itself.</p>

<me>\{{\bf 1,2,5,10,25,50}\} \alert{\text{ Factors of }50}</me>
<me>\{{\bf1,2, } 4,{\bf 5,10, }\, 20,{\bf 25,50, }\, 100\} \alert{\text{ Factors of }100}</me>
    
<p>Another way to find the GCF of two numbers is to consider their prime factorizations. The GCF will be the product of all the prime factors that they have in common. For example, we can compute the GCF of 108 and 72 as follows:</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
     108\amp = \alert{2}\cdot\alert{2}\cdot\alert{3}\cdot\alert{3}\cdot 3\\
     72\amp =\alert{2}\cdot\alert{2}\cdot 2\cdot\alert{3}\cdot\alert{3}
     \end{aligned}</me>
<me> \text{GCF}(108,72)=\alert{2}\cdot\alert{2}\cdot\alert{3}\cdot\alert{3}=36</me>
    <p>In this case, the product of the common prime factors is <m>36</m>. </p>

    <assemblage><title>To reduce a fraction to lowest terms</title>
<p>
    <ol label="1">
        <li><p>
            Find the greatest common factor of the numerator and denominator. This can be done by listing all the factors of each and identifying the largest number that appears in both lists, or by finding the prime factorizations of both and taking the product of the prime factors they have in common.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Reduce the fraction by dividing both the numerator and the denominator by their GCF.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>


<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{172}{64}</m> by reducing it to lowest terms.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>First, we find the GCF of 172 and 64 by considering their prime factorizations:
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
            172 \amp= \alert{2} \cdot \alert{2} \cdot 43 \\
            64 \amp= \alert{2} \cdot \alert{2} \cdot 2 \cdot 2 \cdot 2 \cdot 2
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
        The product of the common prime factors is <m>2\cdot2=4</m>, so the GCF of 172 and 64 is 4. We can now reduce the fraction:
        <me>
            \frac{172}{64}=\frac{172\alert{\div 4}}{64\alert{\div 4}}=\frac{43}{16}
        </me>.
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{108}{72}</m> by reducing it to lowest terms.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        We have already found that the GCF of 108 and 72 is 36. We can then reduce the fraction:
        <me>\frac{108}{72}=\frac{108\alert{\div 36}}{72\alert{\div 36}}=\frac{3}{2}</me>.
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>In the previous example, we can convert the improper fraction <m>\frac{3}{2}</m> to a mixed number <m>1\frac{1}{2}</m>; however, it is important to note that converting to a mixed number is not part of the reducing process. We consider improper fractions, such as <m>\frac{3}{2}</m>, to be reduced to lowest terms. In algebra it is often preferable to work with improper fractions, although in some applications, mixed numbers are more appropriate.  It is also worth noting that the mixed number notation <m>1\frac{1}{2}</m> is actually a confusing notation.  What we really mean is <m>1+\frac{1}{2}</m></p>

<p>Next we will explore some interesting properties of division. Division is a restatement of multiplication; for example,</p>

<me>\frac{12}{6}=2\, \, \text{ since }\, \, 6\cdot 2=12\text{.}</me>

<p>In this case, the <term>dividend</term> 12 is evenly divided by the <term>divisor</term> 6 to obtain the <term>quotient</term> 2. It is true in general that if we multiply the divisor by the quotient we obtain the dividend. Now consider the case where the dividend is zero and the divisor is nonzero:</p>

<me>\frac{0}{6}=0\, \, \text{ since }\, \, 6\cdot 0=0\text{.}</me>

<p>This demonstrates that zero divided by any nonzero real number must be zero. Now consider a nonzero number divided by zero:</p>

<me>\frac{12}{0}=\alert{?}\, \, \text{ or }\, \, 0\, \cdot\alert{?}=12\text{.}</me>

<p>Zero times anything is zero and we conclude that there is no real number to satisfy the equation <m>0\cdot\text{?}=12</m>. Thus, the quotient <m>\frac{12}{0}</m> is <term>undefined</term>. Try it on a calculator, what does it say? For our purposes, we will simply write “undefined.” To summarize, given any real number <m>a\neq 0</m>, then zero divided by <m>a</m> is zero and <m>a</m> divided by zero is underfined.</p>

<me>0\div a=\frac{0}{a}=0\, \, \alert{\text{ zero}} \text{ and }\, \, a\div 0=\frac{a}{0}\, \, \alert{\text{ undefined}}</me>

<p>We are left to consider the case where the dividend and divisor are both zero.</p>

<me>\frac{0}{0}=\alert{?}\, \, \text{ or }\, \, 0\, \cdot\alert{?}=0</me>

<p>Here, any real number seems to work. For example, <m>0\cdot 5=0</m>
    and also, <m>0\cdot 3=0.</m>
    Therefore, the quotient is uncertain or <term>indeterminate</term>.</p>

<me>0\div 0=\frac{0}{0} \, \, \alert{\text{ indeterminate}}</me>

<p>In this course, we state that <m>0\div 0=\frac{0}{0}</m> is undefined.</p>

<p>Notice that in the definition of fractions we allowed for <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> to be negative. Remember that for any number <m>c</m>, we have <m>-c=(-1)\cdot c</m>. This tells us that
    <me>
        \frac{-a}{b}=\frac{(-1)\cdot a}{b}=-\frac{a}{b}
        </me>
    
        and also
        <me>
            \frac{a}{-b}=\frac{a}{(-1)\cdot b}=-\frac{a}{b}\text{.}</me>
    
    Thus as a rule, we write the negative sign out in front of a fraction if we have it:
    
    <me>\frac{-a}{b}=\frac{a}{-b}=-\frac{a}{b}.
        </me>
    </p>
    
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Order of Operations</title>

<p>Numerical calculations often involve more than one operation. So that everyone agrees on how such expressions should be evaluated, we follow the order of operations.</p>

<assemblage><title>Order of Operations</title>
<p>
    <ol label="1">
        <li><p>
            Simplify any expressions within grouping symbols (parentheses, brackets, square root bars, or fraction bars). Start with the innermost grouping symbols and work outward.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Evaluate all exponents and roots.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Perform multiplications and divisions in order from left to right.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Perform additions and subtractions in order from left to right.
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<p>You may have heard of the acronym PEMDAS to remember the order of operations easily. This acronym stands for Parentheses, Exponents, Multiplication, Division, Addition, and Subtraction. Notice the differences between PEMDAS and the Order of Operations described in the box above. For example, in PEDMAS multiplication is always done before division, while in the Order of Operations, multiplication and division have equal weight and are performed in order from left to right. It is important that we all use the same order when performing operations, as using different orders can lead to drastically different answers.</p>



<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>-10-(-10)-5+3^2+\frac{15}{5}</m> by reducing to lowest terms.
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        Follow order of operations:
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            -10-(-10)-5+3^2+\frac{15}{5}\amp = -10-(-10)-5+3^2+3 \alert{\text{ Simplify fraction}}\\
            \amp = -10-(-10)-5+9+3 \alert{\text{ Evaluate power}}\\
            \amp=-10+10-5+9+3 \alert{\text{ Perform multiplication}}\\
            \amp =0-5+9+3\\
            \amp = 7.
            \end{aligned}</me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>
    We can use parentheses to override the multiplication before addition or subtraction rule. Compare the two expressions below.
    <md>
        <mrow>\amp\text{The sum of 4 times 6 and 10} \amp\amp 4 \cdot 6 + 10</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\text{4 times the sum of 6 and 10} \amp\amp  4(6 + 10)</mrow>
    </md>
</p>
<p>
    In the first expression, we perform the multiplication <m>4\cdot 6</m> first, but in the second expression we perform the addition <m>6 + 10</m> first, because it is enclosed in parentheses.
</p>
<p>
    The location (or absence) of parentheses can drastically alter the meaning of an expression. In the following example, note how the location of the parentheses changes the value of the expression.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-parentheses">
    <p>
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}5-3\cdot 4^2 \amp = 5-3\cdot 16\\
                \amp = 5-48=-43
                \end{aligned}                
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}5-(3\cdot 4)^2 \amp = 5-12^2\\
                \amp= 5-144 = -139
                 \end{aligned}
           </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}(5-3\cdot 4)^2 \amp = (5-12)^2\\
                \amp = (-7)^2 = 49
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}(5-3)\cdot 4^2 \amp = 2\cdot 16\\
                \amp = 32
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</example>

<warning>
    <p>
        In the expression <m>5 - 12^2</m>, which appears in <xref ref="example-parentheses" text="type-global"/>, the exponent <m>2</m> applies only to <m>12</m>, not to <m>-12</m>. Thus, <m>5 - 12^2 \ne 5 + 144</m>.
    </p>
</warning>

<p>
    When dealing with exponents, it's important to pay attention to what the exponent is being applied to. For example,
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        -1^2 \amp= -(1\cdot1) = -1 \\ 
        (-1)^2 \amp= -1\cdot-1 = 1 
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    The properties of exponents will be explored in more detail later.
</p>

<p>
    The order of operations mentions other grouping devices besides parentheses - fraction bars and square root bars. Notice how the placement of the fraction bar affects the expressions in the next example.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-parentheses2">
    <p>
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                \frac{1+2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = \frac{3}{12}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = 1+ \frac{2}{12}
                \end{aligned}                
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = 1+ \frac{8}{3}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \frac{1+2}{3}\cdot 4 = \frac{3}{3}\cdot 4= 1\cdot 4=4
            </m></p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</example>



</subsection>


<subsection><title>Simplest Form</title>

<p>
    As we saw above in part (d) of <xref ref="example-parentheses2" text="type-global"/>, we were able to achieve a "simple" answer by noticing that <m>\frac{3}{3}=1</m>. We can use this sort of notion to simplify all our answers above. A number is in <term>simplest form</term> if all order of operations have been performed and the number is either a reduced fraction or a whole number.
</p>

<p>Adding or subtracting fractions requires a common denominator. Assume the common denominator <m>c</m> is a nonzero integer and we have</p>



<me>\frac{a}{c}+\frac{b}{c}=\frac{a+b}{c}\text{ and }\frac{a}{c}-\frac{b}{c}=\frac{a-b}{c}\text{.}</me>



<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify <m>\frac{2}{9}-\frac{1}{15}+\frac{8}{45}</m>.
    </p></statement>


<solution>
    <p>
        In order to add or subtract fractions, we need them to have a common denominator. To keep the numbers as simple as possible, it is helpful to find the <term>least common denominator</term> (LCD). To find the LCD, we first determine the least common multiple (LCM) of the denominators. We begin by listing the multiples of each given denominator.
        
        <me>\{9,18,27,36,{\bf 45,}\, 54,63,72,81,{\bf{90}},\dots\} \alert{\text{ Multiples of }9}</me>
        <me>\{15,30,{\bf 45,}\, 60,75,{\bf{90}},\dots\} \alert{\text{ Multiples of }15}</me>
        <me>\{{\bf 45,90,135,}\dots\} \alert{\text{ Multiples of }45}</me>
        Here we see that the <me>\text{LCM}(9,15,45)=45</me>. Multiply the numerator and the denominator of each fraction by values that result in equivalent fractions with the determined common denominator.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \frac{2}{9}-\frac{1}{15}+\frac{8}{45}\amp =\frac{2}{9}\cdot\alert{\frac{5}{5}}-\frac{1}{15}\cdot\alert{\frac{3}{3}}+\frac{8}{45}\\
            \amp =\frac{10}{45}-\frac{3}{45}+\frac{8}{45}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
        Once we have equivalent fractions, with a common denominator, we can perform the operations on the numerators and write the result over the common denominator.
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            \amp =\frac{10-3+8}{45}\\
            \amp =\frac{15}{45}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
        Then we reduce if necessary:
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
            \amp =\frac{15\alert{\div 15}}{45\alert{\div 15}}\\
            \amp =\frac{1}{3}\text{.}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Finding the LCM using lists of multiples, as described in the previous example, is often very cumbersome. For example, try making a list of multiples for 12 and 81. We can streamline the process of finding the LCM by using prime factors.</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    12\amp = 2^2\cdot 3\\
    81\amp =3^4
    \end{aligned}
</me>

<p>The least common multiple is the product of each prime factor raised to the highest power. In this case,</p>

<me>\text{LCM}(12,81)=2^2\cdot 3^4=324\text{.}</me>


<example><statement>
    <p>Find the simplest form of each of the answers in <xref ref="example-parentheses2" text="type-global"/>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                \frac{1+2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = \frac{3}{12}=\frac{3}{3\cdot 4}=\frac{1}{4}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = 1+ \frac{2}{12}=\frac{12}{12}+\frac{2}{12}=\frac{14}{12}=\frac{2\cdot 7}{2\cdot 6}=\frac{7}{6}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}
                1+\frac{2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = 1+ \frac{8}{3}=\frac{3}{3}+\frac{8}{3}=\frac{11}{3}
                \end{aligned}
            </m></p></li>
            <li><p>It is already in simplest form.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
        </solution>
    </example>

<p>Unlike addition and subtraction, multiplying or dividing fractions does not require a common denominator. To multiply two fractions, we simply multiply the numerators and multiply the denominators: <me>\frac{a}{b}\cdot\frac{c}{d}=\frac{a\cdot c}{b\cdot d}</me> In order to divide fractions, we need to define the reciprocal of a number. Two real numbers whose product is <m>1</m> are called <term>reciprocals</term>. Therefore, the reciprocal of <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> is <m>\frac{b}{a}</m> because <m>\frac{a}{b}\cdot\frac{b}{a}=\frac{ab}{ab}=1</m>. For example,</p>

    <me>\frac{2}{3}\cdot\frac{3}{2}=\frac{6}{6}=1\text{.}</me>
    
<p>Since their product is <m>1,\frac{2}{3}</m> and <m>\frac{3}{2}</m> are reciprocals. Some other reciprocals are</p>
    
    <me>\frac{5}{8}\, \, \text{ and } \, \, \frac{8}{5},\, \, \, \,  7\, \, \text{ and }\, \, \frac{1}{7},\, \, \, \, -\frac{4}{5}\, \, \text{ and }\, -\frac{5}{4}</me>.
    
<p>This definition is important because dividing fractions requires that you multiply the dividend by the reciprocal of the divisor.</p>

<me>\frac{a}{b}\div\alert{\frac{c}{d}}=\frac{\frac{a}{b}}{\frac{c}{d}}\cdot\frac{\alert{\frac{d}{c}}}{\alert{\frac{d}{c}}}=\frac{\frac{a}{b}\cdot\frac{d}{c}}{1}=\frac{a}{b}\cdot\alert{\frac{d}{c}}</me>

<example>
    <statement>
    <p>Simplify <m>\frac{5}{4}\div\frac{3}{5}\cdot\frac{1}{2}</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Perform the multiplication and division left to right.
            <me>\begin{aligned}
                \frac{5}{4}\div\alert{\frac{3}{5}}\cdot\frac{1}{2}\amp =\frac{5}{4}\cdot\alert{\frac{5}{3}}\cdot\frac{1}{2}\\
                \amp =\frac{5\cdot 5\cdot 1}{4\cdot 3\cdot 2}\\
                \amp =\frac{25}{24}
                \end{aligned}
                </me>
              In algebra, it is often preferable to work with improper fractions. In this case, we leave the answer expressed as an improper fraction.
               </p>
        </solution>
</example>

<example>
    <statement>
    <p>Simplify <m>\frac{(3^2-1)2+\frac{1}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2}</m>.
        </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Recall that fraction bars are a grouping operation; this means that we need to simplify everything in the numerator and everything in the denominator separately first. In the numerator, we simplify everything in parentheses before moving on to multiplication and addition. In the denominator, we perform multiplication and division from left to right.
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                \frac{(3^2-1)2+\frac{1}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2} \amp= \frac{(8)2+\frac{1}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2} \amp\amp\text{Simplify what's in parentheses.}\\
                \amp= \frac{16+\frac{1}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2} \amp\amp\text{Multiply in the numerator.} \\
                \amp= \frac{\frac{32}{2}+\frac{1}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2} \amp\amp\text{Rewrite }16\text{ as a fraction.} \\
                \amp= \frac{\frac{33}{2}}{6\div3\cdot2} \amp\amp\text{Add in the numerator.} \\
                \amp= \frac{\frac{33}{2}}{2\cdot2}\amp\amp\text{Divide in the denominator.} \\
                \amp= \frac{\frac{33}{2}}{4} \amp\amp\text{Multiply in the denominator.} \\
                \amp= \frac{33}{2}\cdot\frac{1}{4} \amp\amp\text{Divide by multiplying by the reciprocal.} \\
                \amp= \frac{33}{8}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
</example>

<warning>
    <p>
        In the previous example, we could have change the fraction <m>\frac{33}{2}</m> to the decimal <m>16.5</m> to obtain an answer of <me>\frac{16.5}{4}</me> Although this may look like a simplified fraction, it is not! To be a simplified fraction, the numerator and denominator must both be whole numbers.
    </p>
</warning>




</subsection>


<subsection><title>Percents</title>

    <p> Percents are used to express a number as a fraction out of <m>100</m>. For example, the number <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> is equal to <m>50</m>% since <m>\frac{1}{2}=\frac{50}{100}</m>. When working with percents, we will often have to change a percentage to a decimal value or vice versa:
    </p>

    <assemblage><title>Percent to Decimal Transformation</title>
    <p>Suppose <m>a</m> represents a partial amount of the whole amount <m>b</m>. Then we have
    <me>
        \frac{\text{partial amount }a}{\text{whole amount }b} = \text{decimal value }
        </me>
    The decimal value is then converted to a percent by multiplying by <m>100</m> and adding the percent symbol %.</p>
    </assemblage>
     
     <p>For example, say we have 15 red marbles in a bag of 75. If we want to know the percentage of the marbles that are red, we set up the following:</p>
     
     <me>
         \begin{aligned}
         \frac{\text{partial amount }a}{\text{whole amount } b}\amp = \frac{15}{75} \amp\text{Let }a=15,\, b=75\\
         \amp =\frac{15}{75}\cdot\frac{\frac{4}{3}}{\frac{4}{3}}\\
         \amp=\frac{20}{100} \\
         \amp=0.2\amp\text{Write as a decimal}\\
         \amp=20\text{%}\amp\text{Convert to a percent}
         \end{aligned}
     </me>
        
    <example><statement>
        <p>Lara's choir consists of 25 singers and 18 are women. What is the percent of women in the choir?</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \frac{\text{partial amount }a}{\text{whole amount } b}\amp = \frac{18}{25} \amp\text{Let }a=32,\, b=50\\
        \amp =\frac{18}{25}\left(\alert{\frac{4}{4}}\right)\\
        \amp =\frac{72}{100}\\
        \amp =0.72 \amp\text{Write as a decimal}\\
        \amp =72\text{%}\amp\text{Convert to a percent}
        \end{aligned}
        </me>
    <p>Lara's choir is <m>72</m>% women.</p>
    </solution>
    </example>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Areeba's mathematics grade includes 300 points for exams. If the entire amount of points she can earn is 750, what percentage of her grade comes from exams?
            </p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                    The partial amount is the <m>300</m> points for exams, and the whole amount is the <m>750</m> points overall.
                    <me>\begin{aligned}
                        \frac{\text{partial amount }a}{\text{whole amount }b}=\frac{300}{750}=0.4=40\text{%}
                        \end{aligned}
                    </me>
                    So <m>40</m>% of Areeba's grade comes from exams.
                </p>
            </solution>
        </example>
    
    <p> Percents are often used to represent the change in some quantity.  When representing change, percents give you the ability to see how big the change is relative to the quantity that is changing.

<assemblage><title>Percent Change</title>
<p><m>\text{percent change (as a decimal)} =\frac{\text{amount of change}}{\text{original amount}}</m></p>
</assemblage>
</p>

<example> <statement><p>Your favorite store is having a sale on jeans. Their original price is <m>$40</m>, but today, their sale price is <m>$28</m>. What is the percent discount on the jeans?</p></statement>

<solution><p>The amount of change in the price of the jeans is <m>28-40 = -12</m> dollars. So the percent change is <m>\frac{-12}{40} = -.3</m>. We convert this to a percent, or <m>-30\text{%}</m>. The negative tells us that the price has decreased. So the percent discount on the jeans was <m>30\text{%}</m>.
</p></solution>
</example>

<example>
<statement><p>The population of Mongolia in 2007 was estimated to be <m>2.62</m> million. In 2010, it was estimated to be <m>2.76</m> million. What was the percent increase in the population of Mongolia over this three year period?</p></statement>
<solution><p>The amount of change in population was <m>2.76 - 2.62 = 0.14</m> million. So the percent change was <m> \frac{0.14}{2.76} = 0.051</m> (approximately). We convert this to a percent, or <m>5.1</m>%. So the population of Mongolia increased by <m>5.1</m>% between 2007 and 2010.</p>
 </solution>
 </example>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Radicals</title>
<p>
    You may already be familiar with square roots. Every nonnegative number has two square roots, defined as follows:
    <me>s ~\text{ is a square root of }~ n ~\text{ if }~s^2 = n.</me>
    For example, 4 is a square root of 16, because <m>4^2=16</m>. Since <m>(-4)^2=16</m>, we can say that <m>-4</m> is a square root of 16 as well. We use the radical sign <m>\sqrt{  }</m> to denote the square root of a number. By convention, we will use the positive answer when calculating a square root if there are two choices.
    There are several other kinds of roots, one of which is called the <term>cube root</term><idx>cube root</idx>, denoted by <m>\sqrt[3]{n}</m>. We define the cube root as follows.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Cube Roots</title><idx>cube root</idx>
<p>
    <me>b ~\text{is a cube root of}~n~\text{if}~ b ~\text{cubed (raised to the power of }3~\text{) equals}~n.</me>
    In symbols, we write
    <me>b=\sqrt[3]{n} ~\text{ if } ~ b^3=n.</me>
</p></assemblage>

<p>
    Although we cannot take the square root of a <em>negative number</em>, we can take the cube root of <em>any</em> real number. For example,
    <me>\sqrt[3]{64}=4 ~\text{ because }~ 4^3=64</me>
    and
    <me>\sqrt[3]{-27}=-3 ~\text{ because }~ (-3)^3=-27.</me>
</p>
<p>
    In the order of operations, simplifying radicals and powers comes after parentheses but before products and quotients.
</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify each expression.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol>
    </p></statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        <ol label="a">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}=3(-2)=-6</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}=2-(-5)=7</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}=\frac{6-(-3)}{2}=\frac{9}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p> It will not always be the case that the number inside a square root is a perfect square. If not, we use the following two properties to simplify the expression. Let <m>\sqrt[n]{a}</m> and <m>\sqrt[n]{b}</m> be real numbers where <m>b\neq 0</m>.</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\text{Product Rule for Radicals: }\, \sqrt[n]{a\cdot b}=\sqrt[n]{a}\cdot\sqrt[n]{b}</mrow>
    <mrow>\text{Quotient Rule for Radicals: }\, \sqrt[n]{\frac{a}{b}}=\frac{\sqrt[n]{a}}{\sqrt[n]{b}}</mrow>
</md>

<p>A simplified radical is one where the inside number does not consist of any factors that can be written as perfect powers. Given a square root, the idea is to identify the largest square factor of the inside number and then apply the property shown above. As an example, to simplify <m>\sqrt{12}</m>, notice that <m>12</m> is not a perfect square. However, <m>12</m> does have a perfect square factor, <m>12=4\cdot 3</m>. Apply the property as follows:</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    \sqrt{12}\amp=\sqrt{4\cdot 3}\\
    \amp=\sqrt{4}\cdot\sqrt{3}\\
    \amp=2\cdot\sqrt{3}\text{.}
    \end{aligned}</me>

<p>The number <m>2\sqrt{3}</m> is a simplified radical.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify the expression
        <m>\sqrt{135}</m>.
            </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <li>Begin by finding the largest perfect square factor of 135.</li>
                <li><m>\begin{aligned}
                    135 \amp=3\cdot 3\cdot 3\cdot 5\\
                    \amp=3^2\cdot 3\cdot 5\\
                    \amp=9\cdot 15.
                    \end{aligned}</m></li>
                Therefore we have
               <li> <m>\begin{aligned}
                    \sqrt{135} \amp=\sqrt{9\cdot 15}\\
                    \amp=\sqrt{9}\cdot\sqrt{15}\\
                    \amp=3\cdot\sqrt{15}.
                    \end{aligned}
                </m></li>
                
            </p>
        </solution>
    </example>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Simplify the expression
        <m>\sqrt{\frac{108}{169}}</m>.
            </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <li>Begin by finding the prime factorizations of both 108 and 169. This will enable us to easily determine the largest perfect square factors.</li>
                <li><m>\begin{aligned}
                    108 \amp=2\cdot 2\cdot 3\cdot 3\cdot 3=2^2\cdot 3^2\cdot 3,\\
                    169\amp=13\cdot 13=13^2.
                    \end{aligned}</m></li>
                <li>Therefore we have</li>
                <li><m>\begin{aligned}
                    \sqrt{\frac{108}{169}} \amp=\sqrt{\frac{2^2\cdot 3^2\cdot 3}{13^2}}\\
                    \amp=\frac{\sqrt{2^2\cdot 3^2\cdot 3}}{\sqrt{13^2}}\\
                    \amp=\frac{\sqrt{2^2}\sqrt{3^2}\sqrt{3}}{\sqrt{13^2}}\\
                    \amp=\frac{2\cdot 3\cdot \sqrt{3}}{13}\\
                    \amp=\frac{6\cdot{\sqrt{3}}}{13}.
                    \end{aligned}
                </m></li>
                
            </p>
        </solution>
    </example>

<p>A cube root is simplified if it does not contain any factors that can be written as perfect cubes. The idea is to identify the largest cube factor of the radicand and then apply the product or quotient rule for radicals. As an example, to simplify <m>\sqrt[3]{80}</m>, notice that 80 is not a perfect cube. However, <m>80=8\cdot 10</m>, so we can write</p>

<me>\begin{aligned}
    \sqrt[3]{80} \amp=\sqrt[3]{8\cdot 10}\\
    \amp=\sqrt[3]{8}\cdot\sqrt[3]{10}\\
    \amp=2\cdot\sqrt[3]{10}.
    \end{aligned}
</me>

</subsection>
</section>


<section  xml:id="Expressions-and-Formulas"><title>Algebraic Expressions and Formulas</title>
<subsection><title>Algebraic Expressions and the Distributive Property</title>
    
    <p>In algebra, letters called <term></term>variables are used to represent numbers. Combinations of variables and numbers along with mathematical operations form <term>algebraic expressions</term>, or just expressions. The following are some examples of expressions with one variable, <m>x</m>: </p>
    
    <md>
        <mrow> 2x+3,~~~ x^2-9,~~~ \frac{1}{x}+\frac{x}{x+2}, ~~~ 3\sqrt{x}+x</mrow>
        </md>
  

    <p><term>Terms</term> in an algebraic expression are separated by addition operators and <term>factors</term> are separated by multiplication operators. The numerical factor of a term is called the <term>coefficient</term>. For example, the algebraic expression <m>x^2y^2+6xy-3</m> can be thought of as <m>x^2y^2+6xy+(-3)</m> and has three terms. The first term, <m>x^2y^2</m>, represents the quantity <m>1x^2y^2=1\cdot x\cdot x\cdot y\cdot y</m> where <m>1</m> is the coefficient and <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are the variables. All of the variable factors with their exponents form the variable part of a term. If a term is written without a variable factor, then it is called a <term>constant</term> term. Below we see the components of <m>x^2y^2+6xy-3</m>. </p>
    
    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Terms</cell>
            <cell>Coefficient</cell>
            <cell>Variable Part</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>x^2y^2</m></cell>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
            <cell><m>x^2y^2</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>6xy</m></cell>
            <cell><m>6</m></cell>
            <cell><m>xy</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>-3</m></cell>
            <cell><m>-3</m></cell>
            <cell></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>

    <p>Notice that the first term has a coefficient of <m>1</m>. Since we can always multiple an expression by <m>1</m> without changing its value, we say that a term without a coefficient has a coefficient of <m>1</m>.</p>

    <p>The third term in this expression, <m>-3</m>, is called a constant term because it is written without a variable factor. While a variable represents an unknown quantity and may change, the constant term does not change. Also, notice that the constant term is <m>-3</m>, not just <m>3</m>. Since terms are defined by addition, whenever we see subtraction, we can think of it as making the coefficient negative. </p>
    
    <example><statement>
        <p>
            List all coefficients and variable parts of each term in the expression <m>10a^2-5ab-b^2</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>
         We want to think of the third term in this example, <m>-b^2</m>, as <m>-1b^2.</m>
         <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
             <row bottom="minor">
                 <cell>Terms</cell>
                 <cell>Coefficient</cell>
                 <cell>Variable Part</cell>
             </row>
             <row>
                 <cell><m>10a^2</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>a^2</m></cell>
             </row>
             <row>
                 <cell><m>-5ab</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>-5</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>ab</m></cell>
             </row>
             <row>
                 <cell><m>-b^2</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>-1</m></cell>
                 <cell><m>b^2</m></cell>
             </row>
         </tabular></sidebyside>
        </p>
    </solution>
    </example>
    
    <p>In our study of algebra, we will encounter a wide variety of algebraic expressions. Typically, expressions use the two most common variables, <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>. However, expressions may use any letter (or symbol) for a variable, even Greek letters, such as alpha (<m>\alpha</m>) and beta (<m>\beta</m>). Some letters and symbols are reserved for special constants, such as <m>\pi\approx 3.14159</m>. </p>
    
    <p>The properties of real numbers are important in our study of algebra because a variable is simply a letter that represents a real number. In particular, the <term>distributive property</term> states that if given any real numbers <m>a</m>, <m>b</m> and <m>c</m>, then
    <me> a(b+c)=ab+ac. </me> Since the order does not matter for multiplication, we can apply the distributive property on the other side as well: <me>(b+c)a=ba+ca</me> </p>
    
    <p> This property is one that we apply often when simplifying algebraic expressions. To demonstrate how it will be used, we simplify <m>2(5-3)</m> in two ways, and observe the same correct result.</p>
    
    <p>
        <md>
            <mrow>\text{Working parenthesis first: } 2(5-3)=2(2)=4,</mrow>
            <mrow>\text{Using the distributive property: } 2(5-3)=2\cdot 5-2\cdot 3=10-6=4.</mrow>
        </md>
    </p>
    
    <p>Certainly, if the contents of the parentheses can be simplified we should do that first. On the other hand, when the contents of parentheses cannot be simplified any further, we multiply every term within it by the factor outside of it using the distributive property. Applying the distributive property allows us to multiply and remove the parentheses.</p>
    
    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Simplify <m>5(-2a+5b)-2c</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p> Multiply only the terms grouped within the parentheses for which we are applying the distributive property.
            <me>\begin{aligned}
                5(-2a+5b)-2c \amp = 5\cdot (-2a)+5\cdot 5b-2c\\
                \amp = -10a+25b-2c.
                \end{aligned}</me>
        </p>
    </solution>
    </example>
    
    <p>Terms whose variable parts have the same variables with the same exponents are called <term>like terms</term>. Furthermore, constant terms are considered to be like terms. If an algebraic expression contains like terms, we can apply the distributive property as follows:</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
    5x+7x \amp = (5+7)x = 12x\\
    4x^2+5x^2-7x^2\amp=(4+5-7)x^2=2x^2.
    \end{aligned}</me>

    <p>In other words, if the variable parts of terms are exactly the same, then we can add or subtract the coefficients to obtain the coefficient of a single term with the same variable part. This process is called <term>combining like terms</term>. For example,</p>
    
    <me>12x^2y^3+3x^2y^3=15x^2y^3.</me>
    
    <p>Notice that the variable factors and their exponents do not change. Combining like terms in this manner, so that the expression contains no other similar terms, is called <term>simplifying</term> the expression. Use this idea to simplify algebraic expressions with multiple like terms.</p>

        <example><statement>
            <p>
                Simplify <m>x^2-10x+8+5x^2-6x-1</m>.
            </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p> Identify the like terms and add the corresponding coefficients.
                <me>\begin{aligned}
                    1x^2-10x+8+5x^2-6x-1
                    = 6x^2-16x+7
                    \end{aligned}</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        
        
        <example><statement>
            <p>
                Simplify <m>a^2b^2-ab-2(2a^2b^2-7ab+1+2ab)</m>.
            </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>Before applying the distributive property, we should try to combine like terms.
                <me>\begin{aligned}
                    a^2b^2-ab-2(2a^2b^2-7ab+1+2ab)\amp=a^2b^2-ab-2(2a^2b^2-5ab+1)
                    \end{aligned}</me>
            </p>
            <p>Next we distribute <m>-2</m> and then combine like terms.
                <me>\begin{aligned}
                    a^2b^2-ab-2(2a^2b^2-5ab+1) \amp = a^2b^2-ab-4a^2b^2+10ab-2\\
                    \amp = -3a^2b^2+9ab-2
                    \end{aligned}</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
    
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection><title>Evaluating Algebraic Expressions</title>
        
        <p>An algebraic expression can be thought of as a generalization of particular arithmetic operations. Performing these operations after substituting given values for variables is called <term>evaluating</term>. In algebra, a variable represents an unknown value. However, if the problem specifically assigns a value to a variable, then you can replace that letter with the given number and evaluate using the order of operations.</p>
        
        <example><statement>
            <p>
                Evaluate:
                    <ol label="a">
                        <li><m>5x-2
                        </m> where <m>x=\frac{2}{3}</m>,</li>
                        <li><m>y^2-y-6
                        </m> where <m>y=-4</m>.</li>
                        </ol>
                </p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p> We replace, or substitute, the given value for the variable.
                    <ol label="a">
                        <li><m>
                            \begin{aligned}5x-2 \amp= 5 \left(\frac{2}{3}\right)-2\\
                            \amp =\frac{10}{3}-\frac{2}{1}\cdot\frac{3}{3}\\
                            \amp=\frac{10-6}{3}\\
                            \amp=\frac{4}{3},
                            \end{aligned}
                        </m></li>
                        <li><m>\begin{aligned}y^2-y-6 \amp= (-4)^2-(-4)-6\\
                            \amp =16+4-6\\
                            \amp=14.
                            \end{aligned}
                        </m></li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
        </solution>
        </example>

        <example><statement>
            <p>
                Evaluate:
                    <ol label="a">
                        <li><m>1+x+x^2+x^3
                        </m> where <m>x=1</m>,</li>
                        <li><m>1+x+x^2+x^3
                        </m> where <m>x=-1</m>.</li>
                        </ol>
                </p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p> We replace, or substitute, the given value for the variable.
                    <ol label="a">
                        <li><m>
                            \begin{aligned}1+x+x^2+x^3 \amp= 1+(1)+(1)^2+(1)^3 \\
                            \amp=1+1+1+1 \\
                            \amp=4
                            \end{aligned}
                        </m></li>
                        <li><m>\begin{aligned}1+x+x^2+x^3 \amp= 1+(-1)+(-1)^2+(-1)^3 \\
                            \amp=1-1+1-1 \\
                            \amp=0
                            \end{aligned}
                        </m></li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
        </solution>
        </example>

        <p>Often algebraic expressions will involve more than one variable. </p>
        
        <example><statement>
            <p>
                Evaluate <m>a^3-8b^3</m> where <m>a=-1</m> and <m>b=\frac{1}{2}</m>.
            </p></statement>
        <solution>
            <p>After substituting in the appropriate values, we must take care to simplify using the correct order of operations.
                <me>\begin{aligned}
                    a^3-8b^3 \amp = (\alert{-1})^3-8\left(\alert{\frac{1}{2}}\right)^3\\
                    \amp = -1-8\left(\frac{1}{8}\right)\\
                    \amp = -1-1\\
                    \amp = -2
                    \end{aligned}</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
  
  <example><statement>
      <p>
          Evaluate <m>\frac{x^2-y^2}{2x-1}</m> where <m>x=-\frac{3}{2}</m> and <m>y=-3</m>.
      </p></statement>
  <solution>
      <p>
          <me>\begin{aligned}
              \frac{x^2-y^2}{2x-1} \amp = \frac{\left(\alert{-\frac{3}{2}}\right)^2-(\alert{-3})^2}{2\left(\alert{-\frac{3}{2}}\right)-1}\\
              \amp = \frac{\frac{9}{4}-9}{-3-1}
              \end{aligned}</me>
          At this point we have a complex fraction. Simplify the numerator and then multiply by the reciprocal of the denominator.
          <me>\begin{aligned}
              \amp = \frac{\frac{9}{4}-\frac{9}{1}\cdot\alert{\frac{4}{4}}}{-4}\\
              \amp = \frac{-\frac{27}{4}}{\frac{-4}{1}}\\
              \amp = \frac{-27}{4}\left(-\frac{1}{4}\right)\\
              \amp=\frac{27}{16}
              \end{aligned}</me>
      </p>
  </solution>
  </example>

<p>The answer to the previous example can be written as a mixed number, <m>\frac{27}{16}=1\frac{11}{16}</m>. Unless the original problem has mixed numbers in it, or it is an answer to a real-world application, solutions in this course will be expressed as reduced improper fractions.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>
        Evaluate <m>\sqrt{b^2-4ac}</m> where <m>a=-1,\, b=-7</m> and <m>c=\frac{1}{4}</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>
            Substitute in the appropriate values and then simplify.
            <m>\begin{aligned}
                \sqrt{b^2-4ac} \amp = \sqrt{(\alert{-7})^2-4(\alert{-1})\left(\alert{\frac{1}{4}}\right)}\\
                \amp = \sqrt{49+4\left(\frac{1}{4}\right)}\\
                \amp = \sqrt{49+1}\\
                \amp = \sqrt{50}\\
                \amp = \sqrt{25\cdot 2}\\
                \amp = 5\sqrt{2}
                \end{aligned}</m>
        </p>
    </solution>
</example>
    
    
            
        </subsection>
            
<subsection><title>Formulas</title>
    <p>
        The main difference between algebra and arithmetic is the organized use of variables. This idea leads to reusable formulas. A <term>formula</term><idx>formula</idx> is an equation that relates several variables to describe common applications. For example, the equation
        <me>P = 2l + 2w</me>
        gives the perimeter of a rectangle in terms of its length and width.
    </p>
    
    <!--<p> INSERT PICTURE OF RECTANGLE</p>-->
    <p>
        Suppose we have some wire fence to enclose an exercise area for rabbits, and we would like to see what dimensions are possible for different rectangles with that perimeter. In this case, it would be more useful to have a formula for the length of the rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width. We can find such a formula by solving the perimeter formula for <m>l</m> in terms of <m>P</m> and <m>w</m>.
        <md>
            <mrow>2l + 2w \amp= P \amp\amp\text{Subtract }2 w \text{ from both sides}</mrow>
            <mrow>2l \amp= P - 2w \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 2}</mrow>
            <mrow>l \amp= \frac{P - 2w}{2}</mrow>
        </md>
        The result is a new formula that gives the length of a rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width.
    </p>
    
    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Solve <m>3x - 5y = 40</m> for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>
            We isolate <m>y</m> on one side of the equation.
            <md>
                <mrow>
                    3x - 5y \amp = 40\amp\amp\text{Subtract }3x \text{ from both sides.}
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                    -5y \amp = 40 - 3x\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }-5.
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                    \frac{-5y}{-5} \amp = \frac{40 - 3x}{-5}\amp\amp\text{Simplify both sides.}
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                    y \amp = -8 + \frac{3}{5}x
                </mrow>
            </md>
        </p>
    </solution></example>
    
    <p>There are many real world applications for which we can use formulas. One such useful formula is that which relates Fahrenheit to Celsius.</p>
    
    <example><statement>
        <p>
            The formula <m>5F = 9C + 160</m> relates the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit, <m>F</m>, to the temperature in degrees Celsius, <m>C</m>. Solve the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>
            We begin by isolating the term that contains <m>C</m>.
            <md>
                <mrow>
                    5F \amp= 9C + 160 \amp\amp\text{Subtract 160 from both sides.}
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                    5F - 160 \amp = 9C \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 9.}
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                    \frac{5F - 160}{9} \amp =C
                </mrow>
            </md>
            We can also write the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m> as <m>C = \dfrac{5}{9}F - \dfrac{160}{9}</m>.
        </p>
    </solution></example>


    <p> Formulas can be found in a multitude of subjects. One especially useful everyday application is that of percents. For example, simple interest <m>I</m> is given by the formula <m>I=prt</m> where <m>p</m> represents the principal amount invested at an annual interest rate <m>r</m> (as a decimal, not a percent) for <m>t</m> years.</p>

    <example><statement>
        <p>
            Calculate the simple interest earned on a <m>2</m>-year investment of $<m>1250</m> at an annual interest rate of <m>3.75</m>.
        </p></statement>
    <solution>
        <p>
            We must convert <m>3.75</m>% to a  decimal number before using it in the formula: <me>r=3.75\text{%}=0.0375</me> We also know that <m>p=$1235</m> and <m>t=2</m>, so
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                I\amp=prt \\ \amp=(\alert{1250})(\alert{0.0375})(\alert{2}) \\ \amp= 93.75
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
            The simple interest earned is <m>$93.75</m>.
        </p>
    </solution></example>
    
    </subsection>

</section>







</chapter> 








<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
