<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->




<chapter xml:id="Linear-Equations-and-Modeling"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Linear Equations and Modeling</title>

    <introduction>
        
            <p>In this chapter, we'll discuss the most basic form an equation can be, a linear equation. Many of the ideas you learn about linear equations like inputs, outputs, slope, intercepts, etc. are all qualities that other equations have in one way, shape, or form. Therefore, learning these things for linear equations means you'll easily be able to learn them for more complicated equations!</p>

            <p> One application of linear equations in the professional world is in linear regression models for finance, business, and statistics. Suppose we have data like the average annual pay for a certain job from the years 1980 to 2020. We can visualize this data on a graph where the horizontal axis is years and the vertical axis is dollars for the pay. See the figure below. </p>

            <p></p>

            <image source="images/linearequations1.png" width="90%"><description>Random data</description></image>

            <p>
            What linear regression provides us is a line that draws the trend of the data. Therefore, we can make educated estimates on how much this particular job will make in the next year or 10 years down that line. The slope and other properties about this line can also be useful information, and so it's important to know what these properties are and this chapter will be the introduction!
            </p>

            <p></p>

            <image source="images/linearequations2.png" width="90%"><description>Linear Data</description></image>
            
    </introduction>


<section xml:id="Linear-Equations"><title>Linear Equations</title>
<introduction>
<p>In the previous chapter, we explored algebraic expressions. In this section, we will introduce a new type of mathematical statement known as <term>equations</term>. In particular, we will look at <term>linear equations</term> and how to solve them.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>define <term>equations</term> and what it means for an equation to be <term>linear</term></p></li>
        <li><p>solve linear equations in one variable and identify the number of solutions</p></li>
        <li><p>manipulate linear equations in two variables</p></li>
        <li><p>use <term>formulas</term> for real-world applications</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
		<li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108185&amp;node=34303331&amp;a=64605644&amp;autoplay=1">What is an Equation and a Solution, and How to Solve Linear Equations</url></li>
		<li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108183&amp;node=34303344&amp;a=96179413&amp;autoplay=1">Number of Solutions and Multiple Variables</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>



<p>An <term>equation</term> is a mathematical statement that two expressions are equal, such as <m>3x-12=0</m>. A <term>solution</term> to an equation is any set of values that can replace the variables to produce a true statement. The variable in the equation <m>3x-12=0</m> is <m>x</m> and the solution is <m>x=4</m>. To verify this, substitute the value 4 in for <m>x</m> and check that you get a true statement:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>3x-12 \amp =0</mrow>
    <mrow>3(\alert{4})-12 \amp=0</mrow>
    <mrow>12-12\amp =0</mrow>
    <mrow>0\amp =0 \ \checkmark</mrow>
</md>

<p>In this chapter, we are particularly interested in <term>linear</term>, or first-degree, equations. Linear equations are equations that can be written so that every term is either a constant or a constant times a single variable with no exponent. For example,</p>

<me>y=-5,\: \: \: y=4x,\: \: \: 2x+4=13,\: \: \: y=14-2x,\: \: \: y=13x+9-3x</me>

<p>There are a few things worth noticing among these examples. First, notice that the last equation above is linear, even though it is not in its simplified form. All the terms <m>13x, 9, -3x</m> are either constants or constants times the variable <m>x</m>. If we simplify the equation, we have <m>y=10x+9</m>, and again, the terms <m>10x</m> and <m>9</m> are a constant times the variable and a constant, satisfying the conditions for a linear equation. Second, a linear equation can have one variable or many: <m>y=-5</m> is a linear equation in one variable, while <m>y=4x</m> is a linear equation in two variables.</p>

<p>Some examples of equations that are NOT linear are:</p>


<me>y=x^3,\: \: \:  y=-4x^2+3,\: \: \:  y=3x-17+5x^3,\: \: \:  y=\sqrt{x-4},\: \: \:  y=\frac{1}{x}+2, \: \: \: y=2x^x</me>
</introduction>


<subsection><title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

<p>To solve an equation we can generate simpler equations that have the same solutions. Equations that have identical solutions are called <term>equivalent equations</term>. For example,
    <me>3x - 5 = x + 3</me>
and
    <me>2x = 8</me>
are equivalent equations because the solution of each equation is <m>4</m>. Often we can find simpler equivalent equations by undoing in reverse order the operations performed on the variable.</p>

<p>By the end of this section, we will consider linear equations in more than one variable, but we will first focus on solving linear equations in a single variable.</p>

<p>The following list provides important rules for solving linear equations.</p>

<assemblage><title>To Generate Equivalent Equations</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li><p>We can add or subtract the <em>same</em> number on <em>both</em> sides of an equation.</p></li>
    <li><p>We can multiply or divide <em>both</em> sides of an equation by the <em>same</em> number (except zero).</p></li>
</ol></p>
</assemblage>

<p>Applying either of these rules produces a new equation equivalent to the old one and thus preserves the solution. We use the rules to isolate the variable on one side of the equation.</p>

<example>
    <statement>
        <p>Solve the equation <m>3x - 5 = x + 3</m>.</p>
    </statement>
    <solution>
        <p>We first collect all the variable terms on one side of the equation, and the constant terms on the other side.
        <md>
            <mrow>
                3x - 5 \alert{{}- x} \amp = x + 3 \alert{{}- x}\amp\amp \text{Subtract }x \text{ from both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x - 5 \amp = 3\amp\amp \text{Simplify.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x - 5 \alert{{}+ 5} \amp = 3 \alert{{}+ 5}\amp\amp \text{Add 5 to both sides.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                2x \amp = 8 \amp\amp\text{Simplify.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                \frac{2x}{\alert{2}}\amp =\frac{8}{\alert{2}}\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 2.}
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
                x\amp = 4\amp\amp\text{Simplify.}
            </mrow>
            </md>
        The solution is <m>4</m>. (You can check the solution by substituting <m>4</m> into the original equation to show that you get a true statement as the result.)</p>
    </solution>
    </example>

<p>The following steps should enable you to solve any linear equation. Of course, you may not need all the steps for a particular equation.</p>

<assemblage><title>To Solve a Linear Equation</title>
<p>
    <ol label="1">
        <li><p>Simplify each side of the equation separately.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p>Apply the distributive law to remove parentheses.</p></li>
            <li><p>Combine like terms.</p></li>
        </ol></p></li>
        <li><p>By adding appropriate terms to both sides of the equation or subtracting appropriate terms from both sides of the equation, get all the variable terms on one side and all the constant terms on the other.</p></li>
        <li><p>Divide both sides of the equation by the coefficient of the variable.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve <m>3(2x - 5) - 4x = 2x - (6 - 3x)</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We begin by simplifying each side of the equation.
    <md>
        <mrow>
            3(2x - 5) - 4x \amp = 2x - (6 - 3x) \amp\amp\text{Apply the distributive law.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            6x - 15 - 4x \amp= 2x - 6 + 3x \amp\amp\text{Combine like terms on each side.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            2x - 15 \amp= 5x - 6
        </mrow>
    </md>
    Next, we collect all the variable terms on the left side of the equation, and all the constant terms on the right side.
    <md>
        <mrow>
            2x - 15 \alert{- 5x} \amp= 5x - 6 \alert{- 5x} \amp\amp\text{Subtract }5x \text{ from both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            -3x - 15 \alert{+ 15} \amp= - 6 \alert{+ 15} \amp\amp\text{Add } 15 \text{ to both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            -3x \amp= 9
        </mrow>
    </md>
    Finally, we divide both sides of the equation by the coefficient of the variable.
    <md>
        <mrow>
            -3x \amp= 9 \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }-3.
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            x \amp =-3
        </mrow>
    </md>
    The solution is <m>-3</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>We will often come across the need to solve linear equations with fraction or decimal coefficients. In this case, we can "clear" the denominators by multiplying both sides of the equation by the least common multiple of the denominators, as shown in the following example.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve <m>\frac{p-2}{3}+\frac{p}{4}=\frac{1}{2}</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We begin by finding the least common multiple of the three denominators: LCM<m>(3,4,2)=12</m>. Then we multiply both sides of the equation by <m>12</m>, and continue solving as normal.
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \frac{p-2}{3}+\frac{p}{4}\amp =\frac{1}{2}\\
        (\alert{12})\left(\frac{p-2}{3}+\frac{p}{4}\right)\amp =(\alert{12})\frac{1}{2}\\
        \frac{12(p-2)}{3}+\frac{12p}{4}\amp =\frac{12}{2}\\
        4(p-2)+3p\amp =6\\
        4p-8+3p\amp =6\\
        7p-8\amp = 6\\
        7p\amp =14\\
        p\amp =2
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    The solution is <m>p=2</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>When we have decimal coefficients, it is sometimes easier to multiply through by <m>10,100</m>, etc. before solving the equation.</p>
<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve <m>0.04x+0.08x=-0.1+0.17x</m>.</p>
  </statement>
  <solution>
    <p>As always, our first step is to combine like terms.
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        0.04x+0.08x \amp= -0.1+0.17x \\
        0.12x \amp= -0.1+0.17x
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    Since the decimal coefficients have up to <m>2</m> decimal places, we will multiply each side of the equation by <m>100</m> before solving the equation.
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
            0.12x \amp =-0.1+0.17x\\
            (\alert{100})(0.12x) \amp =(\alert{100})(-0.1+0.17x)\\
            2x\amp =-10+17x\\
            -5x\amp =-10\\
            x\amp =2
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    The solution is <m>x=2</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Number of Solutions to Linear Equations of One Variable.</title>
<p>
Not all linear equations have one solution. Although all of the examples above of linear equations with one variable have one solution, there are two other possible scenarios. Firstly, an equation of one variable which has equivalent expressions on both sides of the equals sign has infinitely many solutions. For example,
<me>3x-2 = 3x-2, \hspace{1cm} x=x, \hspace{.5cm}\text{and}\hspace{.5cm} 2(x+1) = 2x+2 </me>
all have infinitely many solutions. In this situation, any values we substitute for the variables will result in a true statement. Secondly, an equation which has two expressions that are not equal for any values of the variables has no solution. For example,
<me> 7x+2 = 7x+10, \hspace{1cm} 17 = 0, \hspace{.5cm}\text{and}\hspace{.5cm} 2(8x+3) = 16x -5 </me>
all have no solutions. Here, no matter what values we substitute for the variables we will receive a false statement.
</p>
<p>
The number of solutions to a linear equation may not be immediately obvious. To determine the number of solutions, follow the procedures above for solving a linear equation. If at any point we have a statement which we recognize as always true or always false, then we know the equation has infinitely many or zero solutions, respectively. Else, we will finish solving the equation to determine the single solution.
</p>

  <example><statement>
      <p>
Solve each equation. Determine whether there is one solution, infinitely many solutions, or no solutions.
<ol>
<li><p><m>5(7-2x) +1 = -10x + 25</m></p></li>
<li><p><m>6x = 12 - (x-7)</m></p></li>
<li><p><m>-36-12x = -3(12+4x)</m></p></li>
</ol>
      </p></statement>
  <solution>
    <ol>
    <li><md>
        <mrow> 5 (7 - 2x) +1 \amp= -10x + 25 \amp\amp \text{Apply the distributive property.}</mrow>
        <mrow> 35 - 10x +1 \amp= -10x + 25 \amp\amp \text{Combine like terms.}</mrow>
        <mrow> -10x+36 \amp= -10x + 25 </mrow>
    </md>
    <p>Since <m>-10x+36</m> is not equal to <m>-10x+25</m> for any value of <m>x</m>, this equation has no solution.</p></li>
    <li><md>
        <mrow> 6x\amp= 12 - (x-7) \amp\amp \text{Apply the distributive property.}</mrow>
        <mrow> 6x \amp= 12-x+7 \amp\amp \text{Combine like terms.}</mrow>
        <mrow> 6x \amp= -x+19 \amp\amp \text{Move variable terms to one side.}</mrow>
        <mrow> 7x \amp= 19 \amp\amp \text{Divide by coefficient on variable.}</mrow>
        <mrow> x \amp=\frac{19}{7}</mrow>
    </md>
    <p>This equation has exactly one solution, <m>x=\frac{19}{7}</m>.</p></li>
    <li><md>
        <mrow> -36-12x \amp= -3(12+4x) \amp\amp \text{Apply the distributive property.}</mrow>
        <mrow> -36-12x \amp= -36-12x</mrow>
    </md>
    <p>It is always the case that <m>-36-12x = -36-12x</m>, regardless of the value of <m>x</m>. In other words, this equation has infinitely many solutions.</p></li>
    </ol>

  </solution></example>





  <example><statement>
      <p>
          Solve <m>  0.3x+1.4=-0.6x-2.2</m>.
      </p></statement>
  <solution>
      <p><me>\begin{aligned}
            0.3x+1.4 \amp= -0.6x-2.2 \amp\amp\text{Multiply both sides by }10\text{ to clear the decimals.}\\
            3x+14 \amp= -6x-22 \amp\amp\text{Add }6x \text{ to both sides.}\\
            9x+14 \amp= -22 \amp\amp\text{Subtract }14\text{ from both sides.}\\
            9x \amp= -36 \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 9}\\
            x \amp= -4
        \end{aligned}
      </me>
      This equation has exactly one solution, <m>x=-4</m>.
      </p>
  </solution></example>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Linear Equations and Formulas with Multiple Variables</title>

<p>Up to this point, we have only solved linear equations in one variable. Sometimes we will encounter a linear equation in more than one variable; although we cannot necessarily find an explicit solution, it may be helpful to solve such equations for particular variables.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve the equation <m>y=3(x+8)</m> for <m>x</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To solve for <m>x</m>, we can use the same processes as before: we first simplify both sides, and then isolate <m>x</m>.</p>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
            y \amp= 3(x+8) \amp\amp\text{Apply the distributive property.} \\
            y \amp= 3x+24 \amp\amp\text{Subtract 24 from both sides.} \\
            y-24 \amp= 3x\amp\amp\text{Divide by 3.} \\
            \dfrac{y-24}{3} \amp= x
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Solving an equation for a given variable is particularly helpful when dealing with formulas. A <term>formula</term> is an equation that reflects a real-world situation. For example, <me>P = 2L + 2W</me> gives the perimeter of a rectangle in terms of its length and width.</p>

<image source="images/perimeter-rectangle.png" width="45%"></image>


<p>Suppose we have some wire fence to enclose an exercise area for rabbits, and we would like to see what dimensions are possible for different rectangles with that perimeter. In this case, it would be more useful to have a formula for the length of the rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width. We can find such a formula by solving the perimeter formula for <m>L</m> in terms of <m>P</m> and <m>W</m>.
<md>
    <mrow>
        2L + 2W \amp= P \amp\amp\text{Subtract }2W \text{ from both sides}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        2L \amp= P - 2W \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 2}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        L \amp= \frac{P - 2W}{2}
    </mrow>
</md>
The result is a new formula that gives the length of a rectangle in terms of its perimeter and its width.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve <m>3x - 5y = 40</m> for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We isolate <m>y</m> on one side of the equation.</p>
    <md>
        <mrow>
            3x - 5y \amp = 40\amp\amp\text{Subtract }3x \text{ from both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
                    -5y \amp = 40 - 3x\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }-5.
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
                    \frac{-5y}{-5} \amp = \frac{40 - 3x}{-5}\amp\amp\text{Simplify both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
                    y \amp = -8 + \frac{3}{5}x
        </mrow>
    </md>
</solution>
</example>

<p>There are many real world applications for which we can use formulas. One such useful formula is that which relates Fahrenheit to Celsius.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>The formula <m>5F = 9C + 160</m> relates the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit, <m>F</m>, to the temperature in degrees Celsius, <m>C</m>. Solve the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We begin by isolating the term that contains <m>C</m>.</p>
    <md>
        <mrow>
            5F \amp= 9C + 160 \amp\amp\text{Subtract 160 from both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            5F - 160 \amp = 9C \amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 9.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            \frac{5F - 160}{9} \amp =C
        </mrow>
    </md>
    <p>We can also write the formula for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m> as <m>C = \dfrac{5}{9}F - \dfrac{160}{9}</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Formulas can be found in a multitude of subjects. One especially useful everyday application is that of percents. For example, simple interest <m>I</m> is given by the formula <m>I=prt</m> where <m>p</m> represents the principal amount invested at an annual interest rate <m>r</m> (as a decimal, not a percent) for <m>t</m> years.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Calculate the simple interest earned on a <m>2</m>-year investment of $<m>1250</m> at an annual interest rate of <m>3.75</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We must convert <m>3.75</m>% to a  decimal number before using it in the formula: <me>r=3.75\text{%}=0.0375</me> We also know that <m>p=$1235</m> and <m>t=2</m>, so</p>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        I\amp=prt \\ \amp=(\alert{1250})(\alert{0.0375})(\alert{2}) \\ \amp= 93.75
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    <p>The simple interest earned is <m>$93.75</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>



<exercises>
<exercise>

    <title>Verifying Solutions</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/true_false_solutionsJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Definition of Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/linear_in_x.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve1JustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve3JustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve5JustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve6JustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve_no_solutionJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Linear Equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve_all_solutionJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Formulas</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve_volumeJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Formulas</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/solve_temperatureJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Converting Temperatures</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/convert_tempsJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Simple Interest</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/simple_interestJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Train</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/trainJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Tank</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/tankJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Commissions</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_equations/commissionsJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>


</exercises>







</section>


<section xml:id="Linear-Inequalities"><title>Linear Inequalities </title>
<introduction>
<p>In the previous section, we talked about linear <em>equations</em>, which are mathematical statements that indicate that two expressions are equal. But what if we would like to compare expressions that are different "sizes"?</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
    <p><ul>
        <li><p>solve linear <term>inequalities</term></p></li>
        <li><p>represent solutions to inequalities using a variety of representations</p></li>
    </ul></p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
		<li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108191&amp;node=34303337&amp;a=118414985&amp;autoplay=1">What is an Inequality and How to Solve a Linear Inequality, Notation and Graphs</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

</introduction>

<subsection><title>Linear Inequalities</title>

<p>The symbol <m>\gt</m> is called an <term>inequality symbol</term><idx>inequality symbol</idx>, and the statement <m>a\gt b</m> is called an <term>inequality</term><idx>inequality</idx>. There are four inequality symbols:
<md>
    <mrow>
        \amp\gt \amp\amp\text{is greater than}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        \amp\lt \amp\amp\text{is less than}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        \amp\ge \amp\amp\text{is greater than or equal to}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        \amp\le \amp\amp\text{is less than or equal to}
    </mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>Inequalities that include the symbols <m>\gt</m> or <m>\lt</m> are called <term>strict inequalities</term><idx>strict inequalities</idx>; those that include <m>\ge</m> or <m>\le</m> are called <term>nonstrict</term><idx>nonstrict</idx>.</p>

<p>If an inequality has one or more variables in it, a <term>solution</term> of that inequality is any set of values that can replace the variables to produce a true statement. For example, <m>3</m> is a solution for <m>2x>2</m> since <m>2\cdot3>2</m> is a true statement. However, <m>3</m> is not the only solution! In fact, any number greater than <m>1</m> is a solution. While linear equations have exactly one, zero, or infinitely many solutions, linear inequalities can have much more complex solution sets.</p>

<p>Solving linear inequalities is very similar to solving linear equalities. The main difference is in multiplying and dividing: if we multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a negative number, the direction of the inequality must be reversed. For example, if we multiply both sides of the inequality <me>2\lt 5</me> by <m>-3</m>, we get
<md>
    <mrow>
        \alert{-3}(2) \amp\gt \alert{-3}(5)\amp\amp \text{Change inequality symbol from }\lt \text{ to }\gt.
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        -6 \amp\gt -15.
    </mrow>
</md>
Because of this property, the rules for solving linear equations must be revised slightly for solving linear inequalities.</p>

<assemblage><title>To Solve a Linear Inequality</title>
<p>
<ol label="1">
    <li><p>We may add the same number to both sides of an inequality or subtract the same number from both sides of an inequality without changing its solutions.</p></li>
    <li><p>We may multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a <em>positive</em> number.</p></li>
    <li><p>If we multiply or divide both sides of an inequality by a <em>negative</em> number, we must <em>reverse the direction of the inequality symbol</em>.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Solve the inequality <m>4 - 3x \ge -17</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Use the rules above to isolate <m>x</m> on one side of the inequality.
    <md>
        <mrow>
            4 - 3x \amp\ge -17\amp\amp\text{Subtract 4 from both sides.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            -3x \amp\ge -21\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }-3.
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            x \amp\le 7
        </mrow>
    </md>
    Notice that we reversed the direction of the inequality when we divided by <m>-3</m>. Any number less than or equal to <m>7</m> is a solution of the inequality.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>A <term>compound inequality</term><idx>compound inequality</idx> involves two inequality symbols. To solve a compound inequality, we use the same steps as before, applying the operations on all three "sides" of the inequality symbols.</p>

<example xml:id="example-compound-inequality">
<statement>
    <p>Solve <m>4 \le 3x + 10 \le 16</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>We isolate <m>x</m> by performing the same operations on all three sides of the inequality.
    <md alignment="alignat">
        <mrow>
            4 \amp{}\le{} 3x\amp {}+{}\amp 10 \amp{}\le{} 16\hphantom{blank} \amp\text{Subtract }10\text{ from each piece.}
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            -6 \amp{}\le{} \amp 3x\amp {}{}\amp {}\le{} 6\hphantom{blank} \amp\text{Divide each piece by }3.
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            -2 \amp{}\le{} \amp x\amp {}{}\amp{}\le{} 2\hphantom{blank}\amp
        </mrow>
    </md>
    The solutions are all numbers between <m>-2</m> and <m>2</m>, inclusive.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<warning>
    <p>Notice in the previous example that in a compound inequality, both of the inequality symbols are in the same "direction". You typically would not see something like <m>4\lt x \geq 8</m> or <m>-3\geq x \leq 2</m>.</p>
</warning>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Interval Notation</title>
<p>A common way to represent solutions of an inequality is with <term>interval notation</term>. An interval is a set that consists of all the real numbers between two numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>.</p>

<p>The set <m>-2 \le x \le 2</m> includes its endpoints <m>-2</m> and <m>2</m>, so we call it a <term>closed interval</term><idx>closed interval</idx>, and we denote it by <m>[-2, 2]</m> (see <xref ref="fig-numline-closed-vs-open" text="type-global"/>a). The square brackets tell us that the endpoints are included in the interval. An interval that does not include its endpoints, such as <m>-2 \lt x \lt 2</m>, is called an <term>open interval</term><idx>open interval</idx>, and we denote it with round brackets, <m>(-2, 2)</m> (see <xref ref="fig-numline-closed-vs-open" text="type-global"/>b).</p>

 <figure xml:id="fig-numline-closed-vs-open">
    <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-numline-closed-vs-open.svg"><description>closed interval and open interval</description></image>
</figure>

<warning>
    <p>Do not confuse the open interval <m>(-2, 2)</m> with the point <m>(-2, 2)</m>! The notation is the same, so you must decide from the context whether an interval or a point is being discussed.</p>
</warning>

<p>We can also discuss <term>infinite intervals</term><idx>infinite intervals</idx>, such as <m>x\lt 3</m> and <m>x\ge -1</m>, shown in <xref ref="fig-numline-infinite-intervals" text="type-global"/>. We denote the interval <m>x\lt 3</m> by <m>(-\infty, 3)</m>, and the interval <m>x\ge -1</m> by <m>[-1, \infty)</m>. The symbol <m>\infty</m>, for infinity, does not represent a specific real number but rather indicates that the interval continues forever along the real line. We always use round brackets next to <m>\pm\infty</m> in infinite intervals.</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-numline-infinite-intervals">
    <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-numline-infinite-intervals.svg"  width="70%"><description>infinite intervals</description></image>
</figure>

<p>Finally, we can combine two or more intervals into a larger set. For example, the set consisting of <m>x\lt -1</m> or <m>x\gt 2</m>, shown in <xref ref="fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals" text="type-global"/>, is the <term>union</term><idx>union</idx> of two intervals and is denoted by <m>(-\infty,-2) \cup (2,\infty)</m>.</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals">
    <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-numline-disjoint-infinite-intervals.svg"  width="70%"><description>number line with two disjoint infinite intervals</description></image>
</figure>

<p>Many solutions of inequalities are intervals or unions of intervals.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Write each of the solution sets with interval notation and graph the solution set on a number line.
    <ol label="a">
        <li><p><m>3 \le x \lt 6</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>x \ge -9</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>x\le 1 ~\text{ or }~ x\gt 4</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>-8 \lt x \le -5 ~\text{ or }~ -1 \le x \lt 3</m></p></li>
    </ol>
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>
    <ol label="a">
        <li><p><m>[3, 6)</m>. This is called a <term>half-open</term><idx>half-open</idx> or <term>half-closed</term><idx>half-closed</idx> interval. (See <xref ref="fig-half-open-interval" text="type-global"/>.)</p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-half-open-interval">
            <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-half-open-interval.svg"  width="70%"><description>half-open interval</description></image>
        </figure>
        </li>
        <li><p><m>[-9,\infty)</m>. We always use round brackets next to the symbol <m>\infty</m> because <m>\infty</m> is not a specific number and is not included in the set. (See <xref ref="fig-half-closed-infinite-interval" text="type-global"/>.)</p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-half-closed-infinite-interval">
            <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-half-closed-infinite-interval.svg"  width="70%"><description>half-closed infinite interval</description></image>
        </figure>
        </li>
        <li><p><m>(-\infty, 1] \cup (4, \infty)</m>. The word <em>or</em> describes the union of two sets. (See <xref ref="fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals" text="type-global"/>.)</p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals">
            <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-disjoint-infinite-intervals.svg"  width="70%"><description>disjoint infinite intervals</description></image>
        </figure>
        </li>
        <li><p><m>(-8,-5] \cup [-1, 3)</m>. (See <xref ref="fig-disjoint-finite-intervals" text="type-global"/>.)</p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-disjoint-finite-intervals">
            <caption></caption><image source="images/fig-disjoint-finite-intervals.svg"  width="70%"><description>disjoint finite intervals</description></image>
        </figure>
        </li>
    </ol>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>




<exercises>
<exercise>

    <title>Interval Notation</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/interval_notationJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve1JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve2JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve3JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve4JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Compound Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve5JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Solving Compound Inequalities</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/solve7JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Positive, Negative, and Zero</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/positive_negativeJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Car Rentals</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/linear_inequalities/drivingJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>


</exercises>


</section>



<section  xml:id="Applications-of-Linear-Equations"><title>Applications of Linear Equations</title>
<introduction>
<p>Algebra simplifies the process of solving real-world problems. This is done by using letters to represent unknowns, restating problems in the form of equations, and by offering systematic techniques for solving those equations. In this section, we will solve several types of real world problems using algebra.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>translate verbal descriptions into equations</p></li>
        <li><p>write and solve linear equations to represent real world applications</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
		<li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108188&amp;node=34303346&amp;a=155532008&amp;autoplay=1">Translate Verbal Descriptions into Equations, A Few Examples</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<p>To solve problems using algebra, first translate the wording of the problem into mathematical statements that describe the relationships between the given information and the unknowns. Usually, this translation to mathematical statements is the difficult step in the process. The key to the translation is to carefully read the problem and identify certain key words and phrases.</p>


<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell>Key Words</cell>
        <cell>Translation</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><alert>Sum</alert>: increased by, more than, plus, added to, total</cell>
        <cell><m>+</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><alert>Difference</alert>: decreased by, subtracted from, less, minus</cell>
        <cell><m>-</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><alert>Product:</alert> multiplied by, of, times, twice</cell>
        <cell><m>\cdot</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><alert>Quotient:</alert> divided by, ratio, per</cell>
        <cell><m>\div</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><alert>Equals:</alert> is, total, result</cell>
        <cell><m>=</m></cell>
    </row>
</tabular></sidebyside>

<p>When translating sentences into mathematical statements, be sure to read the sentence several times and parse out the key words and phrases. It is important to first identify what needs to be represented by a variable, and then specify what that variable will be. For instance, if we are solving a word problem that asks us to find the distance that a car travelled, we likely will want to define a variable to represent the distance the car travelled. It is important to be specific and include units if applicable: it is better to say "<m>d=</m>the distance travelled by the car in miles" than simply saying "<m>d=</m>distance".</p>

<p>In the previous paragraph, we chose the variable <m>d</m> to represent distance. You can choose any letter for your variables, but it can be helpful to chose a letter that aligns with what the variable represents (such as <m>d</m> for distance, <m>t</m> for time, etc.). However, we often just use <m>x</m>. As long as you clearly define your variables, it does not matter what variables you use.</p>

<p>Before we work with word problems, we will first practice translating simple sentences into equations.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>
        Write an equation for the sequence of operations to describe each situation below.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>x</m> is <m>9</m> more than <m>y</m>.</p></li>
            <li><p>Half of <m>x</m> is <m>y</m>.</p></li>
            <li><p><m>x</m> is <m>30\%</m> of <m>y</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>In all of these examples, it can be helpful to think of the word "is" as the equals sign.
        <ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>x</m> is <m>9</m> more than <m>y</m> means that <m>x=y+9</m>.</p></li>
            <li><p>Half of <m>x</m> is <m>y</m> means that <m>\frac{1}{2}x=y</m>.</p></li>
            <li><p><m>x</m> is <m>30\%</m> of <m>y</m> means that <m>x=0.30y</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
    </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>We will now expand these ideas to solve a word problem using a linear equation.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>
        When 6 is subtracted from twice the sum of a number and 8, the result is 5. Find the number.
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>
        Let <m>n</m> represent the unknown number. In the sentence above, "the sum of a number and 8" is represented by <m>n+8</m>, so "twice the sum of a number and 8" is <m>2(n+8)</m>. Next, "6 subtracted from twice the sum of a number and 8" would be 6 less than this, so it is <m>2(n+8)-6</m>. Finally, we are told that the result is 5; in other words, this expressions is equal to 5:
        <me>
            2\cdot (n+8)-6=5
        </me>
        Now that we have translated the problem into a linear equation, we can solve for <m>n</m>:
        <me>
        \begin{aligned}
            2(n+8)-6 \amp = 5\\
            2n+16-6\amp = 5\\
            2n+10\amp =5\\
            2n\amp = -5\\
            n\amp = -\frac{5}{2}
        \end{aligned}
        </me>
        We should always check our answer to be sure that we didn't make a mistake in setting up or solving the problem. The sum of <m>-\frac{5}{2}</m> and <m>8</m> is <m>-\frac{5}{2}+8=\frac{11}{2}</m>. Twice this is <m>\frac{11}{2}\cdot2=11</m>, and <m>6</m> less than this is <m>5</m>. Since we got the desired result, we know that our answer is correct. The unknown numbers is <m>-\frac{5}{2}</m>.
        </p>
</solution>
</example>

<p> General guidelines for setting up and solving word problems follow:</p>

<assemblage><title>Guidelines for Word Problems</title><idx>word problems</idx>
<p>
    <ol label="1">
        <li>
            Read the problem several times, identify the key words and phrases, and organize the given information.
        </li>
        <li>
            Identify the variables by assigning a letter or expression to the unknown quantities.
        </li>
        <li>
            Translate and set up an algebraic equation that models the problem.
        </li>
        <li>
            Solve the resulting algebraic equation.
        </li>
        <li>
            Finally, answer the question in sentence form and make sure it makes sense (check it).
        </li>
    </ol>
</p>
</assemblage>


<p>All of the equations in the following examples can be set up using only one variable. We can avoid two variables by looking for a relationship between the unknowns. </p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>A rectangle has a perimeter measuring <m>92</m> meters. The length is <m>2</m> meters less than <m>3</m> times the width. Find the dimensions of the rectangle.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The sentence "The length is <m>2</m> meters less than <m>3</m> times the width" gives us the relationship between the two important quantities, the length and the width. Let <m>w</m> represent the width of the rectangle. Since the length is <m>2</m> meters less than <m>3</m> times the width, the length must be <m>3w-2</m>.</p>
    <p>The sentence "A rectangle has a perimeter measuring <m>92</m> meters" suggests an algebraic set up. The perimeter of a rectangle is always the sum of twice the length and twice the width; in this example, this means that the perimeter is <me>2w+2(3w-2)</me> Since we know that the perimeter is <m>92</m> meters, we have the following equation:</p>
        <me>92=2w+2(3w-2)</me>
    <p>Once you have set up an algebraic equation with one variable, solve for the width, <m>w</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        92\amp =2w+2(3w-2) \amp \text{Distribute}\\
        92\amp =2w+6w-4 \amp\text{Combine like terms}\\
        92\amp =8w-4 \amp\text{Solve for }w\\
        96\amp =8w\\
        12\amp =w\\
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Now that we know the width, we can use the fact that the length is <m>3w-2</m> to find the length.</p>

    <me>3w-2=3(\alert{12})-2=36-2=34</me>

    <p>This means that the dimensions of the rectangle are <m>12</m> meters by <m>34</m> meters. To check, we make sure the perimeter is actually <m>92</m> meters:</p>

    <me>2(12)+2(34)=24+68=92</me>

</solution>
</example>

<p>For the rest of this section, we will explore several different categories of application problems that you might see, such as applications of interest, currency, distances, and more. </p>
</introduction>

<subsection><title>Interest Applications</title>

<p>In problems involving simple interest, it is often helpful to use the simple interest formula <m>I=prt</m> where <m>I</m> is the simple interest earned on a principle investment, <m>p</m>, with an interest rate of <m>r</m> over <m>t</m> years.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Given a <m>4.375</m>% annual interest rate, how long will it take <m>$2,500</m> to yield <m>$437.50</m> in simple interest?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Let <m>t</m> represent the time needed to earn $<m>437.50</m> at <m>4.375</m>%. Organize the information needed to use the formula for simple interest, <m>I=prt</m>.</p>

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Given interest for the time period</cell>
            <cell><m>I=</m> $<m>437.50</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>Given principal</cell>
            <cell><m>p=</m> $<m>2,500</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>Given rate</cell>
            <cell><m>r=4.375\text{%}=0.04375</m></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>

    <p>Next, substitute all of the known quantities into the formula and then solve for the only unknown, <m>t</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        I\amp = prt\\
        \alert{437.50}\amp = \alert{2500}(\alert{0.04375})t\\
        437.50\amp = 109.375t\\
        \frac{437.50}{109.375}\amp = \frac{109.375t}{109.375}\\
        4\amp = t
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>It takes <m>4</m> years for <m>$2,500</m> invested at <m>4.375</m>% to earn <m>$437.50</m> in simple interest.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Stephanie invested her total savings of <m>$12,500</m> in two accounts earning simple interest. Her mutual fund account earned <m>7</m>% last year and her CD earned <m>4.5</m>%. If her total interest for the year was <m>$670</m>, how much was in each account?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p> The sum of the money in each account is <m>$12,500</m>. When a total is involved, a common technique used to avoid two variables is to represent the second unknown as the difference of the total and the first unknown.</p>

    <p>Let <m>m</m> represent the amount invested in the mutual fund.</p>

    <p>Since the amount in the two accounts total <m>$12,500</m>, the amount in the CD must be <m>12,500-m</m>.</p>

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell>Interest earned in the mutual fund (in dollars)</cell>
            <cell><md>
                <mrow>I\amp = prt</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = m\cdot 0.07\cdot 1</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp =0.07m</mrow>
            </md></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>Interest earned in the CD (in dollars)</cell>
            <cell><md>
                <mrow>I\amp = prt</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = (12,500-m)\cdot 0.045\cdot 1</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = 0.045(12,500-m)</mrow>
            </md></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>Total Interest</cell>
            <cell><m>$670</m></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>

    <p>The total interest is the sum of the interest earned from each account.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \text{mutual fund interest}+\text{CD interest} \amp = \text{total interest}\\
        0.07m +0.045(12,500-m)\amp = 670
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>This equation models the problem with one variable. Solve for <m>m</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        0.07m+0.045(12,500-m)\amp = 670\\
        0.07m+562.5-0.045m\amp = 670\\
        0.025m+562.5\amp = 670\\
        0.025m\amp = 107.5\\
        m\amp = \frac{107.5}{0.025}\\
        m\amp =4,300
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Use <m>12,500-m</m> to find the amount in the CD.</p>

    <me>12,500-m=12,500-\alert{4300}=8,200 </me>

    <p> Stephanie invested <m>$4,300</m> at <m>7</m>% in a mutual fund and <m>$8,200</m> at <m>4.5</m>% in a CD.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Currency Applications</title>
<p> A new kind of problem we come across in applications is something we call currency problems. These problems involve finding the number of coins or bills given other information about value. It is important to be careful in defining our variables specifically - either for the number of currency or the value of the currency.</p>


<example>
<statement>
    <p>Ashley has $17.25 in her piggy bank, which has only quarters and fifty-cent pieces in it.  Ashley has nine more fifty-cent pieces than she has quarters. How many coins of each denomination does she have?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Let <m>q</m> represent the number of quarters. Since Ashley has nine more fifty-cent pieces than quarters, the number of fifty cent pieces she has is <m>q+9</m>.</p>

    <p>Since a quarter is worth <m>$0.25</m>, <m>0.25q</m> represents the value of Ashley's quarters. Similarly, since a fifty-cent piece is worth <m>$0.50</m>, <m>0.50(q+9)</m> gives the value of Ashley's fifty-cent pieces.</p>

    <p>Since Ashley has a total of <m>$17.25</m>, it must be the case that the sum of these values is <m>17.25</m>: <me>0.25q+0.50(q+9)=17.25</me> We can now solve for <m>q</m>:

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        0.25q+0.50(q+9) \amp= 17.25 \\
        0.25q+0.50q+4.50 \amp= 17.25 \\
        0.75q+4.50 \amp= 17.25 \\
        0.75q \amp= 12.75 \\
        q \amp= 17
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    Ashley has <m>17</m> quarters, and therefore <m>26</m> fifty-cent pieces.</p>
</solution>

<warning>
<p>A common mistake in currency problems is to translate nickels being worth 5 cents to their value being <m>.5</m>. As a decimal, nickels are worth <m>.05</m>!</p>
</warning>
</example>


</subsection>

<subsection><title>Mixing Applications</title>

<p>Mixture problems often include a percentage and some total amount. It is important to make a distinction between these two types of quantities. For example, if a problem states that a 10-ounce container is filled with a <m>3</m>% saline (salt) solution, then this means that the container is filled with a mixture of salt and water as follows:</p>

<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m></m></cell>
        <cell><m>Percentage</m></cell>
        <cell><m>Amount</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>Salt</m></cell>
        <cell><m>3</m>%<m>=0.03</m></cell>
        <cell><m>0.03</m> (<m>10</m> ounces)<m>=0.3</m> ounces</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>Water</m></cell>
        <cell><m>97</m>%<m>=0.97</m></cell>
        <cell><m>0.97</m> (<m>10</m> ounces)<m>=9.7</m> ounces</cell>
    </row>
</tabular></sidebyside>

<p>In other words, we multiply the percentage times the total to get the amount of each part of the mixture.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>How many milliliters of a <m>15</m>% alcohol solution must be mixed with <m>110</m> milliliters of a <m>35</m>% solution to obtain a <m>25</m>% solution?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>It is often helpful to use a table to organize your work for application problems. We will use the following table to keep track of all the different solutions in this problem:</p>

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="major">
        <cell>Solution</cell>
        <cell>Percent Alcohol</cell>
        <cell>Total Amount of Liquid</cell>
        <cell>Amount of Alcohol</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>15</m>% solution</cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="major">
        <cell><m>35</m>% solution</cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>Mixture</cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
        <cell></cell>
    </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>

    <p>Let <m>m</m> be the milliliters of the <m>15</m>% solution. To get the amount of alcohol in this part of the mixture, we multiply the percentage by the amount: <m>0.15m</m>.</p>

    <p>Likewise, to get the amount of the second part of the mixture, we multiply the percentage by the amount: <m>0.35\cdot 110=38.5</m>.</p>

    <p>Let's now think about the mixture of these two solutions. We know that we're aiming for a <m>25</m>% solution. Since there are <m>m</m> milliliters from the first solution and <m>110</m> milliliters from the second solution, the mixture will have <m>m+110</m> milliliters in it. Again, we find the amount of alcohol in the mixture by multiplying the percentage by the amount: <m>0.25(m+110)</m>. We can now fill in our table.</p>

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="major">
        <cell>Solution</cell>
        <cell>Percent Alcohol</cell>
        <cell>Total Amount of Liquid</cell>
        <cell>Amount of Alcohol</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell><m>15</m>% solution</cell>
        <cell><m>15</m>%<m>=0.15</m></cell>
        <cell><m>m</m> mL</cell>
        <cell><m>0.15(m</m> mL<m>)=0.15m</m> mL</cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="major">
        <cell><m>35</m>% solution</cell>
        <cell><m>35</m>%<m>=0.35</m></cell>
        <cell><m>110</m> mL</cell>
        <cell><m>0.35(110</m> mL<m>)=38.5</m> mL</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>Mixture</cell>
        <cell><m>25</m>%<m>=0.25</m></cell>
        <cell><m>m+110</m> mL</cell>
        <cell><m>0.25(m+110)</m> mL</cell>
    </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>

    <p>From our table, we see that the total amount of alcohol in the mixture is <m>0.25(m+110)</m>. On the other hand, we know that there are <m>0.15m</m> milliliters from the first solution and <m>38.5</m> milliliters from the second solution, for a total of <m>0.15m+38.5</m> milliliters of alcohol in the solution. We have found two different expressions for the total amount of alcohol in the mixture, so they must be equal:</p>

    <me>0.15m+38.5 = 0.25(m+110)</me>

    <p>We can now solve for <m>m</m>.</p>

    <me>\begin{aligned}
        0.15m+38.5\amp = 0.25(m+110)\\
        0.15m +38.5 \amp =0.25m+27.5\\
        38.5\amp = 0.10m+27.5\\
        11\amp =0.10m\\
        110\amp =m
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>We have found that we must mix <m>110</m> milliliters of a <m>15</m>% alcohol solution with <m>110</m> milliliters of a <m>35</m>% solution to obtain a <m>25</m>% solution.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<subsection><title>Distance Applications</title>

<p>The distance traveled is equal to the average rate times the time traveled at that rate, <m>d=r\cdot t</m>. These problems usually have a lot of data, so it helps to carefully rewrite the pertinent information as you define variables.</p>


<example>
<statement>
    <p>Two planes leave a city traveling in opposite directions. One travels at a rate of <m>530</m> mph and the other at a rate of <m>600</m> mph. How long will it take until they are <m>3672.5</m> miles apart?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Let <m>d_1</m> represent the distance travelled by the first plane in miles, and let <m>d_1</m> represent the distance travelled by the second plane in miles. The key to this problem is that the sum of their distances is the distance between them:</p>

    <image source="images/planes-distance.png" width="75%"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image>

    <p>Let <m>t</m> represent the time it takes for them to be <m>3672.5</m> miles apart (in hours); this is what we're actually looking for. The first plane travels at a rate of <m>530</m> mph, meaning that its distance is modeled by the equation
        <me> d_1=r\cdot t= 530 t</me>
    The second plane travels at a rate of <m>600</m> mph, meaning that its distance is modeled by the equation
        <me> d_2=r\cdot t= 600 t</me>
    Since the sum of their distances is the distance between them, after <m>t</m> hours the two planes will be
        <me>d_1+d_2=530t+600t=1130t</me>
    miles apart. Now, we want to know when the distance is <m>3672.5</m>. Thus we solve:
        <me>\begin{aligned}
            3672.5\amp =1130t\\
            3.25\amp =t
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    This tells us that it will take <m>3</m> hours and <m>15</m> minutes for the planes to be <m>3672.5</m> miles apart.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>



<exercises>

<exercise>

    <title>Translating verbal to equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/translateJustHint.pg"/>

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Translating verbal to equations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/translate2JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Automobile journey</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/automobile_journeyJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Mario and Luigi</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/mario_and_luigiJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Average speed</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/average_speedJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Mixing solutions</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/mixing2JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>


<exercise>

    <title>Two dogs</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/two_dogs.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Two dogs</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/two_dogs2JustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Class schedule</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/classesJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Simple Interest</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/interestJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Sales tax</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/sales_taxJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>

<exercise>

    <title>Loose change</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Applications_of_Linear_Equations/currencyJustHint.pg" />

</exercise>







</exercises>




</section>


<section  xml:id="Relations-Tables-and-Graphs"><title>Relations, Tables, and Graphs</title>
<introduction>
<p>Mathematics is often concerned with how different mathematical objects are related to one another. For example, consider the equation <m>y=x+1</m>. Since <m>x=3</m>, <m>y=4</m> is a solution to this equation, one might say that <m>x=3</m> is related to <m>y=4</m>. In this section, we will define a mathematical <term>relation</term> and explore different ways that relations can be represented.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
    <p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>define <term>relations</term></p></li>
        <li><p>represent relations with ordered pairs, tables, arrow diagrams, and graphs</p></li>
        <li><p>identify the <term>domain</term> and <term>range</term> of a relation from its different representations</p></li>
    </ul>
    </p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
	    <li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108186&amp;node=34303342&amp;a=5325634&amp;autoplay=1">The Different Ways to View a Relation</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

</introduction>

<subsection><title>Relations and their Representations</title>

<p>A <term>relation</term> is a collection of pairs of objects from two sets. Often, the objects are numbers that have been paired together in a particular way. In the context of algebra, the relations of interest are sets of <term>ordered pairs</term> <m>(x,y)</m> that are related by an algebraic equation. We call the first entry in the ordered pair the <term><m>x</m>-coordinate</term>, and the second entry the <term><m>y</m>-coordinate</term>.</p>

<p>For example, using the rule <m>y=x+1</m>, <m>x=3</m> is related to <m>y=4</m>. We would simply write that <m>(3,4)</m> is a part of this relation. Some other ordered pairs in this relation are <m>(5,6)</m>, <m>(-4,-3)</m>, and <m>(1.52,2.52)</m>.</p>

<warning><p>In the example above, the pair <m>(4,3)</m> is NOT in this relation. Ordered pairs look like <m>(x,y)</m> with the <m>x</m>-coordinate appearing first.</p></warning>

<p>If we wanted to list several ordered pairs of a relation, we could simply list them. The following is an example of a relation:
    <me>\big\{(4,6), \ (2,1), \ (0,4), \ (5,5), \ (-1,4)\big\}</me>
</p>

<note><p>The brackets "<m>\{ \ \}</m>" are used to indicate a list of mathematical objects. In this course, you will see brackets used to indicate a set of ordered pairs for a relation, as well as sets of numbers.</p></note>

<p>Two ways that we can represent a relation that are more organized than a list of ordered pairs are with tables and arrow diagrams. The table and arrow diagram for this relation are shown below.</p>

<sidebyside ><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="major">
        <cell><m>x</m></cell>
        <cell><m>y</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>4</m></cell>
        <cell><m>6</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>2</m></cell>
        <cell><m>1</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
        <cell><m>4</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>5</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>-1</m></cell>
        <cell><m>4</m></cell>
    </row>
</tabular>
<image source="images/relations-arrows.png"><description>Arrow Diagram</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>Arrow diagrams are less common than the other representations in this section, but are particularly useful when talking about functions, which will be discussed in Chapter 4.</p>

<p>The last (and perhaps most important) representation of a relation that we will discuss is a graph. For relations between sets of numbers, graphs are a visual way to represent the relationship between the numbers on a coordinate plane. The rectangular coordinate system consists of two real number lines that intersect at a right angle. The horizontal number line is often referred to as the <term><m>x</m>-axis</term>, and the vertical number line is often  referred to as the <term><m>y</m>-axis</term>. These two number lines define a flat surface called a <term>plane</term>. The intersection of the two axes is known as the <term>origin</term>, which corresponds to the point <m>(0, 0)</m>.</p>

<p>The <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-axes break the plane into four regions called <term>quadrants</term>, named using Roman numerals I, II, III, and IV, as pictured. The ordered pair <m>(x, y)</m> represents the position of points relative to the origin. For example, the ordered pair <m>(-4, 3)</m> represents the position <m>4</m> units to the left of the origin, and <m>3</m> units above in the second quadrant.</p>

<image source="images/Quadrants.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image>

<p>Returning to our previous example, the relation would be represented by the following graph:</p>

<sidebyside width="65%"><image source="images/relations-graph.png"><description>Graph of a Relation</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>Let's explore another relation: consider the absolute value, denoted <m>|x|</m>. The absolute value takes an input <m>x</m> and tells us its distance from zero. For instance, <m>|5|=5</m>, <m>|-7|=7</m>, and <m>|-112|=112</m>. Now let's consider the algebraic equations <m>y=|x|-2</m> and <m>x=|y|+1</m>. Both these equations define relations between <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> involving the absolute values. The tables below show some of the ordered pairs for each of these relations.</p>

<image source="images/SolutionsAbsValue.png"><description>Solutions to Absolute Value Equations</description></image>


<p>As ordered pairs, we can list these solutions as well.</p>

<small>
<md>
    <mrow>
        y\amp=|x|-2\text{ has solutions }{(-3,1),(-2,0),(-1,-1),(0,-2),(1,-1),(2,0),(3,1)}
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
        x\amp =|y|+1\text{ has solutions }{(4,-3),(3,-2),(2,-1),(1,0),(2,1),(3,2),(4,3)}
    </mrow>
</md>
</small>

<p>We can visually display any relation of this type on a coordinate plane by plotting the points, or ordered pairs.</p>

<image source="images/AbsValue1.png"><description>Absolute Value Graphs</description></image>

<p>The solution sets of each equation will form a relation consisting of infinitely many ordered pairs. We can use the given ordered pair solutions to estimate all of the other ordered pairs by drawing a line through the given points. Here we put an arrow on the ends of our lines to indicate that this set of ordered pairs continues without bounds.</p>

<image source="images/AbsValue2.png"><description>Absolute Value Graphs</description></image>

</subsection>

 <subsection><title>Domain and Range</title>

<p>The set consisting of all of the first components of a relation, in this case the <m>x</m>-values, is called the <term>domain</term>. And the set consisting of all second components of a relation, in this case the <m>y</m>-values, is called the <term>range</term> (or codomain). Often, we can determine the domain and range of a relation if we are given its graph.</p>

    <image source="images/AbsValue3.png"><description>Absolute Value Graphs</description></image>

<p>Here we can see that the graph of <m>y=|x|-2</m> has a domain consisting of all real numbers, <m>\mathbb{R}=(-\infty,\infty)</m>, and a range of all <m>y</m>-values greater than or equal to <m>-2</m>, <m>[-2,\infty)</m>. The domain of the graph of <m>x=|y|+1</m> consists of all <m>x</m>-values greater than or equal to <m>1</m>, <m>[1,\infty)</m>, and the range consists of all real numbers, <m>\mathbb{R}=(-\infty,\infty)</m>.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Determine the domain and range of the following relation.

        <image source="images/DomainRange1.png"><description>Vertical Line Test</description></image>
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The minimum <m>x</m>-value represented on the graph is <m>-8</m> and all others are larger. Therefore the domain consists of all <m>x</m>-values in the interval <m>[-8,\infty)</m>. The minimum <m>y</m>-value represented on the graph is <m>0</m> so the range is <m>[0,\infty)</m>.
        <image source="images/DomainRange2.png"><description>Vertical Line Test</description></image>
    The domain is given by <m>[-8,\infty)</m> and the range is <m>[0,\infty)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Determine the domain and range of the following relation.

        <me>
            \big\{(4,6), \ (2,5), \ (3,6), \ (0,0)\big\}
        </me>
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The domain is the set of first components of a relation; for this relation, the first components are
        <me>\{4, \ 2, \ 3, \ 0\}</me>
    The range is the set of the second components, which are
        <me>\{6, \ 5, \ 0\}</me>
    Notice that <m>6</m> was a second component twice. This is allowed, but we only need to list it in the range once.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<note><p>The domain and range of a relation do not indicate which components are related to one another, so the order that we list elements of the domain and range does not matter.</p></note>

</subsection>


<exercises>
<exercise>

    <title>Representations of Relations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Relations_Tables_and_Graphs/RepresentRelation-table.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Representations of Relations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Relations_Tables_and_Graphs/RepresentRelation-pairs.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Representations of Relations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Relations_Tables_and_Graphs/RepresentRelation-equation.pg"/>

</exercise>
<exercise>

    <title>Domain and Range of Relations</title>

    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Relations_Tables_and_Graphs/GiveDomainRange.pg"/>

</exercise>


</exercises>
</section>



<section xml:id="Graphs-of-Linear-Equations"><title>Graphs of Linear Equations</title>
<introduction>
<p>At the beginning of this chapter, we defined <term>linear equations</term> to be equations in which each term was either a constant or a constant times a single variable. In this section, we will look at linear equations in two variables, and, using the skills from the previous section, explores their graphs.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>generate tables to represent linear equations in two variables</p></li>
        <li><p>graph linear equations from a table</p></li>
        <li><p>graph lines from their equations</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
	    <li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108184&amp;node=34303340&amp;a=156009082&amp;autoplay=1">How to Plot Linear Equations and its Parts</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>
</introduction>

<subsection><title>Graphing Linear Equations</title>
<p>Consider the linear equation <m>8x+4y=12</m>. Before we try to graph this equation, let's generate a table of ordered pairs for this relation. To do so, we can pick any <m>x</m> values and find their corresponding <m>y</m> values, or vice versa. Some ordered pairs are shown below.</p>

<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>x</m></cell>
        <cell><m>y</m></cell>
        <cell>Ordered pair</cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>-2</m></cell>
        <cell><m>7</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(-2,7)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>-1</m></cell>
        <cell><m>5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(-1,5)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
        <cell><m>3</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(0,3)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>4</m></cell>
        <cell><m>-5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(4,-5)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>6</m></cell>
        <cell><m>-9</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(6,-9)</m></cell>
    </row>
</tabular></sidebyside>
<p>We can now plot these points. All of these points fall in a straight line; connecting the points, we get the graph of the equation <m>8x+4y=12</m>. We add arrows on either end to indicate that the graph extends indefinitely in both directions.</p>

<image source="images/graph-line-1.png" xml:id="graph-line-1"><description>Graph of <m>8x+4y=12</m></description></image>

<p>Let's create a table and graph the linear equation <m>2y-x=8</m>. Again, we start by generating a table with several ordered pairs that satisfy this equation.</p>

<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>x</m></cell>
        <cell><m>y</m></cell>
        <cell>Ordered pair</cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>-3</m></cell>
        <cell><m>2.5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(-3,2.5)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>-1</m></cell>
        <cell><m>3.5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(-1,3.5)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
        <cell><m>4</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(0,4)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>3</m></cell>
        <cell><m>5.5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(4,5.5)</m></cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><m>2</m></cell>
        <cell><m>5</m></cell>
        <cell><m>(2,5)</m></cell>
    </row>
</tabular></sidebyside>

<p>Notice that several of the ordered pairs in our table have decimal-valued coordinates. If you are randomly selecting values of <m>x</m>, this will often happen and is okay. However, if you are plotting these points by hand and cannot accurately plot decimal-valued points, you should avoid using these points. In the table above, we found two points with integer coordinates: <m>(0,4)</m> and <m>(2,5)</m>. These two points are enough to graph this equation. We can then verify that all of the decimal-valued coordinates do in fact fall on this line.</p>

<image source="images/graph-line-2.png" xml:id="graph-line-2"><description>Graph of <m>2y+x=8</m></description></image>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Intercepts of Graphs of Linear Equations</title>
<p>It is often useful to describe where the graph of a linear equation meets the <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-axes. The point where a graph intersects the <m>x</m>-axis is called the <term><m>x</m>-intercept</term> of the graph, and the point where a graph intersects the <m>y</m>-axis it called the <term><m>y</m>-intercept</term>.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Look back at the graphs of <m>8x+4y=12</m> and <m>2y-x=8</m> from earlier in this section. What are the <m>y</m>-intercepts of each of these graphs?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The <m>y</m>-intercept of <m>8x+4y=12</m> is <m>(0,4)</m>. The <m>y</m>-intercept of <m>2y-x=8</m> is <m>(0,4)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>It is not always clear from the graph what the intercepts of a line are. For example, consider the graph of the equation <m>6y-3x=-17</m>.</p>

<image source="images/graph-line-3.png" xml:id="graph-line-3"><description>Graph of <m>6y-3x=-17</m></description></image>

<p>It is not clear where exactly the line is intersecting the axes. Although we could estimate where these points lie, there is a more accurate way to find the intercepts.</p>

<p>Think about points that lie on the <m>x</m>-axis. What do these points have in common? If a point lies on the <m>x</m>-axis, it will have the form <m>(x,0)</m>; the <m>y</m>-value will always be <m>0</m>. This means that to find the <m>x</m>-intercept of a graph of a linear equation, we are looking for the <m>x</m>-value that corresponds to <m>y=0</m>. Substituting <m>y=0</m> into <m>6y-3x=-17</m>, we have
<me>
    \begin{aligned}
        6(\alert{0})-3x \amp= -17 \\
        -3x \amp= -17 \\
        x \amp= \dfrac{17}{3}
    \end{aligned}
</me>
This means that the <m>x</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>6y-3x=-17</m> is <m>(\frac{17}{3},0)</m>.</p>

<p>We can think about the <m>y</m>-intercepts similarly. Points on the <m>y</m>-axis have the form <m>(0,y)</m>, so they always have <m>x=0</m>. To find the <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>6y-3x=-17</m>, we substitute <m>x=0</m>:
<me>
    \begin{aligned}
        6y-3(\alert{0}) \amp= -17 \\
        6y \amp= -17 \\
        x \amp= -\dfrac{17}{6}
    \end{aligned}
</me>
This means that the <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>6y-3x=-17</m> is <m>(0,-\frac{17}{6})</m>.</p>

<note>
    <p>Some lines don't have an <m>x</m>-intercept, and some lines don't have a <m>y</m>-intercept. Can you draw such lines? These lines will be discussed in the next section.</p>
</note>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find the <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-intercepts of the graph of <m>6x+9y=18</m>. Verify your answers by graphing the equation.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To find the <m>x</m>-intercept, we substitute <m>y=0</m>:
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        6x+9(0) \amp= 18 \\
        6x \amp= 18 \\
        x \amp= 3
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    This means that the <m>x</m>-intercept is at <m>(3,0)</m>. For the <m>y</m>-intercept, we substitute <m>x=0</m>:
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        6(0)+9y \amp= 18 \\
        9y \amp= 18 \\
        y \amp= 2
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    Therefore the <m>y</m>-intercept is at <m>(0,2)</m>.
</p>
<image source="images/graph-line-intercepts.png" width="75%"><description>Graph of <m>6y-3x=-17</m></description></image>
</solution>
</example>
</subsection>

<exercises>
<exercise>
    <title>Graphing Points</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/identify_points1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Identifying Points</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/identify_points2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Table and Graph of a Linear Equation</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/table_and_graph_from_equation2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Intercepts and Graph of a Linear Equation</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/intercepts_and_graph_from_equation2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Intercepts and Graph of a Linear Equation</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/intercepts_and_graph_from_equation4JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Intercepts and Graph of a Linear Equation</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/graphs_of_linear_equations/intercepts_and_graph_from_equation5JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>








</exercises>











</section>



<section  xml:id="The-Slope-of-a-Line"><title>The Slope of a Line</title>
<introduction>
<p>In the previous section, we saw that the graphs of linear equations in two variables form straight lines. When graphing lines, there are two defining characteristics of the graphs: where the line sits in the plane and how the line sits in the plane. In this section, we are primarily concerned with how lines sit in the plane; that is, how steep the line is relative to the axes.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>define the <term>slope</term> of a line</p></li>
        <li><p>identify the slope of a line from its graph</p></li>
        <li><p>compute the slope of a line given two points on that line</p></li>
        <li><p>explore the different geometric possibilities of lines, including vertical and horizontal lines</p></li>
        <li><p>calculate the <term>rate of change</term> given a real world scenario modeled by a linear equation</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
		<li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108189&amp;node=34303347&amp;a=212463758&amp;autoplay=1">What is the Slope of a Line, Its Formula, and Its Meaning</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

</introduction>
<subsection><title>Meaning of Slope</title>

<p>The steepness of any incline can be measured as the ratio of the vertical change to the horizontal change. For example, a <m>5</m>% incline can be written as <m>\frac{5}{100}</m>, which means that for every 100 feet forward, the height increases 5 feet.</p>

<p> <image source="images/SlopePercentIncline.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>In mathematics, we call the incline of a line the <term>slope</term>, denoted by the letter <m>m</m>. The vertical change is called the rise and the horizontal change is called the run. Given any two points <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)</m>, we can obtain the rise and run by subtracting the corresponding coordinates.</p>


<p> <image source="images/SlopeIncline.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>This leads us to the slope formula. Given any two points <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)</m>, the slope is given by the following formula:</p>

<md>
    <mrow>\alert{\text{Slope }}= m=\frac{rise}{run}=\frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}=\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x}= \alert{\frac{\text{Change in }y}{\text{Change in }x}}\text{.}</mrow>
</md>

<p>The Greek letter delta <m>(\Delta)</m> is often used to describe the change in a quantity. Therefore, the slope is sometimes described using the notation <m>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x}</m>, which represents the change in <m>y</m> divided by the change in <m>x</m>.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find the slope of the line passing through <m>(-3, -5)</m> and <m>(2, 1)</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Given <m>(-3, -5)</m> and <m>(2, 1)</m>, calculate the difference of the <m>y</m>-values divided by the difference of the <m>x</m>-values. Take care to be consistent when subtracting the coordinates.</p>

    <p>Let <m>(x_1,y_1)=(-3,-5)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)=(2,1)</m>.</p>

    <me>
    \begin{aligned}
        m\amp = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}\\
        \amp =\frac{1-(-5)}{2-(-3)}\\
        \amp =\frac{1+5}{2+3}\\
        \amp =\frac{6}{5}
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The slope is given by <m>m=\frac{6}{5}</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>It does not matter which point you consider to be the first and second when calculating slope. However, because subtraction is not commutative, you must take care to subtract the coordinates of the first point from the coordinates of the second point in the same order. To demonstrate this we obtain the same result in the example above if we apply the slope formula with the points switched.</p>

<p>Let <m>(x_1,y_1)=(2,1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)=(-3,-5)</m>.</p>

<me>
\begin{aligned}
    m\amp = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}\\
    \amp =\frac{-5-1}{-3-2}\\
    \amp =\frac{-6}{-5}\\
    \amp =\frac{6}{5}
\end{aligned}
</me>

<p>We can verify that the slope is <m>\frac{6}{5}</m> by graphing the linear equation described in the previous example.</p>

<p> <image source="images/Slope2.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>Certainly the graph is optional - the beauty of the slope formula is that, given any two points, we can obtain the slope using only algebra.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find the <m>y</m>-value for which the slope of the line passing through <m>(6,-3)</m> and <m>(-9,y)</m> is <m>-\frac{2}{3}</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Substitute the given information into the slope formula.</p>

    <p>We have <m>m=-\frac{2}{3}</m> and we can let <m>(x_1,y_1)=(6,-3)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)=(-9,y)</m>.</p>

    <me>
    \begin{aligned}
        m\amp = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}\\
            -\frac{2}{3}\amp=\frac{y-(-3)}{-9-6}\\
            -\frac{2}{3}\amp=\frac{y+3}{-15}\\
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>After substituting in the given information, the only variable left is <m>y</m>.  Solve for <m>y</m>.</p>

    <me>
    \begin{aligned}
        \alert{-15}\left(-\frac{2}{3}\right)\amp = \alert{-15}\left(-\frac{y+3}{15}\right)\\
        10\amp = y+3\\
        7\amp = y
    \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The <m>y</m>-value which satisfies the conditions above is <m>y=7</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>


<p>There are four geometric cases for the value of the slope.</p>

<p> <image source="images/SlopeCases.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>Reading the graph from left to right, lines with an upward incline have positive slopes and lines with a downward incline have negative slopes. The other two cases involve horizontal and vertical lines. If <m>c</m> is a real number we have</p>

<md>
    <mrow>y\amp =c \text{ whose graph is a } \alert{\text{horizontal line.}}</mrow>
    <mrow>x\amp =c \text{ whose graph is a } \alert{\text{vertical line.}}</mrow>
</md>

<p> For example, if we graph <m>y=2</m> we obtain a horizontal line, and if we graph <m>x=-4</m> we obtain a vertical line.</p>

<p> <image source="images/Slope3.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<p>From the graphs we can determine two points and calculate the slope using the slope formula.</p>

<sidebyside>
<tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
    <row bottom="minor">
        <cell><em>Horizontal Line</em></cell>
        <cell><em>Vertical Line</em></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>Let <m>(x_1,y_1)=(-3,2)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)=(3,2)</m>.
            <md>
                <mrow>m\amp = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = \frac{2-(2)}{3-(-3)}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp=\frac{2-2}{3+3}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp =\frac{0}{6}=0</mrow>
            </md>
        </cell>
        <cell>Let <m>(x_1,y_1)=(-4,-1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)=(-4,1)</m>.
            <md>
                <mrow>m\amp = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = \frac{1-(-1)}{-4-(-4)}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp=\frac{1+1}{-4+4}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp =\frac{2}{0} \, \, \alert{\text{Undefined}}</mrow>
            </md>
        </cell>
    </row>
</tabular>
</sidebyside>

<p>Notice that the points on the horizontal line share the same <m>y</m>-values. Therefore, the rise is zero and hence the slope is zero. The points on the vertical line share the same <m>x</m>-values. Consequently, the run is zero, leading to an undefined slope. These give us the last two cases.</p>

<p> <image source="images/SlopeCases2.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

</subsection>
<subsection><title>Average Rate of Change</title>

<p>When a real world situation can be represented by a linear equation, the slope of the line is sometimes called the average <term>rate of change</term>. For example, suppose we graphed the distance (in miles) that a car drives over time (in hours). If the car drives at a consistent speed then it would form a straight line. The slope of this line would measure the average rate of change of the car's distance relative to time; in other words, the slope measures the speed of the car.</p>

<p>Consider the equation <m>C=4+2t</m> representing the cost of a movie rental in terms of the number of days of the rental. If we graph this equation, we can choose any two points on the line to compute its slope. For example, if we choose the points <m>(0,4)</m> and <m>(4,12)</m> then we have the following slope.</p>

<me>m=\frac{12-4}{4-0}=\frac{8}{4}=2</me>

<p>The slope of the line is <m>2</m>. In terms of renting a movie, our slope expression is telling us</p>

<me>
    \frac{\text{Change in Cost}}{\text{Change in Time}}=\frac{8 \text{ dollars}}{4 \text{ days}}\text{.}
</me>

<p>In other words, if we were to increase the length of the rental by <m>4</m> days, the cost of the rental increases by <m>8</m> dollars. The slope gives the rate of increase in the rental fee, <m>$2</m> per day. </p>

<p>In general, we say the slope of a line or equation measures the rate of change of the output variable with respect to the input variable. Depending on the units involved, this rate might be interpreted as a rate of growth or a rate of speed. A negative slope may represent a rate of decrease or a rate of consumption. The slope, or rate of change, of a graph can give us valuable information about the variables.</p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Nathan went hiking and took some trail mix. After hiking <m>2.5</m> miles he had eaten <m>3</m> ounces of trail mix. On average, how many ounces of trail mix did Nathan eat per mile?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>The amount of trail mix that Nathan has eaten depends on how far he has hiked. This tells us that the independent variable is the distance he has hiked, in miles, and the dependent variable is the ounces of trail mix. We are looking for the average rate of change of ounces of trail mix per mile.</p>

    <me>\frac{\text{change in ounces of trail mix}}{\text{change in miles climbed}}=\frac{3\text{ ounces}}{2.5\text{ miles}}=1.2 \text{ ounces per mile}</me>

    <p> This tells us that Nathan ate <m>1.2</m> ounces of trail mix per mile on his hike.</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<exercises>
<exercise>
    <title>The Slope Through Two Points</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/slope_through_pointsJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Slope from a Table</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/slope_from_tableJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Slope from a Graph</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/slope_from_graphJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Slope from a Graph</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/slope_from_graph_horizontalJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Slope from an Equation</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/slope_from_equation1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Slope from Salaries</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/salaryJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Drones</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/droneJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Population</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/The_Slope_of_a_Line/populationJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>


</exercises>




</section>




<section  xml:id="Forms-of-a-Line"><title>Forms of a Line</title>

<introduction>
<p>Up to this point, we have explored several properties of linear equations and their graphs, such as how to graph lines, finding the intercepts of lines, and finding the slope. In this section, we will now work backwards and write equations of lines given certain properties.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>learn two forms of linear equations: the <term>slope-intercept</term> form and the <term>point-slope</term> form</p></li>
        <li><p>write an equation for a linear equation given
            <ul>
                <li><p>the slope of a line and its <m>y</m>-intercept</p></li>
                <li><p>the slope of a line and any point on that line</p></li>
                <li><p>any two points on the line</p></li>
                <li><p>the graph of the equation</p></li>
            </ul>
        </p></li>
        <li><p>graph linear equations in point-slope and slope-intercept form</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
        <li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108187&amp;node=34303338&amp;a=62848992&amp;autoplay=1">Slope-Intercept and Point-Slope</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>
</introduction>

<subsection><title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>

<assemblage><title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>
<p>
    The form of a linear equation that you're probably most famililar with is called the <term>slope-intercept form</term>, which looks like <me>y=mx+b.</me> If a linear equation is in this form, then <m>m</m>, the coefficient in front of <m>x</m>, is the slope of the line, and <m>b</m>, the constant term, corresponds to the <m>y</m>-intercept of <m>(0,b)</m>.
</p>
</assemblage>

<p> For example, suppose we're given the linear equation <m>3x-4y=8</m>. Solving for <m>y</m>, we have</p>

<md>
    <mrow>3x-4y\amp =8</mrow>
    <mrow>-4y\amp = -3x+8</mrow>
    <mrow>y\amp =\frac{-3x+8}{-4}</mrow>
    <mrow>y\amp = \frac{-3x}{-4}+\frac{8}{-4}</mrow>
    <mrow>y\amp = \frac{3}{4}x-2\text{.}</mrow>
</md>

<p>From here, we can immediately see that the slope of this line is <m>\frac{3}{4}</m> and the <m>y</m>-intercept is at <m>(0,-2)</m>. With this information, we can easily graph this line: we can first plot the <m>y</m>-intercept at <m>(0,-2)</m>, and then use the slope to plot another point by going up <m>3</m> and over to the right <m>4</m>.</p>

<p> <image source="images/Slope4.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Put the linear equation <m>3y+5x=18</m> into slope-intercept form. Graph this equation, and identify the <m>x</m>-intercept.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To put this equation into slope-intercept form, we need to solve for <m>y</m>:</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        3y + 5x \amp= 18 \\
        3y \amp= -5x + 18 \\
        y \amp= -\frac{5}{3}x + 6
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>From here, we see that the slope is <m>-\frac{5}{3}</m> and the <m>y</m>-intercept is <m>(0,6)</m>. To graph this equation, we first plot the <m>y</m>-intercept. Using the fact that</p>

    <me>m=-\dfrac{5}{3}=\dfrac{-5}{3}=\dfrac{\text{rise}}{\text{run}},</me>

    <p>we can find another point by starting from the <m>y</m>-intercept and moving down <m>5</m> units and right <m>3</m> units. Drawing the line passing through these two points, we get the line for this equation.</p>

    <p> <image source="images/Slope6.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

    <p>To determine the <m>x</m>-intercept, we substitute <m>y=0</m>:</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        3(\alert{0}) + 5x \amp = 18 \\
        5x \amp= 18 \\
        x \amp= \frac{18}{5}
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Therefore, the <m>x</m>-intercept is <m>\left(\frac{18}{5},0\right)</m>. The general rule is to label all important points that cannot be clearly read from the graph.</p>

    <p> <image source="images/Slope7.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>
</solution>
</example>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Write a linear equation that defines the graph below, and find the <m>x</m>-intercept of the graph.</p>

    <p> <image source="images/Slope9.png"><description></description></image></p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>Consider the two points marked on the graph, <m>(0,3)</m> and <m>(3,1)</m>. From these points, we see that the slope is
        <me>m=\dfrac{\text{rise}}{\text{run}}=\dfrac{-2}{3}</me>
    In addition, the <m>y</m>-intercept is <m>(0, 3)</m> and thus <m>b=3.</m>Putting these together, we can write an equation in slope-intercept form:</p>
        <me>
            y=-\dfrac{2}{3}x+3
        </me>

    <p>To find the <m>x</m>-intercept of the graph, we substitute <m>y=0</m> and solve for <m>x</m>:</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \alert{0} \amp= -\dfrac{2}{3}x+3 \\
        \dfrac{2}{3}x \amp= 3 \\
        x \amp= 3\cdot\dfrac{3}{2} \\
        x\amp= \dfrac{9}{2}
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Thus the <m>x</m>-intercept is given by <m>\left(\frac{9}{2},0\right)</m>. </p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Point-Slope Form</title>

<p>The slope-intercept form of a line is perhaps the simplest form, but it has its limitations. For example, suppose we wanted to write an equation for the following line. </p>

<image source="images/point-slope-1.png" width="75%"><description></description></image>

<p>While we can certainly find the slope of this line, the <m>y</m>-intercept is not immediately clear. In cases like this where the <m>y</m>-intercept is not known, we can use the <term>point-slope form</term> of a line.</p>

<p>As the name suggests, point-slope form is useful when we know the slope and one point on a line. Suppose the slope of a line is <m>m</m> and we have a point <m>(x_1,y_1)</m>. Let <m>(x,y)</m> be a variable point. Then using the slope formula and rearranging, we have</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    m \amp= \dfrac{y-y_1}{x-x_1} \\
    m(x-x_1) \amp = y - y_1
    \end{aligned}
</me>

<p>Therefore, the equation of a line with a slope of <m>m</m> through the point <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> can be written in point-slope form:</p>
    <me>y-y_1=m(x-x_1)</me>
<p>Let's return to the graph above. On the graph, we can identify two points, <m>(-1,0)</m> and <m>(2,1)</m>. These two points give us a slope of <m>m=\frac{1}{3}</m>. Next, we can use either point to write an equation for this line. Using <m>(x_1,y_1)=(-1,0)</m>, we get an equation of <me>y-0=\dfrac{1}{3}(x-(-1))</me> Using <m>(x_1,y_1)=(2,1)</m>, we get <me>y-1=\dfrac{1}{3}(x-2)</me> It is not obvious that these are actually the same line; to verify this, we can simplify them both into slope-intercept form.</p>

<me>
    \begin{aligned}
    y-0 \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}(x-(-1)) \\
    y \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}(x+1) \\
    y \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}x+\dfrac{1}{3} \\
    \\
    y-1 \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}(x-2) \\
    y-1 \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}x - \dfrac{2}{3} \\
    y \amp= \dfrac{1}{3}x + \dfrac{1}{3}
    \end{aligned}
</me>

<assemblage><title>Point-Slope Form</title>
<p>
    The <term>point-slope form</term> looks like <me>y-y_1=m(x-x_1)</me> where <m>m</m> is the slope and <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> is any point on the line. Sometimes, it is helpful to rewrite the formula as
    <me>y=y_1+m(x-x_1).</me>
</p>
</assemblage>

<note><p>Unless a problem specifically instructs you too, it's not necessary to rearrage and simplify the equations into slope-intercept form. In the previous example, it was only done to verify that the equation does not depend on which point you choose.</p></note>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Write an equation for the line passing through the point <m>(3,6)</m> and <m>(-2,5)</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>First, we compute the slope:</p>
    <me>m=\dfrac{6-5}{3-(-2)}=\dfrac{1}{5}</me>
    <p>Next, we use either point to construct an equation in point-slope form. It does not matter which point we choose. Using <m>(3,6)</m>, we have</p>
    <me>y-6=\dfrac{1}{5}(x-3)</me>
</solution>
</example>

<example>
<statement>
<p>Write an equation that defines the following graph.</p>

<image source="images/point-slope-2.png" width="75%"><description></description></image>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>From the two marked points on the graph, we see that the slope is <me>m=\dfrac{\text{rise}}{\text{run}}=\dfrac{1}{6}</me> Next, we use either point to construct an equation in point-slope form. Using <m>(-4,-2)</m>, we have</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        y-(-2) \amp= \dfrac{1}{6}(x-(-4)) \\
        y+2 \amp= \dfrac{1}{6}(x+4)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
</solution>
</example>
</subsection>


<exercises>
<exercise>
    <title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/slope-and-intercept1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/slope-and-intercept2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Equation from a Graph</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_from_graph1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Equation from a Graph</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_from_graph2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Point-Slope Form</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_from_info1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Point-Slope Form</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_from_info2JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Line Through Points</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_through_points1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>The Line Through Points</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/equation_through_points1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Catering</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Forms_of_a_Line/cateringJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
</exercises>











</section>







<section  xml:id="Modeling-Linear-Equations"><title>Modeling Linear Equations</title>

<introduction>
<p>Up to this point, we have learned how to create graphs that reflect linear equations and how to construct linear equations given graphs. In this section, we will introduce two characteristics that pairs of lines can have so that we can continue to construct linear equations with various properties.</p>

<assemblage><title>In this section, you will...</title>
<p>
    <ul>
        <li><p>learn what it means for two lines to be <term>parallel</term></p></li>
        <li><p>learn what it means for two lines to be <term>perpendicular</term></p></li>
        <li><p>determine whether lines are parallel, perpendicular, or neither from their equations</p></li>
        <li><p>construct linear equations for lines with various properties</p></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>

<assemblage><title>Supplemental Videos</title>
<p>The main topics of this section are also presented in the following videos:
    <ul>
        <li><url href="https://unl.yuja.com/V/Video?v=7108190&amp;node=34303339&amp;a=181399847&amp;autoplay=1">Parallel vs Perpendicular vs Neither</url></li>
    </ul>
</p>
</assemblage>
</introduction>


<subsection><title>Parallel and Perpendicular Lines</title>

<p><term>Parallel lines</term> are lines in the same plane that never intersect. Two different lines in the same plane are parallel if their slopes are the same; in symbols, if the slope of the first line is <m>m_1</m> and the slope of a different line is <m>m_2</m>, then the slopes are parallel if <m>m_1=m_2</m>.</p>



<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find an equation of the line passing through <m>(4,1)</m> and parallel to <m>x-2y=-2</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To find the slope of the given line, solve for <m>y</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        x-2y\amp =-2\\
        -2y\amp = -x-2\\
        y\amp =\frac{-x-2}{-2}\\
        y\amp = \frac{-x}{-2}-\frac{2}{-2}\\
        y\amp =\frac{1}{2}x+1
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>Here the given line has slope <m>m_1=\frac{1}{2}</m>. The line we are constructing is parallel to this line and will therefore have the same slope, so <m>m_2=\frac{1}{2}</m>. Since we are given a point and we now have the slope, we will choose to use point-slope form of a linear equations to determine the slope-intercept form of the equation.</p>

    <p>Our point is <m>(4,1)</m> and our slope is <m>m=\frac{1}{2}</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        y-y_1 \amp= m(x-x_1) \\
        y-1 \amp= \dfrac{1}{2}(x-4)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The equation of the line is given by <m>y-1 = \dfrac{1}{2}(x-4)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>It is important to have a geometric understanding of this question. The line we were given, <m>x-2y=-2</m>, is shown in blue. The line we constructed, <m>y-1=\frac{1}{2}(x-4)</m>, is shown in magenta. notice that the slope is the same at the given line, but they are distinct lines (that is, they do not have the same <m>y</m>-intercept).</p>

<p> <image source="images/Modeling3.png"><description>Geometric Understanding</description></image></p>

<p><term>Perpendicular lines</term> are lines in the same plane that intersect at right angles (90 degrees). Two nonvertical lines, in the same plane with slopes <m>m_1</m> and <m>m_2</m>, are perpendicular if the product of their slopes is <m>-1</m>, <m>m_1\cdot m_2=-1</m>. We can solve for <m>m_1</m> and obtain <m>m_1=-\frac{1}{m_2}</m>. In this form, we see that perpendicular lines have slopes that are <term>opposite reciprocals</term>. In general, given non-zero real numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, if the slope of the first line is given by <m>m_1=\frac{a}{b}</m>, then the slope of the perpendicular line is <m>m_2=-\frac{b}{a}</m>.</p>

<p>For example, the opposite reciprocal of <m>m_1=-\frac{3}{5}</m> is <m>m_2=\frac{5}{3}</m>. We can verify that two slopes produce perpendicular lines if their product is <m>-1</m>.</p>

<md>
    <mrow>m_1\cdot m_2=-\frac{3}{5}\cdot\frac{5}{3}=-\frac{15}{15}=-1</mrow>
</md>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find an equation of the line passing through <m>(-5,-2)</m> and perpendicular to the graph of <m>x+4y=4</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To find the slope of the given line, solve for <m>y</m>.</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        x+4y\amp =4\\
        4y\amp = -x+4\\
        y\amp = \frac{-x+4}{4}\\
        y\amp = -\frac{x}{4}+\frac{4}{4}\\
        y\amp = -\frac{1}{4}x+1
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p>The given line has slope <m>m_1=-\frac{1}{4}</m>. Since we are constructing a line that is perpendicular to this line, their slopes should be opposite reciprocals, and thus the line we are constructing should have a slope of <m>m_2=+\frac{4}{1}=4</m>. Now we can substitute the slope, <m>m_2=4</m>, and the given point, <m>(-5,-2)</m>, into point-slope form:</p>

    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        y-y_1\amp =m(x-x_1)\\
        y-(-2)\amp = 4(x-(-5))\\
        y+2\amp = 4(x+5)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>

    <p> The equation of the perpendicular line is given by <m>y+2=4(x+5)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Geometrically, we see that the graph of <m>y=4x+18</m>, shown as the dashed line in the graph, passes through <m>(-5,-2)</m> and is perpendicular to the graph of <m>y=-\frac{1}{4}x+1</m>.</p>

<p> <image source="images/Modeling4.png"><description>Quadrants of the Plane</description></image></p>

<example>
<statement>
    <p>Find an equation of the line passing through <m>(-5,-1)</m> and perpendicular to <m>\frac{1}{3}x-\frac{1}{2}y=-2</m>.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
    <p>To find the slope of the given line, we solve for <m>y</m>:</p>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        \frac{1}{3}x-\frac{1}{2}y \amp= -2 \\
        6\left(\frac{1}{3}x-\frac{1}{2}y\right) \amp= 6(-2) \\
        2x - 3y \amp= -12 \\
        -3y \amp= -2x - 12 \\
        y \amp= \dfrac{2}{3}x + 4
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
    <p>The given line has slope <m>m_1=\frac{2}{3}</m>, therefore the line we are constructing must have a slope of <m>m_2=-\frac{3}{2}</m>. Using this and the point <m>(-5,-1)</m>, we can use point-slope form to write the following equation:</p>
    <me>
        \begin{aligned}
        y-(-1) \amp= -\frac{3}{2}(x-(-5)) \\
        y+1 \amp- -\frac{3}{2}(x+5)
        \end{aligned}
    </me>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>


<exercises>
<exercise>
    <title>Parellel, Perpendicular, or Neither?</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/multiple_choiceJustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Parellel, Perpendicular, or Neither?</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct1JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct4JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct5JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct6JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct7JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct8JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
<exercise>
    <title>Constructing Linear Equations</title>
    <webwork source="UNL-Problems/100A-Problems/Workbook/Modeling_Linear_Equations/construct9JustHint.pg" />
</exercise>
</exercises>




</section>
</chapter>








<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->
