<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2016 Katherine Yoshiwara
Copyright 2018 Nathan Wakefield, Taran Funk, Ariel Setniker, Karina Uhing


*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This just inserts a draft xml file     -->
<mathbook xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:lang="en-US">

<xi:include href="./ptx/bookinfo.xml" />   <!-- ISBN, website, other metadata -->

<book xml:id="Test">
       <title>Mathematics</title>
       <subtitle>PreCalculus Mathematics at Nebraska</subtitle>

       <xi:include href="./ptx/frontmatter.xml" />            <!--  Title Page, Preface, etc.  -->
       <part><title>Intermediate Algebra</title>
       <xi:include href="./ptx/IAchap1.xml" />        <!-- current chap  -->
       <xi:include href="./ptx/IAchap2.xml" />        <!-- current chap  -->
       <xi:include href="./ptx/IAchap3.xml" />        <!-- current chap  -->
       <xi:include href="./ptx/IAchap4.xml" />        <!-- current chap  -->
</part>


<part><title>College Algebra</title>
<chapter xml:id="chap-101-1"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
        <title>Functions and Their Graphs</title>
        <introduction>
            <sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="images/fig1.png"><description>Sunrise through tree: Martin Ruegner/Getty Images</description></image></sidebyside>
            <p>You may have heard that mathematics is the language of science.  In fact, professionals in nearly every discipline take advantage of mathematical methods to analyze data, identify trends, and predict the effects of change.  This process is called <term>mathematical modeling</term>.</p>  
            <p>A <term>model</term> is a simplified representation of reality that helps us understand a process or phenomenon.  Because it is a simplification, a model can never be completely accurate.  Instead, it should focus on those aspects of the real situation that will help us answer specific questions. Here is an example. </p>
            
            <p>The world's population is growing at different rates in different nations.  Many factors, including economic and social forces, influence the birth rate.  Is there a connection between birth rates and education levels?</p>  

            <p>The figure shows the birth rate plotted against the female literacy rate in 148 countries.  Although the data points do not all lie precisely on a line, we see a generally decreasing trend:  the higher the literacy rate, the lower the birth rate.  The <term>regression line</term> provides a model for this trend, and a tool for analyzing the data.</p>  

            <p>In this chapter we study the properties of linear models and some techniques for fitting a linear model to data.</p>
            
            <sidebyside width="80%"><image source="images/BirthRateVsFemaleLiteracy"><description>Plot of birth rate vs female literacy</description></image></sidebyside>
            
</introduction>
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-1P.xml" />             <!-- Introduction To Functions  -->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-2P.xml" />         <!-- Rates of Change-->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-3P.xml" />         <!-- Linear Functions-->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-4P.xml" />         <!-- Finding Linear Functions-->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-5P.xml" />         <!-- Comparing Linear Functions-->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-6P.xml" />             <!-- Function notation, Input and Output  -->
        <xi:include href="./ptx/section-1-7P.xml" />             <!-- Domain and Range  -->
</chapter> 


<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap2.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap3.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap4.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap5.xml"/>


<chapter xml:id="chap-101-6"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Quadratic Functions</title>
<introduction>
<sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="images/water-arcs.png"><description>water fountains, Justin Pumfrey/Getty Images</description></image></sidebyside>
<p>
    The models we have explored so far, namely, linear, exponential, and logarithmic are <term>monotonic</term> functions, that is, always increasing or always decreasing on their domains. (Remember that we used power functions as models in the first quadrant only.) In this chapter, we investigate problems where the output variable may change from increasing to decreasing, or vice versa. The simplest sort of function that models this behavior is a quadratic function, one that involves the square of the variable.
</p>
<p>
    Around 1600, Galileo began to study the motion of falling objects. He used a ball rolling down an inclined plane or ramp to slow down the motion. 
</p>
<sidebyside width="66%"><image source="images/fig-inclined-plane"><description>position of rolling ball marked on incline plane</description></image></sidebyside>

<sidebyside widths="55% 30%"><p>
    Galileo had no accurate way to measure time; clocks had not been invented yet. So he used water running into a jar to mark equal time intervals.
     After many trials, Galileo found that the ball traveled <m>1</m> unit of distance down the plane in the first time interval, <m>3</m> units in the second time interval, <m>5</m> units in the third time interval, and so on, as shown in the figure, with the distances increasing through odd units of distance as time went on. 
</p>

<table xml:id="table-inclined-plane"><caption></caption><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="major">
            <cell>Time</cell>
            <cell><line>Distance</line><line>traveled</line></cell>
            <cell><line>Total</line><line>distance</line></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
            <cell><m>3</m></cell>
            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>3</m></cell>
            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
            <cell><m>9</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
            <cell><m>7</m></cell>
            <cell><m>16</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
            <cell><m>9</m></cell>
            <cell><m>25</m></cell>
        </row>
    </tabular></table>
</sidebyside>

<sidebyside widths="50% 20%">
    
     <p>As you can see in <xref ref="table-inclined-plane" text="type-global"/>, the total distance traveled by the ball is proportional to the square of the time elapsed, <m>s = kt^2</m>. Galileo found that this relationship held no matter how steep he made the ramp. Plotting the height of the ball as a function of time, we obtain a portion of the graph of a quadratic function.</p>
    <p><image source="images/fig-inclined-plane-graph"><description>graph of ball rolling down inclined plane</description></image></p>
</sidebyside>

<p></p>

<investigation xml:id="investigation-height-of-baseball"><title>Height of a Baseball</title><statement>
    <p>
        Suppose a baseball player pops up, that is, hits the baseball straight up into the air. The height, <m>h</m>, of the baseball <m>t</m> seconds after it leaves the bat can be calculated using a formula from physics. This formula takes into account the initial speed of the ball (<m>64</m> feet per second) and its height when it was hit (<m>4</m> feet). The formula for the height of the ball (in feet) is
        <me>h = -16t^2 + 64t + 4</me>
    </p>
    <p><ol>
        <li><p>
            Evaluate the formula to complete the table of values for the height of the baseball.</p><sidebyside>
            <tabular top="minor" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
                <col right="major"/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/>
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell><m>t</m></cell>
            <cell><m>0</m></cell>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
            <cell><m>3</m></cell>
            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>h</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\hphantom{blank}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\hphantom{blank}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\hphantom{blank}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\hphantom{blank}</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\hphantom{blank}</m></cell>
         </row>
    </tabular></sidebyside>
        </li>
        <li><p>
            Graph the height of the baseball as a function of time. Plot data points from your table, then connect the points with a smooth curve.</p>
            <sidebyside width="30%"><image source="images/fig-grid-for-popup"><description>blank grid</description></image></sidebyside>
        </li>
        <li><p>
            What are the coordinates of the highest point on the graph? When does the baseball reach its maximum height, and what is that height?
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use the formula to find the height of the baseball after <m>\dfrac{1}{2}</m> second.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Check that your answer to part (4) corresponds to a point on your graph. Approximate from your graph another time at which the baseball is at the same height as your answer to part (4).
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use your graph to find two times when the baseball is at a height of <m>64</m> feet.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use your graph to approximate two times when the baseball is at a height of <m>20</m> feet. Then use the formula to find the actual heights at those times.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Suppose the catcher catches the baseball at a height of <m>4</m> feet, before it strikes the ground. At what time was the ball caught?
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use your calculator to make a table of values for the equation <m>h = -16t^2 + 64t + 4</m>
            with TblStart = <m>0</m> and <m>\Delta</m>Tbl <m>= 0.5</m>.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use your calculator to graph the equation for the height of the ball, with window settings
            \begin{align}
            \text{Xmin} \amp = 0, \amp\amp \text{Xmax} = 4.5, \amp\amp \text{Yscl} = 5\\
            \text{Ymin} \amp = 0, \amp\amp \text{Ymax} = 70, \amp\amp \text{Yscl} = 5
            \end{align}
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use the <em>intersect</em> command to verify your answer part (7): Estimate two times when the baseball is at a height of <m>20</m> feet.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            Use the <em>intersect</em> command to verify your answer to part (8): At what time was the ball caught if it was caught at a height of <m>4</m> feet?
        </p></li>
    </ol>
</p></statement></investigation>


</introduction>


    <xi:include href="./ptx/section-6-1P.xml" />  <!-- Intro to Quadratic Functions  -->
    <xi:include href="./ptx/section-6-2P.xml" />  <!-- The Vertex of a Parabola -->

</chapter> 



<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap7.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/101chap8.xml"/>





</part>
<part><title>College Trigonometry</title>
<chapter>

<title>Introduction to Trigonometry</title>



        <introduction>
<sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="imagesChap13/ocean.jpeg"><description>picture showing ocean waves</description></image></sidebyside>
<p>
The world is full of natural occurrences that repeat themselves in predictable, periodic ways. Sound waves, radio waves, AC electrical currents, seasonal temperature changes, and ocean tides are just a few examples of periodic phenomena which can be modeled by so called “trigonometric” functions.
</p>
<p>  In this chapter, we introduce periodic functions and the unit circle and explore connections between them.
</p>
            
        </introduction>





<xi:include href="./ptx/Section13.1.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section13.2.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section13.3.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section13.4.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section13.5.xml"/>

</chapter>

<chapter>
    
<title>Solving Trigonometric Equations</title>



        <introduction>
            <sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="imagesChap14/clouds.jpeg"><description>picture a cloudy sky</description></image></sidebyside>
<p>
Weather patterns often occur in a periodic fashion as the Earth revolves around the Sun.  
For example, the average daily temperature in a city typically looks like a trigonometric function.  
However, in this case the period of the function would be 365 days, not <m>2 \pi</m>.  
In order to model more complicate phenomena like average daily temperature we will need to make use of generalized trigonometric functions.
</p>
            
        </introduction>



<xi:include href="./ptx/Section14.1.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section14.2.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section14.3.xml"/>

</chapter>

<chapter>

<title>Applications of Trigonometry</title>


        <introduction>
            <sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="imagesChap15/moon.JPG"><description>picture showing the moon in the sky</description></image></sidebyside>
<p>
For thousands of years people have looked to the periodic nature of the phases of the moon.  Early civilizations based their entire calendar around these predictable phases.
</p>
<p>
In fact, the surface area of the moon that is illuminated can be modeled by trigonometric function.  If <m>\theta</m> is the angle formed between the sun, moon, and earth then the surface area of the moon that is illuminated is given by <m>\frac{1}{2} \pi 1080^2 \left(1+ \cos \theta \right).</m>
</p>
<p>
The above example is just one example of how trigonometry can be used.  Other examples include additional astronomy, navigation and even music.   In this chapter you will explore some of the tools used to apply trigonometry to the real world.  
</p>
            
        </introduction>


<xi:include href="./ptx/Section15.1.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section15.2.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section15.3.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section15.4.xml"/>
<xi:include href="./ptx/Section15.5.xml"/>

</chapter>
</part>



<!--       <xi:include href="./backmatter.xml" />   -->     <!--   GFDL, Hints, Notation  -->
    <!-- Index follows appendices, preceded only colophon -->
    <xi:include href="./ptx/backmatterP.xml" />       
    </book>
</mathbook>
