<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-12-E-exercises">

<title>Chapter 12 Exercises</title>


<!--comment here-->

<subsection><title>Section 12.1 Exercises</title>



		<p>1.	A company needs to deliver product to each of their 5 stores around the Dallas, TX area. Driving distances between the stores are shown below. Find a route for the driver to follow, returning to the distribution center in Fort Worth: (a) using the Nearest Neighbor algorithm starting in Fort Worth, and (b) using the Repeated Nearest Neighbor algorithm; (c) then implement the result from (b) beginning at Arlington.
		</p>

		<figure xml:id="Dallas-area-drive-times"><caption></caption>
				<image source="images/Dallas-area-drive-times.png" width="80%"/>
		</figure>

				<p>2. Apply the repeated nearest neighbor algorithm to the graph below to find a Hamilton circuit. After you find the circuit, implement it starting at vertex C. </p>

		<figure xml:id="Nearest-neighbor-K4-graph"><caption></caption>
				<image source="images/Nearest-neighbor-K4-graph.png" width="45%"/>
		</figure>




			<p>
				3.	When installing fiber optics, some companies will install a sonet ring; a full loop of cable connecting multiple locations. This is used so that if any part of the cable is damaged it does not interrupt service, since there is a second connection to the hub. A company has 5 buildings. Costs (in thousands of dollars) to lay cables between pairs of buildings are shown below. Find the circuit that will minimize cost: (a)	using Nearest Neighbor from building A, and (b) using Repeated Nearest Neighbor, then implemented beginning from building E.
				</p>

				<figure xml:id="fiber-optics-repeated-nearest-neighbor"><caption></caption>
	 				 <image source="images/fiber-optics-repeated-nearest-neighbor.png" width="60%"/>
	 		 </figure>

			 </subsection>

<subsection><title>Section 12.2 Exercises</title>

<p>  </p>

<p>4. Use the Cheapest Link (or sorted-edges) Algorithm on problem 1 above.  </p>
<p>5. Use the Cheapest Link (or sorted-edges) Algorithm on problem 2 above.  </p>
<p>6. Use the Cheapest Link (or sorted-edges) Algorithm on problem 3 above.  </p>
					<!--<sidebyside>
						<image source="images/nhood-diagram.png" width="45%"/>
						<image source="images/nhood-graph.png" width="45%"/>
					</sidebyside>

					<figure xml:id="easy-graph"><caption>Two representations of the same graph</caption>
					<sidebyside widths="30% 40%">
					<image source="images/easy-graph-square.png"/>
					<image source="images/easy-graph-triangle.png"/>
					</sidebyside>
				</figure> -->

</subsection>


</section>
